<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="40"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[THE MAGAZINE OF THE INTERNATIONAL CHILD ART FOUNDATION                             JULY – SEPTEMBER 2020]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[JULY – SEPT 2020



             Editor’s Letter




             A casualty of Covid-19 is the post-
             ponement of the 6th World Children’s

             Festival, which will now take place
             on July 30th–August 1st at The National
             Mall across from the U.S. Capitol.

             Art can be a powerful catalyst for
                                                                         Volume 20, Issue 1, Number 59
             cultural and social change. Art can
             also provide immediate benefits that
             result in better mental and physical                Editor/Publisher        Contributors
             health, especially during this pan-                 Ashfaq Ishaq, PhD       Ngozi Akande
             demic, hence this special issue on                  Assistant Editor        Maria Claudia Albini

             “Art for Health.”                                   Claire Bryan            Karen Alexander

             We are grateful to NEA Chairman Mary                Creative Director       Sara Beck, PhD
             Anne Carter for writing for ChildArt                Katie Verrant           Mary Anne Carter
             and we thank all other contributors. We                                     Gayathri J. Dowling, PhD

             are also grateful to those who have                 Designer                Sloka Ganne
             worked behind the scenes to make this               Shannon Smith
                                                                                         Katia Delrahim Howlett, PhD
             issue possible, in particular Frederick             Graphic Artist

             Marks, ICAF Board Member, and                                               Miriam Diane Lense, PhD
                                                                 Mimi Shang
             Sunil Iyengar, NEA Director of Research                                     Susan Magsamen
             and Analysis.                                       IT Director             Ssembiro Mike
                                                                 Melanie Lontsi          Che Sabalja, MA, MS
             While we rely on science to free us

             from Covid-19, art opens windows to                 Media Officer           D. Paul Schafer
             new vistas and can serve as a mirror                Maya Barnes Dholakia    Tracy L.F. Worley, DM, PMP
             for self-improvement.

             Sincerely,


                                                                 Next issue: ChildArt (Oct-Dec 2020) will be on the ABCD
                                                                 Study in collaboration with the National Institutes of Health
                                                                 and the National Endowment for the Arts


                                                                 COVER ART
             Ashfaq Ishaq Ph. D.                                 “The Camping Site” by Alina Ponomarenko, Age 11, Texas
                                                                 BACK COVER ART
             Chairman                                            “Gymnasts in Action” Aishling Kelly, Age 11, Arizona]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[ART FOR                                                                                                     01



         HEALTH                                                                                                      Jul–Sep 2020  |  https://icaf.org/












                  WHY ART FOR HEALTH                                                     02



           1      STATE OF THE ART


                 What Science Can Tell Us – Mary Anne Carter                             06

                 Teen Brains, Today’s Science, Brighter Future – Katia Delrahim          08
                 Howlett, PhD, MPP, MBA & Gayathri J. Dowling, PhD


           2     ARTS OLYMPIAD


                 “Designer” Sports Figures – Che Sabalja, MA, MS                         12
                 Art in Abuja – Ngozi Akande                                             16

                 Is Art a Waste of Time? – Maria Claudia Albini                          18

                 Fostering Children’s Creativity in Uganda – Mike Ssembiro               20
                 Colorful Emotions in Baku – Narmina Valiyeva                            22

                 Overland Park Arts Olympiad Winner – Sloka Ganne                        24



           3     FRESH PERSPECTIVES

                 Healthy, Happy with Art – Susan Magsamen & Karen Alexander              28

                 Now is the Time – Tracy L. F. Worley, DM, PMP                           30

                 How do Scientists Study Music? – Sara Beck, PhD & Miriam                32
                 Diane Lense, PhD

                 Why the Arts are Good for You! – D. Paul Schafer                        34


                  ART AND HEALTH RESOURCES                                               36]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[02         WHY


    ChildArt  |  Art for Health  ART FOR







              HEALTH









             We never dreamed we’d wear masks every             together, while maintaining our own health and
             day, wash our hands thoroughly at each turn,       safety. Whether it’s in the stories you tell, the
             or avoid meeting our friends instead of greet-     interactions you have with others, your night-
             ing them. These are surreal times, when the        time doodle, or in your curiosity for the world
             unimaginable becomes the daily reality. No         around you, creativity flows freely. Your sense
             hugs or handshakes. No playdates or outings.       of optimism will bring that creativity out in
             Zoom birthday parties. Will schools reopen         everyone else. You have to use all available
             this fall? What will I do if I test positive? These   tools to keep yourself busy learning every day

             are heavy questions for anyone to carry. How       and staying hopeful and inspired.
             can that weight be lessened in a world full of
                                                                This special issue of ChildArt opens with an
             question but few answers?
                                                                essay by Mary Anne Carter, Chairman of
             One pathway is art! Everyone has creativ-          the National Endowment for the Arts, on the
             ity inside of them and expressing that             importance of the arts for students’ cogni-

             is often a cathartic experience. Not only          tive development and academic performance.
             does partaking in the arts allow us to explore     A seminal neuroscientific study by the Nation-
             our own emotions and minds, but it also has        al Institutes of Health involving 12,000 students
             been proven to have a positive impact on our       over ten years which is outlined in this issue
             mental and physical health. Sharing and ex-        also attests to the value of the arts for brain
             ploring art with others is a great way to create   development.
             community and understanding, and luckily
                                                                This magazine’s second section is about U.S.
             during this time of limited social interation,
                                                                cultural diplomacy through the Arts Olympi-
             art is something we can all create and enjoy
                                                                ad—a free-of-charge school art program of]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[the International Child Art Foundation. You learn
         about the Arts Olympiad in a school in Long
         Island, New York, followed by the International
         Arts Olympiads in Nigeria, Argentina, Uganda,
         and Azerbaijan. You also get to meet the Arts
         Olympiad winner from Overland Park, Kansas,
         and see her Covid-19 artworks.


         The third section provides you diverse
         perspectives on the power of the arts to heal,
         inspire, and connect with others. You learn from
         the International Arts + Mind Lab at Johns Hop-
         kins School of Medicine, the author of a
         book titled “Art for Health,” two scientists at
         Randolph College in Virginia and the Vanderbilt
         University Medical Center in Tennessee, and
         finally, from an eminent cultural researcher in

         Toronto, Canada.

         Happy reading and creating!]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Michael Wong, Age 11, New York]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[1




                                           STATE  OF



                                           THE   ART

















                                               Let’s begin with our country’s two premier institutions,
                                               the National Endowment for the Arts and the Nation-
                                               al Institutes of Health. With its $162 million budget
                                               for 2020, the NEA strengthens America’s creative

                                               capacity by providing diverse opportunities for arts
                                               participation. The NIH will spend $41.7 billion on
                                               medical research in 2020 to turn discoveries into
                                               improved health for the nation.


                                               NEA Chairman Mary Anne Carter makes a compell-
                                               ing case for the arts and arts education for you. The
                                               NIH’s Dr. Howlett and Dr. Dowling introduce you to
                                               a seminal ten-year study involving 12,000 school-

                                               children, which will be groundbreaking in our under-
                                               standing of human cognitive development.]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[GROWING UP WITH THE ARTS:
   06


    ChildArt  |  Art for Health  What Science




             Can Tell Us








                The National Endowment for the Arts is a        childhood
             federal government agency. It awards grants        and youth.
             to support the arts and creativity around the      Here are
             country, in communities large and small. The       a few examples:
             agency is also the proud collaborator on a         •  In a study of “arts enrichment” programs
             large, groundbreaking study that we believe           in Head Start pre-schools in Philadelphia,

             will produce valuable findings about the impor-       West Chester University researchers found
             tance of the arts, creativity, and imagination        that economically disadvantaged children
             to children’s everyday lives.                         who learned in the arts showed lower lev-
                Led by our partners at the National Institutes     els of poverty-related stress, compared
             of Health, this study (called “ABCD” for short)       with similar groups of students who did not

             is collecting and analyzing data from thousands       receive arts programming. In previous stud-
             of children as they grow into teenagers and,          ies, the researchers have noted greater
             eventually, young adults. The study will              school readiness, vocabulary growth, and

             track the evolving brain structure of                 emotion regulation skills among arts-en-
             these children, their social and cogni-               riched preschool students.
             tive development, and their health and             •  In a George Mason University study of
             educational patterns.                                 more than 31,000 Miami children, children

                Because the study also will measure how            in 6th, 7th, and 8th grade who took an arts
             kids participate in arts and cultural activities, it    elective (music, dance, drama, or visual

             should be possible for researchers to under-          art) were shown to have higher GPAs and
             stand whether and how arts participation—over         math and reading scores than students who
             several years—affects this critical phase of          did not take these electives—even after
             childhood development.                                the researchers accounted for other fac-
                Through high-quality research that the             tors. Another study by researchers at Tex-
             Arts Endowment has supported elsewhere, we            as A&M University and the University
             already have many promising indicators about          of Missouri featured more than 10,500

             the potential benefits of arts participation in       elementary school students in Houston.]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[The researchers found that students who         through art, music, and storytelling.                    07
            took part in a local arts education initiative   The NEA Research Lab at Vanderbilt University
            had fewer disciplinary problems than stu-       Medical Center recently developed a “Home
            dents who did not participate. They also        Music Toolkit”—a research-based music curri-
            reported better scores in writing and in        culum that includes a video playlist of song             Jul–Sep 2020  |  https://icaf.org/
            “compassion for others,” as measured by         activities and suggested strategies for parents
            assessment tools.                               and children to interact with music at home.

         •  A National Endowment for the Arts study,        The Lab is currently studying the social and
                                                            emotional benefits of a music therapy program
            using several large databases at the U.S.
                                                            for children with and without autism spectrum
            Department of Education, revealed arts
                                                            disorder. (See pages 31 and 32)
            participation in elementary and high school
                                                               Music therapy and other “creative arts
            as positively linked with social and civic
                                                            therapies” have been widely adopted in a host
            engagement behaviors, such as voting
                                                            of care settings, often involving children and
            and volunteering.
                                                            youth. New research into music programs and
            Early data from the ABCD study
                                                            therapies—including treatments for children
         showed that 60 percent of children
                                                            and youth—is being funded by the National In-
         (ages 9 and 10) have participated in               stitutes of Health and the Arts Endowment. This
         at least one of the following art forms            research builds on an initiative called “Sound

         at some point in their lives: music,               Health,” a partnership with the John F. Kennedy
         dance, visual arts, drama, and crafts.   Center for the Performing Arts to promote the
         Fifty-one percent of all children had partici-     science of music for health and well-being. An

         pated in one of these art forms as recently        Arts Endowment Research Lab at Drexel Uni-
         as the last year. The Arts Endowment remains       versity, meanwhile, is studying the effects of
         interested in learning about and supporting the    art therapy in pediatric cancer care settings.
         whole range of arts activities and art forms       Throughout times of crisis, or in circumstances
         that occupy children and teenagers these           are more favorable, the arts offer relief, joy, and
         days—from attending arts events and creating       purpose to children everywhere. Science is
         art or music, to taking arts classes or engag-     just beginning to reveal how, why, and to what

         ing with the arts through technology. More         extent this is so.
         than three-fourths of the agency’s arts educa-
         tion projects (pre-K through 12th grade) serve
                                                                             Mary Anne Carter
         kids from underprivileged backgrounds.
            The COVID-19 pandemic has shown                                  Chairman of the
                                                                             National Endowment for the Arts
         many of us how in a time of protract-
         ed social isolation, anxiety, and uncer-
         tainty, people often can make the

         deepest connections with each other]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Teen Brains,
   08


    ChildArt  |  Art for Health  Today’s Science,






             Brighter Future








                The National Institutes of Health (NIH) is a   and shape a person’s
             government research agency whose goals are         future.
             to support studies to understand the body and         The ABCD Study

             behavior and to use that knowledge to improve   is big—almost 12,000
             health. One of the studies that the NIH sup-       kids. It started when
             ports is called the Adolescent Brain Cognitive     they were 9 to 10 years old, and it will run for
                          SM
             Development  (ABCD) Study.                         10 years until they are young adults. Partici-
                The ABCD Study will increase our                pants in this $400 million study will meet with
             understanding of how things like the               a local research team every year in-person to
             environment, social interactions,                  answer some questions about their experiences

             genetics and biology, and other factors            and to play games and puzzles that can tell the
             affect brain and childhood develop-                researchers about things like memory, atten-
                                                                tion, reasoning, and planning. Participants also
             ment. It is information that pediatricians,
                                                                provide specimens (such as saliva) for genetic
             teachers, counselors, and parents will be able
                                                                and other testing, and every participant has a
             to use to help you grow up as strong as pos-
                                                                safe non-invasive brain scan (MRI) session
                                              sible and
                                                                to obtain a clear picture of their brain every
                                              become a
                                                                other year.
                                              healthy adult.
                                                                   During the interviews, researchers are ask-
                                              It will also
                                                                ing kids like you and caregivers about their
                                              help policy-
                                                                family lives, friends, school, and extracurricular
                                              makers when
                                                                activities, how much they use different types
                                              making deci-
                                                                of screens, their sleep and exercise patterns,
                                              sions about
                                                                among other experiences. They are also look-
                                              laws that im-
                                                                ing at the effects of participating in artistic
                                              pact adoles-
                                                                activities like dance classes, learning how to
             A study participant preparing for MRI.  cent health
             ABCD Study®, Teen Brains. Today’s Science. Brighter Future.®, and the ABCD Study Logo are registered marks of the U.S. Depart-
             ment of Health & Human Services (HHS). Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development SM Study, is a service mark of HHS.]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[play a musical instrument, and other forms                                                                  09
         of self-expression.

         Science and Art

            If you think about it, science and research                                                              Jul–Sep 2020  |  https://icaf.org/
         have similar goals to art. They all are ways to
         explain and understand our surroundings
         and how they impact us. Artists like painters,
         sculptors, musicians, dancers, actors, or writ-

         ers use skills and imagination to explore their
         world and their lives. Scientists in the ABCD
         Study are using technology like brain scans,
         genetic testing, and puzzles to understand
         how life and learning experiences during teen
         years affect healthy development.                  ABCD Study® Participant-Katelynn M.
            For instance, the MRI scans will help the       and improving the lives not only in America but
         researchers tell whether the brains of             all over the world.

         kids taking art classes, participating                Together, with our government partners and
         in school plays or theater, or learning            the ABCD Study researchers and participants,
         a musical instrument develop any dif-              NIDA is excited to use today’s science to study
         ferently from those students who don’t             how involvement in the arts and other experi-

         participate in such activities. There is al-       ences can help shape brighter futures. Fittingly,
         ready evidence that arts participation has pos-    the National Endowment for the Arts is one of

         itive effects on children’s stress levels, reading   our partners in the study.
         ability, and brain development (see “Growing          More information about the ABCD Study, our
         Up With the Arts: What Science Can Tell Us”   partners and collaborators, and the data being
         in this issue). The scientists will also look at   collected can be found at ABCDStudy.org.
         whether these and other activities have effects
         on other aspects of your health, school perfor-                     Katia Delrahim Howlett, PhD,
         mance, and well-being.                                              MPP, MBA
                                                                             Deputy Director
            The ABCD Study and the data it is collect-
                                                                             Division of Extramural Research
         ing are a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity to help                    National Institute on Drug Abuse
         find answers to important questions about                           National Institutes of Health
         health and development during the second                            Gayathri J. Dowling, PhD
         decade of life. Researchers around the world                        Director
                                                                             Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development Project
         will be able to use the data collected by the
                                                                             Division of Extramural Research
         ABCD Study for many years to come, benefit-                         National Institute on Drug Abuse

         ting your generation and future generations                         National Institutes of Health]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Emily Levine, Age 11, California]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[2




                                           ARTS



                                           OLYMPIAD

















                                               The flagship program of the International Child Art
                                               Foundation, the Arts Olympiad, has grown since
                                               1997 into the world’s largest school art program.
                                               Through structured lesson plans that make connec-

                                               tions between mind and body, the Arts Olympiad
                                               inspires you to become an “artist-athlete” with a
                                               creative mind and healthy body. This revised
                                               self-image solidifies when you depict yourself as an

                                               art-
                                               ist-athlete playing your favorite sport.

                                               You will see how the Arts Olympiad is organized in
                                               a Long Island-New York school and internationally

                                               in Nigeria, Argentina, Uganda, and Azerbaijan. You
                                               will also meet an Arts Olympiad winner and view
                                               the “My Favorite Sport” artwork that serves both
                                               as mirrors and windows.]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[“Designer”
   12


    ChildArt  |  Art for Health  Sports Figures









                Not many art classes happen in one of the       attitudes by addressing the rising obesity
             last three room schoolhouses in the county.        crisis in the country. My students’ ideas
             Teaching art, in the hamlet of New Suffolk, Long    and creativity became part of a glob-
             Island, to 13 multi-grade elementary students      al exchange where they could

             took on the characteristics of a “family.” Meet-   see themselves sharing beyond their
             ing weekly with my 3rd-6th graders, I strived to   local community.
             create challenging learning opportunities that
                                                                   The artist-athlete ideal of the creative mind
             could encourage not only artistic expression
                                                                and healthy body permitted a constructive en-
             but active discussion and empathetic out-
                                                                try into self-image, lifestyle habits, and under-
             comes. The 6th Arts Olympiad created by ICAF
                                                                standing that being healthy is not only a physical
             offered the platform to accomplish these goals
                                                                activity, but integral to mental health, too. It was
             by embracing the “artist-athlete” concept,
                                                                important for students to see the interconnect-
             which connected societal reflection and healthy
                                                                                          edness between so-

                                                                                          cial wellness, art,
                                                                                          and sport, and con-
                                                                                          front the prominent
                                                                                          societal depiction of
                                                                                          the artist and athlete
                                                                                          as separate entities.
                                                                                          Society has always
                                                                                          had a penchant for
                                                                                          categories, but in

                                                                                          reality we need unity
                                                                                          and freedom to ex-
                                                                                          press and be our
                                                                                          best self.
                                                                                             As a class, we

                                                                                          talked about the
                                                                                          characteristics of the
                                                                                          artist and that of the
             Caroline Fannon]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[lesson framework incorporated color theory,              13
                                                            the science and art of using color, along with
                                                            the principles of art and the elements of de-
                                                            sign. The lesson framework incorporated color
                                                            theory, the science and art of using color, along        Jul–Sep 2020  |  https://icaf.org/
                                                            with the principles of art and the elements of
                                                            design. This provided a visual vocabulary from

                                                            which they could communicate their ideas.
                                                            To begin, students were asked to explore pho-
                                                            tos and videos of athletes on their laptop or
                                                            computer to help develop their own sports fig-
                                                            ures in action. To further understand the ana-
                                                            tomy of body and how it moves when in mo-
                                                            tion, they posed artist mannequins to replicate

                                                            movements during sports activities. Several
                                                            students physically recreated the poses around
                                                            the art table, sharing the fun with their class-
                                                            mates. Acting out the movements of

                                                            the athlete also created a deeper
         Lila Dailey
                                                            connection to the act of drawing the
         athlete, and how passion and effort provided
                                                            sports figures. The challenge of making
         the drive to push ourselves to reach goals that
                                                            the figures come to life became easier as
         could impact society as well. We discussed
                                                            students visualized the correlation.
         the shared aspirations of art and sports and
                                                               The entire composition addressed certain
         how this opportunity could deconstruct arbitrary
                                                            aspects of art and design. Focusing mainly
         categories that impede on a child’s psyche
                                                            on pattern, repetition, rhythm and movement,
         and self-esteem. The students spoke about
         times they too felt pressured to be or look a
         certain way by society at large. The topics con-
         tinued into the students’ own conversations.
         The students shared and exchanged ideas,
         viewpoints, stories, and memories.

            The art table buzzed with lively conversation
         and collaborative effort. Community was build-
         ing and overflowing into the artwork.
            Each student created a composition based
         on their favorite sport, or the one they admired,
         because not all of them took part in sports. The
                                                                                             Anna Szymzak]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[14        with line, color and space, students envision-     final outline with black sharpie to accentuate
             ed their sports figures connecting the concepts   the design, the students’ artwork not only

                                                                radiated with the vivacity of the sport,
    ChildArt  |  Art for Health  discussions.                   but captured their passion as well.
             and ideas that surfaced in previous art class
                Each of them chose a color scheme, multi-
                                                                   However, only one artwork from each school
             ple patterns, while demonstrating depth with
                                                                can be chosen for the Arts Olympiad. It was
             foreground, mid-ground, and background.
             Putting the lacrosse players in the foreground,    difficult to choose from the exciting array of
                                                                work. This was a teachable moment. Students
             mid-ground, and background led one student to      had the opportunity to be the art jurors in the
             remark how their art-                                                       selection process. The
             work looked more rea-                                                       Art Olympiad became
             listic. They were start-     For my art, I chose the sport                  our juried exhibition
             ing to really grasp the         tennis. My patterns are                     where the student art-

             visual vocabulary of
                                          geometric. My color scheme                     ists would present
             an artist.                                                                  their art to their class-
                                              is only black and white,
                Students then chal-                                                      mates as jurors.
                                            which gives the patterns
             lenged themselves to                                                           They learned how
             create patterns and              some ‘pop’. One of my                      to critique each other’s
             designs for the sports        characters just served the                    artwork based on
             figures and their re-          ball, and the other one is                   composition, origina-

             spective environment.
                                                about to hit it back.                    lity, theme, effort, and
             Using their imagin-                                                         clarity. We also talked
             ation and creativity                                                        about the larger con-
             they came up with several patterns and designs     cepts of subjectivity and objectivity and that
             that best emulated the action in their artwork.    jurors preference of what they like or dislike
             One student created a pattern of a heartbeat to    can come into play when selecting a work. The
             signify the racing heart of a soccer player.       students learned that it was important to value

                Students were excited to apply color theory  their own work and make a constructive argu-
             to create an energetic environment for their art-  ment on what makes their artwork special when
             istic composition based on color families that     developing the presentation. I asked the stu-
             we explored in an earlier lesson. Some of the      dents to offer a positive com-ment about each
             choices were complementary colors for strong-      other’s work and they replied twofold. Students
             er contrast or “pop” to enliven their sports       who already demonstrated confidence turned

             figures and cool or warm colors to evoke emo-  to encourage their classmates by highlighting
             tions. One student chose a black-and-white         their color choices, amazing designs, and in-
             color scheme to make his tennis players “pop”  tricate patterns!
             while another felt her cool colors depicted the       To break down the juror process, students
             concentration needed to play softball. After a     needed to think of an analogy to everyday]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[events they previously experience.                                                                          15
            Student examples, like trying out for a role
         in play or a position on team, receiving a gold
         medal in gymnastics at the Olympics, or get-
         ting a solo in choir, helped them gain a better                                                             Jul–Sep 2020  |  https://icaf.org/
         understanding of the juror selection process.

         Students gave a five-minute presentation to
         the jurors about creating their artwork. All
         student artwork was exhibited, and students
         carefully examined the work. Afterwards,
         anonymous ballots were handed out to write
         the name of a fellow student. It wasn’t easy to
         choose only one artwork from this vibrant and

         dynamic group of artists.
            However, once the ballots were counted
         with much enthusiasm, one student received
         the most votes from our student jurors for his
         bold black-and-white composition of two ten-
         nis players on the court. It was sixth-grader,
                                                                                          Henry Langmack
         Henry Langmack! Well done!

            Participating in the Arts Olympiad was the      their artistic voice was connected to a com-
         catalyst for my students to understand art as a    munity beyond their own. Our “Designer”
         holistic learning process where they were          Sports Figures opened a pathway towards
                                           able to          engagement in social practice with the stu-
                                           experiment,      dents realizing that their art and creativity

                                           create, and      can address issues and encourage change
                                           refine their     through collaborating with a bigger arena,
                                           ideas.           the world.
                                              Sharing
                                           and listening
                                                                             Che Sabalja, MA, MS
                                           to each oth-
                                                                             Art Educator
                                           er’s perspec-
                                           tives allowed
                                           them to grow
                                           and appre-
                                           ciate that
         Langmack at work developing his black-and-white design. His
         sports figures artwork was ultimately chosen by the class to par-
         ticipate in the 6th Worlds Children’s Festival, hosted by ICAF.]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[Art in
   16


    ChildArt  |  Art for Health  Abuja









                The Nigeria Art Olympiad is orga-
             nized by the Female Artists Associa-

             tion of Nigeria.
                In partnership with the Universal
             Basic Education Board (UBEB), pub-
             lic and private schools were invited
             to participate in the Arts Olympiad.
             The school entries were judged by
             a panel that included professional

             artists, art teachers, and UBEB staff
             members. After much deliberation,
             a total of ten finalists were selected.
             These ten finalists were invited to the
             Children Creativity Fair organized at
             the Nigerian Tulip College in Abuja on
             June 18–20, 2019. The ten students

             were asked to produce new artworks
                                                                                                  John Joseph
             on the Arts Olympiad theme “My Fav-
                                                                                                  Age 12, Nigeria
             orite Sport” so we could select the
             winner. This selection was unbiased by any         day event and arranged transport for the par-
                                                                ticipating schools. Students also received
             mentors or teachers that the student may
             have had.                                          gifts, such as school bags, and books
                The Children Creativity Fair was the first of   to encourage reading. In addition to the

             its kind and many schools were invited. This       award certificate given to each student, the
             event began with registration and art workshops,   winner, John Joseph, received a cash award
             and was followed by the “Unity for Peace”          as well from the UFUK Dialogue Foundation.
             essay writing contest on the second day. The          As a 12-year-old, John Joseph had moved
             third day consisted of cultural performances,      to Abuja when his hometown in the North East
             poetry reading, and the award ceremony. The        was attacked by the insurgents. He lives with
             UFUK Dialogue Foundation, one of the spon-         his brother at the IDP refugee camp and attends

             sors, provided refreshments during the three-      the Local Education Authority (LEA) school. He]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[does not plan to attend secondary school be-          The Nigerian delegation to the 6th World              17
         cause he cannot afford it.                         Children’s Festival in Washington, D.C. will in-
            We are impressed by his creative abilities      clude John Joseph, Judith Yahaya (the winner
         and potential. We arranged an art event on         of the previous Arts Olympiad), the Unity Dance
         December 26, 2019 to raise support for him.        Troupe, Joseph’s parent and/or headmistress,             Jul–Sep 2020  |  https://icaf.org/
         Joseph impressed everyone and                      ten members of the Female Artists Association
         secured funds for both his secondary               of Nigeria, one UBEB official, and a repre-
                                                            sent-ative of the UFUK Dialogue Foundation.
         education and university education.
         We thank Joseph’s supporters because through          The current COVID-19 pandemic has made
         education any child can break the cycle of pov-    it difficult to continue our sponsorship drive, we

         erty and become a productive citizen.              pray that the lockdown will soon be over so we
                                                            can all come together at the World Children’s
            We plan to organize the Children Creativity
                                                            Festival.
         Fair in partnership with UFUK Dialogue Found-
         ation every June based on the methodology of
         the World Children’s Festival.
                                                                             Ngozi Akande
            Our objective is to provide every Nigerian                       A prominent artist, president of the Female
         student an opportunity to showcase his or her                       Artists Association of Nigeria, and assistant
                                                                             director at the National Council for
         talents in the visual and performing arts and
                                                                             Arts & Culture.
         to employ the power of the arts for peace
         and prosperity.




































         Finalists of the the Nigerian Arts Olympiad were invited to attend the first Children’s Creativtiy Fair in Abuja, where they showcased
         various talents in the visual and performing arts.]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Is Art a
   18


    ChildArt  |  Art for Health  Waste of                       development mattered little to the students



                                                                and faculty at Escuela Argentina Modelo in
                                                                Buenos Aires.
             Time?                                              bilingual project (May–October 2019) for the
                                                                   The school developed an interdisciplinary



                                                                following areas of study: Literature (in English),
                                                                Leadership Skills lessons (in Spanish), Art,
             Not so in Buenos Aires                             Physical Education, and Information and Com-

                                                                                         munication Technol-
                In the closing years of the
                                                                                         ogies. On the first
             nineteenth century, Argen-
                                                      An artist is also an               day, we borrowed the
             tina was one of the world’s
                                                       actor, musician,                  theme from the 2016
             richest countries with the
                                                  dancer, or performer.                  Paralympics Games
             highest per capita income.
             Today, Argentina faces an                  So athletes are                  “We’re the Super-
             economic catastrophe, with                    also artists.                 humans!” to inspire

             more than 40 percent of its                                                 the students. They
                                                                                         were astonished to
             population falling under
             poverty. The government
             slashed funding for educa-
             tion, the Ministry of Culture
             was turned into an agency,
             but fortunately many scien-
             tists who had left for better
             opportunities overseas are

             coming back these days.
             What lingers are questions
             about the importance of the
             arts. Sadly but unsurpris-
             ingly, the National Arts Fund
             (Fondo Nacional de las
             Artes) did not support the

             Argentina Arts Olympiad.
                The lack of official inter-
             est in artistic and creative
                                                                                           Paula Doncel Cruz
                                                                                           Age 11, Argentina]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[was to instill values: empathy, solidarity, hum-         19
                                                            ility. The three Olympic values—friendship,
                                                            respect, and excellence—along with the four
                                                            Paralympic values—determination, inspiration,
                                                            courage, and equality—underpin the Games as              Jul–Sep 2020  |  https://icaf.org/
                                                            a set of universal principles, but the teachers
                                                            helped the students realize that they can also be

                                                            applied to education and their daily lives.
                                                               The class also discussed the concepts of
                                                            what makes a positive or a negative leader.
                                                            The students later depicted these values in
                                                            their artwork.

                                                               Through this dialogic process, the students
                                                            incorporated their ideas into larger, multi-voiced
                                                            classroom narratives. They began creating
                                                            meaning out of their own culture and life exper-
                                                            iences. They become active in their learning.

                                                               The students painted the flag (on the left)
                                                            to be displayed at the World Children’s Festi-
         Students at Escuela Argentina Modelo in Buenos Aires painted a   val. They were glad to participate in the Arts
         flag to be displayed at the World Children’s Festival.
                                                            Olympiad, which raised awareness of other
                                                            people’s realities and conditions, led to collab-
         see the videos from the event. “These people
                                                            orative artmaking, the sharing of experiences,
         are awesome. Some of them did not have
                                                            and a better understanding of each other
         arms or legs. Some could not see, but they
                                                            and their world.
         performed their best! I feel ashamed. Because
         I have everything in life. I am healthy, and I                                       María Clau-
         don’t do my best at school. I should change                                          dia Albini
         my attitude. I think that those people are                                           ICAF board member
                                                                                              and representative
         real artists.”
                                                                                              in Argentina
            Classroom discussions about dis-
         ability became a segue to a con-

         versation about art and empathy.
         Does empathy make one “simpático”, or is it
         something more? It is to put yourself in another
         person’s shoes. “But what does this have to

         do with art?” a student asked.
            The lesson plan’s most important aspect]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Fostering Children’s
   20


    ChildArt  |  Art for Health  Creativity in Uganda









                                                                         Ministry of Education and Sports.
                                                                         She told me, “This is a very good
                                                                         project. It is in line with the govern-
                                                                         ment initiative. It enriches our
                                                                         children with creative skills for

                                                                         work.” She pledged the Ministry’s
                                                                         support. The Ministry helped distri-
                                                                         bute the lesson plans to schools and
                                                                         communities in all districts of Uganda.
                                                                         More than 200 schools participated

                                                                         this year in the free-of-charge school
             Ahimbisibwe Mark Juniorr                                    art program. Each school selected
             Age 12, Uganda
                                                                         the two best art pieces on the theme,
                As the founder of Africa Peace Murals, a        “My Favorite Sport.” The works were mailed
             nonprofit for arts educators in Uganda, I have     to the regional offices of the Ministry and then
             had the opportunity to organize the Uganda         to the head office in Kampala. Everyone was
             Arts Olympiad since 2010. Over the past            amazed to see how wondrously the young art-
             decade, more than 10,000 students                  ists portrayed their favorite sports.

             have participated in the Uganda Arts                  Well-known artist-educators such as Kwesiga
             Olympiad which rewards their crea-

             tivity and gives them hope. At the 2011
             World Children’s Festival, the troupe from
             Uganda won the music award. The kids wore
             traditional Gomesi dresses made of barkcloth,
             and their cowrie shells and feathers to repre-
             sent Uganda’s indigenous cultures. When they
             performed at the festival’s “World Stage,” the

             gap between cultures dissipated.
                To organize the prestigious 6th Arts Olympiad,
             I requested a meeting with Dr. Turyagenda
                                                                                        Ayesigye Ianlee Jacob
             Kedrace at the Directorate Education Standards,                            Age 12, Uganda]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[to the school by              21
                                                                                       digging a well and
                                                                                       using solar panels.
                                                                                       She has organized
                                                                                       art workshops and             Jul–Sep 2020  |  https://icaf.org/
                                                                                       provided learning
                                                                                       materials that make
                                                                                       students more pas-

                                                                                       sionate about their
                                                                                       talents and more
                                                                                       hopeful for the future.
                                                                                          Uganda’s deleg-
         Students in schools and communities across Uganda participate in the Arts Olympiad.   ation to the 6th World

         David and Dembe Mary joined the panel of           Children’s Festival will be comprised of the
         judges. Thorough deliberations were necessary      Uganda Arts Olympiad winners and their teach-
         in order to select two winners from the large      ers, the organizing committee members, and a
         pool of unique art pieces that had been sub-       performance troupe. The world festival is not
         mitted. The winning works depicted original-       only arts-based but also an opportunity for a
         ity, creativity, and good composition.             science tour of the Smithsonian Museums, par-
            Every participating school received             ticularly the National Air and Space Museum.

         online printable certificates from the Interna-    The festival provides a platform for
         tional Child Art Foundation and the African        creative children to showcase their tal-
         Peace Murals. The winning artists will be invit-   ents and to learn STEAM disciplines in
         ed to the 6th World Children’s Festival            workshops and through hands-on activities.
         in Washington, D.C.                                Arranging funds for the travel of our large del-

            ICAF has become popular in Uganda for           egation is a major task that leaves me praying
         fostering students’ imagination and creativity.    every night. Big global corporations should
         I have seen the impact of the Arts Olympiad        help the world’s children come together at
         on my students at the Kasangula Talent School,   their World Children’s Festival so they can build
         which I founded to promote the talents of          a better world that will benefit their business
         rural kids through art, music, and sport. About    as well.
         250 students participated in the global Arts
         Olympiad which inspired them and improved
                                                                             Mike Ssembiro
         their academic performance.
                                                                             ICAF representative Uganda
            My school also receives support from ICAF
         board member, Wook Choi, who is based in
         New York City and runs Oogie Art. She led a
         team of volunteers to bring water and electricity]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[Colorful
   22


    ChildArt  |  Art for Health  Emotions                       art but the values of love, humanity, and com-

                                                                   I do not teach my students the secrets of


                                                                passion. Because one’s art is a mirror of the
             in Baku                                            mind, a beautiful mind creates beautiful art.

                                                                I answer their question, “Who am I?” so they
                                                                discover their true identity and can express

                                                                themselves on paper with confidence. One
                Beauty, kindness, and love can save             can start painting at 3, 30, or 90. What unites

             our world. This has been the motto of my           artists is their passion.
             personal and creative life and what guides me         My students have won dozens of interna-
             every day. During these dark times that have       tional art competitions and their works have

             surrounded our world, humanity needs more          been exhibited in many famous museums and
             love and kindness than ever before. I believe      art salons in France and Italy.
             that my young artists can bring new color and         My students also participate in social proj-
             light back to life.                                ects. We have participated in the Arts Olym-
                It is already ten years since I became the      piad and the World Children’s Festival held in

             head of the art studio, Colorful Emotions, in      Washington, D.C.
             Baku, Azerbaijan.                                     It is a big celebration for the nations of the
                                                                                          world because it
                                                                                          brings our future,
                                                                                          our children, to-
                                                                                          gether. The World
                                                                                          Children’s Festival is
                                                                                          a place where many
                                                                                          kids from differ-

                                                                                          ent countries gather
                                                                                          together and ex-
                                                                                          change their creative
                                                                                          works. My students
                                                                                          participate with
                                                                                          great anticipation
                                                                                          and excitement.

                                                                                              Every artist’s point
                                                                                          of view is important
             Leyli Musayeva
             Age 7, Azerbaijan]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[because each uniquely expresses ideas through                                                               23
         paints and brushes. We prepare variations of
         sketches on the Arts Olympiad theme, “My
         Favorite Sport”, and choose the most influen-
         tial compositions. Each Arts Olympiad cap-                                                                  Jul–Sep 2020  |  https://icaf.org/
         tures its moment in time and the concerns that
         children face.
            This year children were thinking that

         staying healthy is not just “me” or “you”
         because we should always try to protect our
         health and keep our forever home healthy as

         well. We are part of a bigger picture, what “me”                                  Sofiya Rasulova
         and “you” do will eventually affect everyone.                                     Age 13, Azerbaijan
         Being healthy is not only important regarding
                                                            orange fox is waiting for her somewhere. Chil-
         physical health, but we should also have a
                                                            dren never run out of ideas, and the next could
         healthy mind and a healthy soul. Just like we
                                                            be more vivid and real.
         clean our bodies every day, we should also
                                                               Adults can learn from them. My students’
         clean away any dirty or useless thoughts be-
                                                            ideas inspire me in my work as an artist. I feel
         cause what is inside will eventually make its
                                                            like a child again, living in a fairytale where eve-
         way outside.
                                                            ry moment is magical.
            Children have different personalities,
                                                               Fifty Azeri kids are planning to participate
         dreams, goals, and backgrounds this is why
                                                            in the 6th World Children’s Festival at Amer-
         their paintings vary a lot from each other. Some
                                                            ica’s National Mall. I plan to organize a mural
         love to be strong and their art captures their
                                                            making project at the festival: “Let’s believe
         strength and complements it in some way.
                                                            in fairytales to save the world.” During these
         Some are empathic and their works por-
                                                            chaotic times, I wish that our world will recover
         tray more loving scenarios. Take the case of
                                                            as soon as possible. When the world heals,
         7-year-old Leyli Musayeva, who says,
                                                            every community will also heal. “Dear world
                                                            we love you a lot, please forgive us!”

                 I believe in miracles

                and I wish that we will                                      Narmina Valiyeva
              save the world one day.                                        Head of “Colorful Emotions” art studio, mem-
                                                                             ber of the Azerbaijan Artists Union and the
                                                                             Europe Women Artists Association, and ICAF
                                                                             board member.
            The 13-year-old student Zahra Mammadova
         sees herself as the “Little Prince” who thinks an]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Overland Park Arts
   24


    ChildArt  |  Art for Health  Olympiad Winner









             It’s not every day that you get
             to have your artwork published
             in an international magazine

             or get selected as a delegate
             from Kansas to the 2021 World
             Children’s Festival. I feel excit-
             ed thinking about the festival,
             meeting all the different peo-
             ple from around the world, and
             seeing what talents they have.

             My passion for art has existed

             for as long as I can remem-
             ber. When I was two, I started
             to draw on cups and walls
             because I thought that they
             needed a dash of creativity. I used to draw        This is a tough year for everyone because of
             piggy noses onto the bottom of the cups and        the pandemic. So, I also painted a piece to
             put them over my mouth. In kindergarten,           represent this time. For the future, I don’t have
             I made a caterpillar out of paper circles and      any plans, but I dream of having a house with
             other items. In first grade, I drew a cat stand-   a big yard and a big garden, open to all ani-

             ing on buildings, and to add color, I took col-    mals. I could be the “neighborhood vet,” tak-
             ored tissue and layered it wherever the build-     ing care of animals. I could become a radio-
             ings were.                                         logist who draws in her free time and is also
                                                                the neighborhood vet.
             In third grade, I drew lizard eyes and it was
             displayed at the Blue Valley District Office. In
             fourth grade, I drew Vincent Van Gogh, pump-                       Sloka Ganne
             kins, and birch trees. This year (fifth grade),                    Age 10, Kansas, USA
             I painted my favorite sport—chess—for the

             Arts Olympiad school art program. Chess is
             my new hobby and I play with my family.]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[25














                                                                                                                     Jul–Sep 2020  |  https://icaf.org/





























































         SLOKA’S COVID-19 ARTWORK]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[Nicola Roos, Age 11, South Africa]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[3



                                           FRESH




                                           PERSPECTIVES

















                                               You have learned about the importance of the arts
                                               from the NEA, the NIH, and the ICAF. How about
                                               perspectives of others? Susan Magsamen and
                                               Karen Alexander inform you about their findings at

                                               the International Arts + Mind Lab at Johns Hopkins
                                               School of Medicine in Baltimore. Dr. Worley, based
                                               in Edgewood, Maryland, suggests some activities
                                               for you from her recent book, Art for Health.


                                               Professor Beck of Randolph College in Lynchburg,
                                               Virginia and Dr. Lense of the Vanderbilt Universi-
                                               ty Medical Center in Nashville, Tennessee explain
                                               their research on the impact of music.


                                               Finally, D. Paul Schafer, founder of the World Cul-
                                               ture Project and an ICAF Board Member based in
                                               Toronto, Canada, explains why we must move from
                                               the economic age to a cultural age for sustainable

                                               prosperity and harmony.]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[Healthy,
   28


    ChildArt  |  Art for Health  Happy






             with Art








             Have you ever noticed how looking
             at or making art can affect how you feel? For      exposure to the arts creates connections be-
             example, you might feel happy when you             tween different areas of the brain.

             sing your favorite song or calm when view-
                                                                Art is magical, but it’s not magic.
             ing a painting of a peaceful scene.
                                                                    It’s a neurological product,
             We are constantly interacting with the world
                                                                        and we can study this
             around us. Our five main senses—hearing,
                                                                 neurological product the same
             sight, touch, smell and taste—are working
                                                                    way we study other complex
             all the time. Science is now revealing that
             there are at least 21 additional senses, such         processes such as language.
             as our senses of balance and movement,                  – Dr. Charles Limb, euroscientist

              that help bring in the world around us.
                                                                   The brain is made up of many chemical sub-
                                                                stances including neurotransmitters, which
                                                                pass information from one cell to another. These
                                                                chemical messengers help the brain regulate
             Art and Your Brain
                                                                our emotions.  For example, the neurotrans-
                Scientists have learned that our brains re-     mitter dopamine helps control the brain’s sys-
             spond differently to different types of sen-sory   tems that make us feel pleasure and a sense
             experiences. They have developed new tools         of accomplishment. Researchers have found

             to look inside and map the brain.                  that dopamine levels increase when we view
                You may have heard that art only uses           or create art.
             either the right or left side of your brain. This     When you draw a picture, hear a song, or
             is not true!                                       write a poem, your brain is receiving and pro-

                The two sides of the brain are connected        cessing information and creating new pathways.
             through the corpus callosum. Brain research-       This is called neuroplasticity, which keeps your
             ers are beginning to better understand that        brain growing and healthy.]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[How Making Art Can Help You                        You Can Help Others                                      29
                                                            Through Art, Too
            Dance helps build and strengthen your brain
         connections and can make you feel happier. Play-      By making art for others, you can provide
         ing an instrument improves memory. Drawing,        them with many of the benefits described above.

         painting, or crafting helps build the fine motor      When a family member or friend feels over-            Jul–Sep 2020  |  https://icaf.org/
         skills needed to do things like writing and grasp-   whelmed, they can look at a drawing or paint-
         ing small objects.                                 ing that you created to help reduce their stress.
            Scientists discovered that drawing forces          When you make art, you can personalize it:
         your brain and body to process information in      for example, you could write a poem or a song

         multiple ways. Creating art helps us learn to      dedicated to a family member or friend. This
         take risks and solve problems. Being able to       can help the recipient feel honored.
         think creatively and handle difficult problems
                                                               Creating art with another person can help
         are important skills that can help you feel less
                                                            strengthen your bond with them. For example,
         stressed by school assignments.
                                                            dancing and listening to music with others can
            Scientists have found that some types of        help us feel closer to our friends. Friends or
         arts experiences can help lower levels of the      family members who make or experience art

         “stress hormone,” cortisol, in the body. These     together will likely feel closer than those who
         processes can also serve as a type of med-         do not.
         itation, which involves training your mind to
                                                               Your art can also help people in your com-
         increase awareness, emphasizes accepting
                                                            munity—for example, you could use chalk to
         feelings and thoughts without judgment, and
                                                            draw pictures on the sidewalk to make people
         helps your body and mind relax.
                                                            in your neighborhood feel happy. Another way
            Have you ever found it difficult to share your    is to make a drawing or painting for your teach-
         feelings or thoughts with another person? Art can    ers to show that you appreciate their hard work.
         help us express our thoughts and emotions with-    Can you think of other ways that your art could
         out using words. Being able to more fully express    help the people in your community?
         yourself can also reduce stress and anxiety.


               I found I could say things                                    Susan Magsamen
                 with color and shapes                                       Executive Director
                                                                             International Arts + Mind Lab
                 that I couldn’t say any                                     Brain Science Institute
                other way—things I had                                       Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine

                       no words for.                                         Karen Alexander

                 – Georgia O’Keeffe, painter                                 Director Education and Outreach
                                                                             International Arts + Mind Lab
                                                                             Brain Science Institute
            For all of these reasons, arts are as essential to               Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine
         our health as exercise, good nutrition, and sleep.]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[Now is
   30


    ChildArt  |  Art for Health  the Time









             In this time of crisis, when students
             and their families are locked down

             all over the world, many things are
             uncertain. Is it safe to see friends?
             Can you go to the ball game? Will
             schools re-open this fall? Understand-

             ably, you are anxious and don’t quite
             know what to do. It almost seems                      ONE
             as if the world is in a stage of transi
             tion—from how it used to be, to how                   Quiet time. Take some time to think about

             it will be in the future. Now, more                the talents you have and document them—in
             than ever, an opportunity exists for               your Android or Apple memo app or on a sheet
             you to change for the better. Some                 of paper. Once you’ve nailed down your list,
             people may be wondering how young                  number the item twice. The first numbering is
                                                                to prioritize them by skill-level, from your best
             people can take advantage of this
                                                                talent (#1) to the talent you feel is maybe your
             time outside the classroom, stuck at
                                                                least practiced or strong. Once you’ve priori-
             home without much to do.
                                                                tized the list according to skill level, number the
             Here’s the challenge: How can                      list again according to how much you enjoy

             you work your talent and open                      each, with #1 being what you enjoy most.
             new doors to learning to help                         When you’ve done both lists, compare
             yourself and others?                               them. What are your number one talents for
                                                                skill and enjoyment? Are they the same for
                                                                each? If so, this may be the talent you focus

                                                                most of your energies on. But here’s a caveat:
                                                                all your talents are valuable, regardless of how
                                                                good you are or how much you enjoy them.
                                                                You want to spend some quiet time to deter-
                                                                mine how you want to do your art.]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[TWO                                            build expertise. Exercise your mind and your             31
                                                            body by using your talents, creating new art-
            You’ve selected the talent or talents you want    work, and honing your skills.
         to explore. Now it’s time to hone your
         craft. Work at it. Practice makes perfect, right?     THREE                                                 Jul–Sep 2020  |  https://icaf.org/

         Absolutely! If you are a vocalist or musician, ex-
         plore different types of music and try copying        You’ve selected the talents you want to ex-
         the styles. Sing alone or with your siblings. Write   plore, and you’ve begun to create within that
         a song and perform it for your parents. Singing    artistic discipline. The most important next step
         exercises your vocal cords and writing lyrics or  is to remain engaged in your art. Seek
         music exercises your mind                          opportunities to share your talent—online show-

            If you are a visual artist, explore styles of   cases, writing competitions, other contests.
         sketch, chalk, and paint. Express your feelings
         about being confined and out of school during
         the pandemic on paper and canvas. Expressing
         yourself through your artform can relieve stress,
         reduce anxiety, and give you an outlet for shar-   Now is your time to stretch yourselves men-
         ing your feelings about this crisis.               tally and physically by pursuing artistic en-

            Do you love to dance? Turn on the music         deavors that will stimulate your creativity and
         and have at it! Feel the beat and just let go.     could lead to better results in school and
         Dancing can provide release by exercising the      your life. The arts give you a voice, a crea-
         physical body. Explore movement and create         tive declaration that will allow you to express
         a dance that expresses your feelings. Choreo-      yourself and better yourself. Learn to express
                                             graph your     yourself in writing. Begin to think critically

                                             story! Share  about ideas and meaning. Learn to articulate
                                             your talent    meaning in your artistic discipline.
                                             by perform-
                                             ing it for     Now is the time! Are you ready?
                                             your family.   Let’s do it!
                                                Creating
                                             a space for
                                                                             Tracy L.F. Worley,
                                             your talent
                                                                             DM, PMP
                                             gives you
                                             an outlet for
                                             your emo-
                                             tions and al-
         Learn more about how the arts can benefit   lows you to
         one’s mental and physical health in Dr. Worley’s
         book, Art for Health.]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[How do Scientists
   32


    ChildArt  |  Art for Health  Study Music?









                Have you ever gotten just a few words of           These are just
             a song or musical phrase stuck in your head?       a few things that
             Music psychologists call this “involuntary         are being studied at

             musical imagery” or sometimes “ear-worms.”         the intersection of
             Some studies find that more than 90% of us         music, psychology,
             experience ear-worms at least once a week!         neuroscience, edu-
                Did you know that choral singing can in-        cation, and health.
             crease life-satisfaction and feelings of well-     This broad, inter-
             being? Scientists are exploring the mechanisms     disciplinary field of
             that might be at play; it could be that feeling    study is often called

             like you belong to a group is part of the magic.   Music Cognition,
             Moving together to the same musical beat           and it encompasses
             certainly plays a role.                            research scientists
                The term music encompasses more than            from many disciplines interested in how music
             you might think, extending all the way to spo-     is processed in the brain as well as how our

             ken language. Researcher Diana Deutsch was         thoughts, feelings, and behaviors are affected
             the first music psychologist to show that the      by music.
             line between speech and song is thin and that it      In our music cognition research, we study
             depends on repetition. Our speech is in-           how music supports social activities in parents
             trinsically rhythmic and melodic, and if we        and children. Music activities provide opportun-
             place a sequence of several words on a “loop”      ities for parents and children to share attention,
             we find that our brain now processes the input     imitate each other, and regulate their emotions,
             as a song instead of speech.                       all of which are important for child development.

                Diana Deutsch calls this “the speech-to-        Our research uses many different methods
             song-illusion.” It may seem like nothing           such as looking at brain activity when people
             more than a party trick, but it tells us some-     listen to music and how people move when
             thing important about sound. All sounds            they make music together. We apply findings
             can be musical, and repetition and                 of our experimental studies to music therapy
             rhythm are key to transforming                     programs through our National Endowment for
             sound into music.                                  the Arts (NEA) Research Lab program. If you
                                                                like to make music with a younger sibling or]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[when babysitting, you can use our Music               Music is a powerful trigger for reminding             33
         Home Toolkit for ideas of ways to play musical        people of events from their own life (called
         games together.                                       autobiographical memories). Most fre-
                                                               quently, people have increased memory for
         How can you experiment with music
                                                               events that occurred in their teens and               Jul–Sep 2020  |  https://icaf.org/
         like a music scientist?
                                                               early adulthood. In a study with college stu-
         •  Music moves us. Most of us—about                   dents, researcher Carol Krumhansl found

            95%—find music rewarding just like other           that the students not only had increased
            pleasurable stimuli such as food, intimacy,        memories associated with songs from
            and social interaction. The reward circuitry       their teenage years but also from when their
            in our brains responds even more strong-           parents were that age! This might be be-
            ly to music that is familiar to us, whether        cause these are the songs their parents
            we like it or not. Have you ever noticed that      played to them when they were growing

            sometimes a song will grow on you after            up. Try listening to songs from the Bill-
            hearing it a certain number of times? Pick         board charts from different years. Do you
            a song you’ve never heard before, and try          most recognize songs you listen to now
            listening to it once every day at the same         as a teenager and also songs from when
            time of day and recording how much you             your parents were teenagers? Do you have
            like it on a scale of 1 to 7. How does your        memories associated with these songs?
            preference change over time?                       Play the songs for your parents. Do your

         •  Some sport psychologists have shown                parents most frequently recognize and
                                                               have memories of songs from when they
            that listening to very up-tempo or fast
                                                               were teenagers?
            songs improves exercise performance
            and reduces perceived exertion, making

            you feel like you didn’t work as hard as
                                                                                Sara Beck, PhD
            you did, but other researchers suggest                              Assistant Professor of Psychology
            the effect only holds at low to medium                              Randolph College
            intensity workouts. Find a few songs with
            tempos of about 130 beats per minute
            (some examples include: Run-DMC, “It’s                              Miriam Lense, PhD
            Tricky”; Maroon 5, “Moves Like Jagger,”                             Assistant Professor of Otolaryngology
                                                                                Co-Director, Music Cognition Lab
            and Destiny’s Child, “Survivor”) and try
                                                                                Vanderbilt University Medical Center
            listening to them when you exercise.
         •  Does the music make your workout

            feel easier? Does the music make more
            or less of a difference if you are pushing
            yourself or just going through the motions?]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[Why the Arts are
   34


    ChildArt  |  Art for Health  Good for You!









                Let’s start with a bit of history. A British    cerned with
             novelist and physical chemist, C. P. Snow pub-  “the basics
             lished a book in 1959 titled, “The Two Cultures   of life”, while

             and the Scientific Revolution”. Snow made the      soft activi-
             case that intellectual life in the western world   ties like the
             was divided into two cultures—the artistic-hu-     arts and
             manistic culture and the scientific culture.       humanities
                Snow felt this was a real hindrance in          were about
             coming to grips with the world’s most difficult    “the frills in life.”
             problems at that time because the artistic-hu-        In the years to follow, art educators had to
             manistic culture was given too much attention      justify programs not only for their ability to

             and the scientific culture too little attention in    teach students to play musical instruments,
             western countries. Snow made such a power-  paint pictures, act in plays, dance, write, and
             ful case for giving much more attention to the     prepare people generally for enjoying the arts
             science education that a shift began to occur   later in life, but also for their ability to address
             away from the arts, humanities, and an artistic-   important social and cultural concerns and to
             humanistic education.                              stimulate people’s creativity.

                It wasn’t long after this that the sciences        The image of the educated person that is
             were treated as “hard subjects” and the arts       promoted and entrenched in today’s economic
             and humanities as “soft subjects.” This was        age is based on the concept of “economic man”
             accompanied by an increase in funding for          or “economic personality” concerned largely
             the sciences and a decrease in funding for         with the production and consumption of goods
             the arts. Since science was linked to econom-      and services and creation of material and mon-
             ics, politics, industry, and technology, policy-   etary wealth in order to keep economies func-
             makers thought that this was the key to            tioning effectively and growing at a rapid rate.

             solving the world’s most pressing and urgent       The problem with this image is that it is not
             problems.                                          compatible with the “global citizens” needed
                The “Snow thesis” eventually became a           if we are to be successful in coming to grips
             societal phenomenon and not just an edu-           with the life-threatening challenges that exist
             cational phenomenon. Hard activities such as       throughout the world today.

             economics, industry, and science were con-            The economic age is not only having a]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[ality”—people who are holistic, centered, crea-          35
                                                            tive, altruistic, and humane. This is necessary
                                                            to achieve more happiness, fulfilment, and
                                                            spirituality in life, as well as live in harmony with
                                                            the natural environment and other people.                Jul–Sep 2020  |  https://icaf.org/
                                                               It is also required to develop new worldviews,

                                                            value systems, mindsets, and modes of behavior
                                                            from the ones that exist today, as well as
                                                            different skills, abilities, and assets if people
                                                            are to function effectively in a cultural age,
                                                            and this age is to provide an effective
                                                            context for arts education and other

                                                            disciplines in the future.
                                                               Ironically, science today shows the impor-
                                                            tance of the arts. Scientific research confirms
                                                            that music provides “a total workout for the
                                                            brain” because music stimulates blood flow,
         Jamie Barill                                       and all other organs and faculties. It also
         Age 10, Canada                                     reduces blood pressure and relieves pain, im-

         devastating effect on the natural environment      proves sleep, increases motivation and men-
         and producing colossal inequalities in income      tal awareness, and enhances memory. Scien-
         and wealth, but also it is not capable of com-     tific research has also confirmed that paintings
         ing to grips with the world pandemics and          enhance many brain functions by having an

         conflicts that arise as a result of the interaction   impact on brain wave patterns and emotions,
         and intermingling of people, groups, races,        the nervous system, and increased serotonin
         cultures, and religions with very different world-   levels, as well as neural systems that yield a
         views, values, traditions, customs, beliefs,       broad range of additional benefits such as
         and ways of life.                                  motor skills, creativity, and improved emotion-
            The time has come to pass out of                al harmony.
         the economic age and into a cultural

         age. Not only would a cultural age provide
                                                                             D. Paul Schafer
         a more effective means for dealing with to-                         Founder and director of the World Culture
         day’s local and global problems, but it                             Project www3.sympatico.ca/dpaulschafer
                                                                             and an ICAF board member
         would also provide a much better context
         for developing, both in arts education, and in
         a general context.
            The image of the educated person needs
         to be “the whole person” or “cultural person-]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[36         ART AND HEALTH


    ChildArt  |  Art for Health  RESOURCES

















             For you

             Grow your interest in music with this!
             http://serenademusicclass.org/home-toolkit

             Don’t know how to draw? No worries!
             https://apps.apple.com/us/app/doodletv/
             id1505985805

             Share your art and express yourself?
             Register for the National PTA Reflections
             Program. https://www.pta.org/home/
             programs/reflections
             Get invited as “Official Delegate” to the
             2021 World Children’s Festival by
             participating in this free Arts Olympiad.
             https://ICAF.org/ArtsOlympiad







                                                                                            Katharina Jellema
                                                                                            Age 9, Germany]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[37














                                                                                                                     Jul–Sep 2020  |  https://icaf.org/


                                                                                           Ksenia Butenko

         For your parents and                                                              Age 12, Ukraine
         teachers too!

         The medical healing power of the arts during       Learn how to be an effective leader during
         Covid-19. https://arts.ufl.edu/in-the-loop/news/   Covid-19. https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/
         can-the-arts-help-stop-covid-19/                   doi/toc/10.1002/(ISSN)1531-5355.crisis-
                                                            leadership
         Learn about neuroaesthetics and how the arts im-
         pact your brain. https://www.artsandmindlab.org/   Learn about transferring art education
                                                            for shelter in place audiences. https://
         See the Arts Education Partnership list of
                                                            nationalguild.org/covid-19-response/
         resources. https://www.aep-arts.org/covid-19-
                                                            transitioning-arts-programming
         resources/
                                                            Meet the author of “The Healing Power of
         Arts Ed Collab has curated art resources
                                                            Human Connection in a Sometimes Lonely
         for educators. https://artsedcollab.org/covid-
                                                            World”. https://aspeninst.zoom.us/webinar/
         19-resources/
                                                            register/WN_8YjuVfYeTuC0n4L5QE6A7w
         The Los Angeles Department of Cultural
         Affairs’ list for art instruction and experiences
         during social distancing. https://culturela.
         org/programs-and-initiatives/arts-resources-
         during-covid-19-2/
















         Leyli Musayeva, age 7, Azerbaijan (see full artwork on p.22, ‘Colorful Emotions in Baku’)]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[Aishling Kelly, Age 11, Arizona







                                                        Participate in the free 6th Arts Olympiad. https://ICAF.org
                                                        Support the 2021 celebration of “Creativity, Diversity, and Unity.”
                                                        https://WorldChildrensFestival.org
                                                        Subscribe online to ChildArt magazine ($30 annually) at
                                                        https://ICAF.org/ChildArt
                                                        Post comments or visit us at www.facebook.com/ICAF.org
                    Please mail your
                    donation check to:
                                           Incorporated in 1997 in the District of Columbia as a 501(c)(3) nonprofit, the International
                    ICAF                   Child Art Foundation serves American children as their national arts organization to foster
                    P. O. Box 58133        their creativity and develop mutual empathy between them and with their peers
                    Washington, DC 20037   worldwide through the universal language of art.]]></page></pages></Search>