<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="42"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[October–December 2016                                             The Magazine of the International Child Art Foundation













































































       LEARNING FROM DESIGN!]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[EDITOR'S CORNER










        The primary purpose of the 2016 Fall   We welcome your open minds to explore
        Issue of ChildArt Magazine, “Learning   ways to engage the learning process
        From Design!” is to engage you and   using the transformative concepts
        your teachers and parents in compelling   set forth – to see through the eyes of
        topics about the discipline of design   budding young creative problem-solvers.
        – along with inspiring you to become   Eight amazing designers responded to
        confident and creative problem-     tough interview questions as visionaries,
        solvers, act as purposeful makers, take   innovators, and creative problem-solvers.
        ownership of your learning, and make   They shared personal stories about
        mindful choices.                    who has influenced them, their greatest
                                            accomplishments, significant challenges
        For more than 20 years, the International                               “My mom was the art director for the
        Child Art Foundation (ICAF) has engaged   they have faced, and offered sage advice   Mr. Rogers’ Neighborhood show; she
        hundreds of thousands of children   for young 21st century creative problem-  created a safe place for us to invent at
        from all over the world in the arts and   solvers! We also heard from remarkable   home; supplies were at the ready without
        creativity. The ICAF strives to enhance   design educators along with ICAF’s   any expectation on what we should make.”
        the academic performance of young   design competition updates.         –Megan Neese, Senior Manager at the
        global citizens by way of creativity,   Here are some highlights of what you    Future Lab, Renault-Nissan Alliance.
        empathy, and 21st century leadership   will find in this issue:
        skills. The ICAF’s goal is to empower                                   “Young creative problem-solvers can
        each child’s imagination to see the   “After that, no project, no matter how big   benefit from diving into opportunities
        possibilities of productive change –   or difficult scared me. I learned I could    to learn how to work alongside others.”
        to infuse their minds with the power   do anything, as long as I did not know    –John Edson, President at LUNAR Design.
        of critical thinking with the intent to   that I did not know how to do it.”
        innovate better futures. This quarterly   –Arnold Wasserman, Principal at the   Our very best wishes to you all,
        publication also serves as a resource   Collective Invention.
        for educators around the globe to assist   “Young creative problem-solvers should
        with curriculum development for learners   not just use digital devices; rather learn
        ages 10-14. With each edition, ChildArt   by rolling up their sleeves and creating
        aims to foster young people’s capacities   things with their own hands as well.”    Doris Wells-Papanek, M.Ed
        to grow their creative imaginations and   –Mauro Porcini, Chief Design Officer    Design Learning Network, Director
        global competencies.                at PepsiCo.                         Guest Editor












                                             Editor and Publisher   Editorial Assistant
                                             Ashfaq Ishaq, Ph.D.   Maya Campbell

                                             Guest Editor       Graphic Designer
        OCT-DEC 2016 / Vol 16, Issue 4, Number 48  Doris Wells-Papanek, M.Ed.   Aurora Colón


        ChildArt quarterly magazine, published   Managing Editor   Graphics Assistant   All rights reserved. Reproduction of the whole or
        since 1998, is a commercial-free arts   Linda Macri     Tracey Silcox   any part of the contents without written permission
                                                                                is prohibited. ChildArt (ISSN 1096-9020). Copyright
        learning, self-discovery, and global    Assistant Editor                2016 International Child Art Foundation. Printed in
        education periodical.                John Koniszewski                   the United States of America.]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[TABLE OF CONTENTS











            INTERVIEWS

            06      Arnold Wasserman
                        & Peter Scupelli                                          ICAF NEWS

            10       Mauro Porcini                                                40    Adobe Certiport Awards

                                                                                  41     Young Lions Competition
            16       John Edson                ARTICLES
            20     Debbie Millman
                                               04    Welcome to Learning
            24     Megan Neese                           From  Design!

            30     Ayse Birsel                 14     Look Around You.
                                                         Design is Everywhere!
            34     Paul Hatch
                                               28    Seeing By Doing
                                               38    A Design-Based
                                                         Game Challenge







        DEAR YOUNG CREATIVE
                                  PROBLEM-SOLVERS,








        As Guest Editor of the 2016 Fall Issue   You will read stories about designing the   Our goal is for you to learn how to
        ChildArt Magazine – it is with great   future, the powerful influence of mentors,   become a courageous and creative
        excitement that I invite you to join us   and the incredible benefits of being   problem-solver, to use your own hands
        in this opportunity to wonder, wish,   curious, resilient, and persistent. You   to bring your ideas to life, to become
        and learn from some of the greatest   will engage in the thrill of design-based   passionate about what you learn, and,
        designers and educators in the world!   learning challenges, ways to visualize,   most of all, to make good choices!
        In these pages, you can learn how to   construct, and articulate what you see
        become a creative problem solver. Use   in your imagination, as well as explore   With our very best wishes to you as
        the contents of this magazine as your   passionate pathways to design the life   you learn and grow,
        stepping-stone into never-ending insights   you love. You will dive into learning as   Ms. Doris
        that will help you navigate whatever   a way to empathize with the struggles
        comes your way. Learning how to think   of others as well as your own, redesign   doris@designlearning.us
        and act as a creative problem-solver can   ways you learn at school, and embrace
        empower you, help you face any problem   reading as a way to gain phenomenal
        or situation while at school and beyond.   courage.]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[WELCOME TO
                          LEARNING FROM DESIGN!







                                                                             by Doris Wells-Papanek


               Welcome to Learning From Design!   really well for students, teachers,   guidance and then lets you work
               Throughout the making of this   and parents.                  through a challenge.  When you
               publication, I experienced the   Diving Deep into             use creative thinking and problem-
               rare privilege of interviewing top   Creative Problem-Solving   solving skills in strategic ways to
               designers from all over the world                             gather information, define a problem
               and interacting with some of the   In 2008, a researcher named John   to solve, build understandings, and
               best design-based educators in the   Hattie, from the University of   show new understandings, you
               nation. As the Director of the Design   Melbourne in Australia, was trying   are taking responsibility for your
               Learning Network, I find myself   to figure out the most effective   learning. Also, it is super important to
               continuously engaged in learning   ways to teach young people. He   reflect and assess your own progress
                                                                             throughout the learning process as
               how to learn and forever curious   learned that, when kids engage
               about why things work they way   in creative thinking, it is far more   well as offer feedback to your teacher.
                                                                             Huge benefits arise from diving deep
               they do. I heard similar ideas in my   effective to ask kids to be problem   and being flexible – especially when
               interviews with the other authors   solvers than just to give them   collaborating with schoolmates.
                                              creative activities to work on. He
               in this issue: they were curious   learned that this approach better
               and excited about understanding   prepares your mind to process and   Here are a few questions to help
               and making sense of our rapidly   retain new information, especially   keep you on track when you are
               changing world.                when you engage in hands-on and   working to solve a problem:
                                                                             How might you define the problem
                                              minds-on activities. He also learned
         ChildArt | October–December 2016  learning organizations all over   effects in core subject areas such   How will you identify, prioritize, and
               The Design Learning Network is
                                                                             (or determine the cause)?
                                              that these methods have positive
               dedicated to collaborating with
                                              as math, science, and reading.
               the world. Our goal is to engage
                                                                             select alternatives for your solutions?
               students like you; kids who are
                                              It will not surprise you that you
                                                                             How might you take into account
               motivated to learn as creative
                                              are most likely to learn new things
                                                                             multiple perspectives, empathize
               problem-solvers. As a network
                                              when you can connect what you are
                                                                             to uncover unknown issues?
               of educators, learners, creatives,
                                              learning with content that matters
                                              productive when, rather than telling
               Design Learning Process to create
                                                                             sketches to represent your new
                                              you what to do, your teacher offers
                                                                             understandings?
               experiences that we know will work
        4      and decision-makers, we use the   to you. Likewise, you are more   How might you use diagrams and]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[combination of the first and second   what you have in mind. You lay the
                                              worlds, to create your own sense   blanket under a tree; then set out a
                                              of reality. Being aware of your own   big bag of popcorn and some grapes
                                              world is the key to showing others   for everyone to share. Once you
                                              what you know, how you think and   sense your friends are a bit more
                                              feel. The technical name for this   relaxed you bring out the game; you
                                              cognitive process is visual-spatial   hope it will take everyone’s mind
                                              reasoning; it describes your ability   into a different place. Success, your
                                              to think, construct new ideas in your   friend’s dog is excited! What do you
                                              mind’s eye, and then problem-solve   think is going to happen next in the
                                              before you share those ideas with   story and why?
                                              others.
                                                                             Now that you are somewhat familiar
                                              Imagine you are out riding your bike.   with how visual-spatial reasoning
               How might you make the most of   You see two friends, a tree, and   works, it is time to explore a few
               collaborating with your peers?  a dog: this is your physical world,   examples as if you were a creative
               How might you go about creating   the things you recognize on the   problem-solver in action.
               a plan of action to implement your   surface. You know that one of your   Think back to when you were 7
               solution?                      friends has been away for a while,   years old, learning how to make
                                              but you are not sure why she looks
               If you are in a position to implement   sad, and you also notice that your   sense of time. How might you
               your ideas, what might that look like?   other friend has a very serious look   create a flipbook to illustrate how

               How will you know if your decisions   on his face: this is your world of   you could redesign “time” when it
                                                                             felt too slow or too fast to be just
               are actually solving the problem?  deeper understanding. After a bit   right?
                                              of thought, you decide you want to
               Design Learning Strategies     try to help your friends feel better,   Envision what life might be like
               Empower Kids to Tackle         though you are not quite sure how   in the year 2050. Given shifts in
               Wicked Problems                to do that yet. This is your world of   technology, what kind of jobs might
                                              creating your own sense of reality.   be available then compared to now?
               Below is a bit of learning science
               behind something called visual-  To address the situation, you begin   Visualize redesigning one of the
               spatial reasoning, followed by a   by visualizing in your mind various   characters in a book you are reading
               short story.                   ways you could cheer them up.   in your language arts class. What
                                              Finally, you come up with a plan!   if you became that person, what
               Did you know that three worlds of   You quickly go back home, collect
               learning come together in your brain                          would you do differently?
               when mind’s eye constructs new   a few things like a yummy snack,   These types of creative
                                              a blanket, and a fun game you just
               ideas, problem-solves, and then                               challenges can indeed play an
               communicates with others?      learned with your dog. Whew, your   important role in your education,
                                              friends are still on the block when
               The first world is physical, the   you return! You greet them with a   experiences that will stick with
               stuff that you see around you; the   big smile and ask if they would like   you for the rest of your life. To
               second world goes deeper into   to hangout for a while. They see   learn more about the Design
               your understandings of the physical   that you have brought along a few   Learning Network, please visit
               stuff that you see; the third is a   things, and become curious about   www.designlearning.us




                                                        As Director of the Design Learning   Curriculum and Instruction Design
                                                        Network, Doris Wells-Papanek, M.Ed.   with a focus on Action Research
                                                        collaborates with educators, learners,  from National Louis University
                                                        creatives, and decision-makers to   and a bachelor’s in Product and
                                                        develop creative problem-solving   Environmental Design from the    ICAF.org
                                                        design-based learning experiences.   Kansas City Art Institute and
                                                        Doris holds a master's degree in   School of Design.    5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Arnold Wasserman is Principal

                                                              of Collective Invention and
                                                              San Francisco Chairman of

                                                              The Idea Factory in Singapore.
                                                              Arnold is an innovation and
                                                              strategy consultant; named

                                                              a “Master of Design” by
                                                              Fast Company magazine.


                                                       ARNOLD






                           WASSERMAN





                                                      & PETER






                                                  SCUPELLI








                                                              Peter Scupelli is Assistant

                                                              Professor, Chair of the
                                                              Environments Track,

                                                              and Director of the Learning
         ChildArt | October–December 2016                     Mellon University. Peter holds
                                                              Environments Lab in the
                                                              School of Design at Carnegie



                                                              a Ph.D. in Human Computer
                                                              Interaction, Masters of Design

                                                              in Interaction Design, and



        6                                                     an Architecture degree.]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[My name is Arnold Wasserman,   Peter: My mom is the one who
               and I am an industrial designer.   had the greatest impact on me.
               From my earliest years, I drew and   My brothers and I did art projects
               painted. My first masterpiece was   with her every day at home. On
               a spinach puree mural on the wall   weekends, she would take us to
               next to my high chair. I read a lot   see art museums. She wanted us
               and learned to draw by copying   to experience incredible things. She
               comic books – my ambition was to   encouraged us to participate in art
               be a comic book artist. Art was a   contests. At one point, we were
               required subject at the schools in   living in Paraguay, and it was such
               my small Pennsylvania Dutch farm   a small school that she volunteered
               town. I got a full tuition scholarship   to become the art teacher. I loved
               to Carnegie Mellon University (CMU)   Leonardo Da Vinci; she took me   They were not worried
               to study painting, then switched   to see his drawings in museums.
               majors and graduated from CMU   As a kid, I wanted to become an   about where it might
               with a bachelor’s degree in Industrial   inventor. My dad is an engineer; my   lead, they wanted me
               Design in 1956. After service in   mom was an anthropologist, but   just to pursue my
               the U.S. Army and working in the   she loved to paint. Between the two
               design field, I went to the University   of them, they got me started going   interests and reach
               of Chicago and graduated in 1966   down the design path. They were not   my full potential.
               with a Master’s degree in History &   worried about where it might lead;
               Theory of Design.              they wanted me just to pursue my
                                              interests and reach my full potential.
               My name is Peter Scupelli, and I
               am an assistant design professor   Arnold: The key person in my life
               at Carnegie Melon University.   was Professor Robert Lepper, head   about deeply analyzing the creative
               My father was a civil engineer   of the industrial design department   process itself. Lepper’s heuristic
               who built hydroelectric dams   at CMU. From Lepper, I learned   thinking informed everything that
               around the world. I had lived in   not just technical skills but habits   I have done since.
               the US, Italy, Brazil, Paraguay, and   of mind that shaped the rest of
               Thailand before I graduated from   my life – specifically a mode of   Peter:  My heroes were people
               high school. I studied architecture   self-reflection he called “heuristic”   like Leonardo da Vinci and
               at the University of Genoa in Italy.   thinking (investigative). He cared   Michelangelo because to them
               With classmates, we founded an   less whether your solution was   art, architecture, design, science,
               architecture collective called Gruppo   original, beautiful, or technically   engineering, poetry, sculpture,
               A12. We explored the boundaries   clever – he wanted to know whether   and music were all connected. My
               between architecture and art   you understood the process you   greatest accomplishment has been,
               through collaborations with new   followed to get there. The design   in this very specialized world of
               media artists. I became interested   problems he gave were very open   deep expertise, to integrate design
               in how spatial environments    and general, and there was no
               and information environments   right answer to the question: “what
               come together to support human   does he want?” At class critiques,
               experience. Next, I studied    you would put up your work and
               Interaction Design at Carnegie   then he would lead you to examine
               Mellon University in 2002 then   the assumptions, explorations,
               went on to do my doctoral studies   and choices that led you to your
               in Human-Computer Interaction. I   solution. This approach to teaching
               now teach in the School of Design   drove some of his students a bit
               at Carnegie Mellon University. I love   nutty. Artists and designers tend                         ICAF.org
               teaching design and doing research.   to care more about the result than
                                                                                                                7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[across specialized disciplines. Such   everybody from the top down –   structural beams that were stolen –
               projects are very collaborative in   the Ministry of Education, school   and then find a steam-driven sawmill
               nature. As to collaboration, I think   principals, teachers, administrators,   to cut the trees to size. I had to go to
               all this work is “anthological” design   and students – how to think   the bazaar to find approximations of
               (collection of works); it depends   about learning the way designers   lost bolts, brackets, and paint. The
               on lots of precursors, mentors,   think about design projects. We   rest I had to improvise. The pavilion
               teachers, advisors, and partners   embedded design-based learning   opened on schedule and was a big
               collaborating all the time. It is a   and design thinking in the new DNA   success. After that, no project, no
               mix of relevant knowledge for the   of Singapore education, creating   matter how big or difficult scared
               problem at hand.               a gene pool of entrepreneurs and   me. I learned I could do anything, as
                                              innovators.                    long as I did not know that I did not
               Arnold: Peter makes a crucial point                           know how to do it.
               for both students and educators. In   Arnold:  At age 23, my first big
               creative pursuits like art and design,   project out of school was to design   Peter:  The biggest challenge that
               there persists this romanticist   the U.S. national pavilion and 32   I have faced so far is this work that
               fantasy of the solitary creator.   exhibits for the Izmir, Turkey trade   I have been doing with Arnold -
               However, creative work, in reality,   fair of 1957 - then go for three and   figuring out how to teach students a
               is deeply collaborative. Educators   a half months to Izmir to supervise   new kind of design we call Futures
               need to construct their curricula,   construction. In Izmir, everything   Dexign, which integrates Future
               pedagogy, and assessment to give   went wrong. Ten percent of the   Thinking with Design Thinking.
               students early experience with   construction materials were stolen   We taught the first Dexign the
               collaborative creativity.      between the ports of New York   Future course together in 2013.
                                              and Izmir. The building site, shown   Based on what worked and did
               My greatest accomplishment was   as flat in the plans I had worked   not work in that course I designed
               working on redesigning the city-state   from, was actually hilly, with a big   two courses. First, Introduction to
               of Singapore, helping them shift   electrical distribution box right   Dexign the Future that focused more
         ChildArt | October–December 2016  innovation, and entrepreneurship   and learn how to use them to   required of all undergraduate design
               their economy from an export and
                                              where the pavilion was supposed to
                                                                             on methods, and second, a new
               execution economy to a creation,
                                                                             course called Dexign Futures that is
                                              go. I had to find survey instruments
               economy. We started by redesigning
                                              resurvey the site.
                                                                             students in their third year.
               their education system to shift
                                              I had to redraw all the plans, working
               from analytical problem solving
                                              under a tent, sweat pouring onto
               to creative exploration, innovation
                                              my drawings in 102-degree heat.
               and entrepreneurship and to build
               to navigate change. We taught
                                              trees cut down to replace the big
        8      the resilience of Singapore’s youth   I had to find straight trees, get the]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Arnold: The Dexign Futures course   2. The second technique is trying   Arnold: What Peter describes here
               Peter describes is very much a   to explain your idea through   is what my mentor Robert Lepper
               “Practice Research” project. The   prototypes:                would call the heuristics of his
               course requires students discover a     – Share your prototype with a   pedagogy. We were teaching those
               principle or process by constructing   friend or someone else  same heuristics in Singapore. In
               something calculated to explore or                            our exponential digital age, life
               test it in practice in the real world.     – Listen very carefully to the   depends not only on critical thinking
               I call it “building the airplane while   questions they ask   and problem solving but also on
               you are flying it.”                 – Where are they confused?   adaptive creativity innovation,
                                                  Which things were not clear?  communication, collaboration and
               Peter:  To learn how to learn in the                          mental resilience. The best way to
               21st century, I teach my students     – Write down the questions they   develop these capacities is through
               three techniques:                  asked                      experiential design-based learning.
                                                   – Make sure you understand what
               1. Many design students believe that   they are saying – ask clarifying   Subject matter knowledge and
                 they are going first to think of the   questions            technical expertise may get you your
                 perfect idea, and then execute it.                          first job. Exceeding your limitations
                 To break this habit, the first thing     – Do not try to answer their   and resilience will get you a career.
                 that I try to teach students is:   questions                Self-reflection will get you a life.
                    – Get your thoughts out of your     – Try to take a deep
                   head so you can see it and     understanding of what are they
                   share it                       asking, why are they asking it
                    – Get it on a wall, or on paper,   3. Then the last technique is to
                   make a drawing, use post-its  revise your ideas to address all
                    – Sketch it out on a whiteboard,   of the questions, confusions, or
                   get it out so you can recognize   concerns that came up – so you
                   patterns                     can start reiterating (repeating the
                                                process) on the next version.
                    – See how things connect –                                                                   ICAF.org
                   understand what it is that you
                   are trying to think                                                                          9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[MAURO







                                             PORCINI








         ChildArt | October–December 2016  Mauro Porcini, as PepsiCo’s first ever Chief Design Officer,


               is responsible for leading innovation by design across the
               company’s food and beverage portfolio, extending from
               physical to virtual expressions of the brands, including
               product, packaging, events, retail activation, architecture,





       10      and digital media.]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Being a good
                                                                                and knowledgeable
                                                                                person with culture

                                                                                    has always been
                                                                                            my dream.





                                                                             and reading – how to apply
                                                                             theoretical thinking. My love for
                                                                             design, to be creative, to transform
                                                                             things with strategy, reflect and
                                                                             understand rational connections
                                                                             – all came from my mother. My
                                                                             parents were humble, simple
                                                                             people with good values driven by
                                                                             knowledge and culture. Being a
                                                                             good and knowledgeable person with
               My name is Mauro Porcini, and I am   As part of an exchange program,   culture has always been my dream. I
               the Chief Design Officer at PepsiCo.   I studied for one year at the   learned that it was not about making
               My team is responsible for the   National College of Art and Design   money or social connections; that
               design of our products around the   of Dublin. The school was behind   was not their way of thinking. I know
               world – including graphic design,   Milan regarding design education;   if I do my best possible work, I will
               industrial design, digital media   however, it was an amazing   succeed.
               design, and architecture; we also   experience because it brought me
               drive innovation and strategy.   back to an authentic approach to   At the age of 18, I met Stefano
                                              understanding the world. With a   Marzano when he was the Chief
               We use design tools and mindsets to   class size of 15, we had access   Design Officer of Philips. His
               think in creative ways and to inform   to the laboratory where we made   work created a new approach to
               the globe of our brand and products   mockups using traditional tools   design that changed the way the
               using interactive social media   without computers. Even today   corporation made use of design.
               channels. We also create innovative   in our digital world, it is so very   Stefano was the person who
               ways to imagine PepsiCo’s future   important to be able to sketch and   convinced me to go to Dublin; he
               offerings by imagining the future of   create mockups. Young creative   was my mentor even though he did
               the world, the future of our society,   problem-solvers should not just use   not realize it at the time. This is an
               and the role of our company in that   digital devices; rather learn by rolling   important lesson that I often share
               future.                        up their sleeves and creating things   with young people: find someone

               I have a Master’s Degree from   with their own hands as well.   who will inspire you and then try
               Polytechnic University of Milan’s   My father is an architect and a   to connect with them. When I
               School of Design, where I learned   painter, as was my grandfather. My   accepted my first corporate job at
               about design strategy, which at that   father gave me this passion, this   3M, my dream was to do exactly
               time was a new and unique role for   love, for everything art. My mother   what Stephano did at Philips. At
               design. It was a big university with   worked in finance with a passion for   the end of the day in my own way, I
               tons of people, so you had to share   philosophy – still today, she writes   succeeded – this is now what I am
               facilities and tools with many people;   poems. My mother gave me this   doing at PepsiCo.
               it was not easy to learn there.  passion for everything philosophy   Claudio Cecchetto is from the music
                                              and literature and a love of writing   world and a big star in Italy – he
                                                                                                                 ICAF.org


                                                                                                               11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[was the creator of the multicultural   to cleaning tools. It was fascinating   improve the brand to make it more
               radio and attracted many talented   to enter a new world of food and   global for today and even more so
               musicians. We shared a company   beverage, take on a huge challenge    for tomorrow.
               for three years, everything he   of managing brands that are a key
               touched turned into gold; he was a   part of pop culture in the U.S. and on   Albeit difficult, many things had
               real innovator. I was a super excited   a global scale – including my country,   to change to solve this significant
               kid. I remember Claudio telling me,   Italy.                  challenge.
               listen, we need to do this because it                         1. We needed to understand what
               is getting us money to support the   When I joined PepsiCo, my main   people want from different
               company, but what we also need   challenge was to understand what   regions of the world, what they
               to do this because no one has ever   it meant to manage a brand at a   love, and what they would be
               done this before. I was 24 when he   global level. Pepsi was successfully   comfortable with from an identity
               gave me that message, and I will live   growing across the world with   standpoint. To accomplish this,
               by it for the rest of my life.   different identities, personalities, and
                                              emotional connections – all of which   we used our creative imagination
               In 2012, I was ready for a new   was fine for many years when the   to revamp Pepsi and gain deeper
               challenge – that is when I accepted   world was mostly fragmented.   understandings of our global
               the job at PepsiCo. I am fortunate                              consumers.
               to have had multiple options back   In the 21st century, we are dealing   2. Next, we needed to understand
               then. I decided to join a company   with a global world that is a hyper-  the business and its relationship
               similar to 3M, a large American   connected by way of social media.   to our consumers’ preferences,
               business with like-minded structure   Our brand is onstage 24/7 without a   needs, wants, and desires. We
               and property. On the other hand, it   specific geographical location. The   needed to figure out what level
               was also different from 3M where I   Pepsi brand was already successful   impact this shift would have on
               touched everything from aerospace   in the world. However, we needed to   our business. We needed to know
                                                                               if this was the right time – or
                                                                               would it be better to wait? There
                                                                               are tons of business-related
                                                                               variables to consider, all of which
                                                                               are extremely important.

                                                                             3. Finally, we needed the ability to
                                                                               understand our stakeholders, the
                                                                               business leaders from different
                                                                               regions of the world. We needed
                                                                               to understand how to bond with
                                                                               them, partner with them, and
                                                                               handle the situation with ease.
                                                                               Whenever a business goes
                                                                               through a big change, creates
         ChildArt | October–December 2016                                      new, there are risks involved.
                                                                               innovation, or does something
                                                                               Innovating and taking risks are a
                                                                               major part of my job at PepsiCo.
                                                                               Business leaders who take
                                                                               risks also need to understand
                                                                               one another and collaborate to




       12]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[drive change. It is important
                 to approach the problem
                 with a creative spirit, flexible
                 imagination, and a deep sense of
                 empathy. After tremendous effort,
                 we now have a successful global
                 brand and worldwide identity.

               Creative thinkers must come to
               understand three important things:
               empathy, strategy, and prototyping.

               1. Empathy is about understanding
                 people's needs, wants, desires,
                 and dreams by way of observation
                 and other means.

               2. Strategy is about taking
                 the insights learned from
                 observations of people and
                 their reality, and then translating
                 those insights into a strategy
                 that makes sense for business,
                 the equity of the company’s   year, or even month-by-month. To   not just with consumers. Creative
                 brand, customers, and the entire   be on top of this, we must get out   thinkers and good innovators use
                 business model.              there and observe what is going   a pragmatic yet emotion-based
                                              on in the world. We must nurture   approach to bring worthwhile
               3. Prototyping is the ability to   our sense of curiosity from the   ideas to life with every meeting,
                 visualize insights and strategies   very beginning; good innovators   connection, and collaborative effort.
                 right away by getting one’s hands   and creative thinkers must learn
                 dirty, creating a quick mockup, or   how to strategize with others and   To learn more about Mauro Porcini’s
                 simple sketch. These skills help to   understand the business world.   thoughtful approach to becoming a
                 align an organization around a key                          creative thinker and good innovator,
                 idea and empower various parts   No matter what we do, at the end of   please Google “A Love Letter by
                 of the organization to contribute   the day, we all want to make a living.   Mauro Porcini”; to learn even more
                 and co-create to bring the idea to   If the goal is to change the world   visit: design.pepsico.com
                 reality.                     and create a better place for society,
                                              business can play an important
               For creative thinkers to become   role to distribute and give access to
               good innovators, they must first   amazing ideas.
               understand people – to do so
               they need to have an open mind,   Prototyping is the key. For example,
               remain curious, and keep reading,   marketing utilizes empathy and
               observing, and traveling.      strategies as well. However, it is
                                              critical for designers to be involved,
               Today’s world is constantly    to mock up the idea to empower all
               changing; society is moving so fast   within a common vision. Empathy is
               that consumer preferences are   also the key. We must learn how to
               changing day-by-day, not year-by-  empathize with anyone around us,
                                                                                                                 ICAF.org


                                                                                                               13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[LOOK AROUND YOU.

                   DESIGN IS EVERYWHERE!







                                                                     by Kathy Bonte


               Look around you. Everything you   build a toy that is both sturdy and   After young designers generate
               see, from the shiny toy on the store   playful. They clearly define the   many ideas and sketches, they
               shelf to the colorful pillowcase   problem set by deciding on who   select a final design. The next
               on your bed or the very shirt on   their audience or their customer will   challenge is to build a model of the
               your back has been "designed" by   be. Are we designing for a chubby   design without the assistance of a
               someone. From a lively placemat   toddler whose fine motor skills are   team of carpenters, metal smiths
               pattern to the placement of a purse   still developing? He/she will need   and model makers. Creative use
               zipper – every detail is there for   a safe toy with no sharp edges or   of materials that are available and
               a reason. A professional designer   small pieces that could come loose.   the clever repurposing (re-using
               carefully considers each of these   Now consider designing a toy for a   stuff that you find) of found objects
               decisions.                     ten-year-old – this may be more of a   now comes into play. A slice of a
                                              challenge.                     Styrofoam pool noodle around a
               How does this creative process                                wooden spool becomes a car tire.
               come to life? How does a toy   Think about what the toy will do or   A sliver of brightly colored duct
               designer, interior designer, textile   what will the 10-year-old do with   tape becomes a racing stripe,
               designer or fashion designer come   it? Is it a furry soft toy for cuddling   and a painted wooden clothespin
               up with the designs that make it   at night or a vehicle with wheels   becomes a driver.
               into our stores, our homes, and   that can move and transport small
               our lives? How can we, as aspiring   objects across the room? Can it   A similar creative process happens
               designers, learn how to apply similar   change its shape or turn into a   in the Interior Dezign summer
               principles that professionals use to   variety of things – like a set of   program. Budding interior designers
                                                                             start with a mood board – a
                                              blocks? How might the toy bend,
               come up with our own creative and
         ChildArt | October–December 2016  Let us begin with the design of toys   sound? What colors will you use?   solidify their vision for their room.
                                              fold, open, close, or take positions
               unique items to use, wear, and play?
                                                                             collection of images, paint chips,
                                                                             and swatches that help them
                                              in different ways? Does it make a
               and playthings. In the DezignKidz
                                              Most kids are attracted to bright
                                                                             For example, do they want to create
               Summer Program, in Silicon Valley,
                                              colors. However, if the toy is a
                                                                             an environment that is peaceful,
               California, “wanna-be” designers in
                                              small-scale replica of a real life item
                                                                             with soft neutrals and cool colors,
               the Toy Dezign class often face a
                                                                             or stimulating to the senses, with
                                              (for example, a police car) – realistic
               creative challenge. We first begin
                                              colors may be better choices than
                                                                             bold patterns and contrasting hues?
               come up with an idea and then
                                                                             up the feeling of the ocean or they
       14      with a sketch; young designers   bright neon shades.          Perhaps they are trying to conjure]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[are inspired by the delicious colors   in frills and lace may make them
               of a candy store. Based on their   feel awkward. If they are quiet and
               initial vision, students then design   low-key, a bright red jumpsuit may
               a collection of appealing objects   draw more attention than their
               for their space that also serves   comfort zone can handle.
               important purposes as determined
               by them (based on what they know   Young designers are encouraged
               about the person who will be part   to look outward for inspiration –
               of the user experience). A pillow   by flipping through magazines,
               may have a secret pocket for a   studying the work of famous
               hiding a book or diary or a hanging   designers or just walking outside to
               organizer may have just the right-  take inspiration from nature. Once
               sized compartments for a favorite   their initial vision becomes clear, a
               collection.                    senior teacher and the counselors
                                              help them define the steps to turn it   Hunger Games. For the Hunger
               Although we avoid teaching     from a sketch to finished garment.   Games Challenge, students first had
               DIY (Do It Yourself) electrical   Sometimes there are detours on   to decide on a specific character
               wiring, students also explore the   the road from the sketch to the   and consider both the personality of
               fundamental principles of lighting.   final project. One middle school   the character as well as the mood
               Using a simple battery-powered LED  boy designed an ambitious pair of   and the setting in which the outfit
               as a base, students can create a   pants with 22 different pockets,   would be worn. The groups worked
               decorative lighting element for their   each one dedicated to a specific   together to brainstorm, sketch, and
               rooms. By changing the material   item he liked to carry with him. After   come up with a final design which
               that covers the bare bulb, students   two failed attempts at making his   they then created in miniature scale
               learn through doing to create   first cargo pocket, he eventually   using scraps of fabric and other
               different moods and effects. Cutouts   got the hang of it but soon decided   materials on hand.
               in the material create interesting   that two large pockets were more
               shadows on walls and ceilings, and   than enough! Lesson learned: while   Chances are only a handful of the
               the choice of color can create an   it is important to see your vision   students who come through our
               eerie effect or a flattering glow.      through, sometimes you need to   program will become professional
                                              make adjustments.              fashion designers, toy designers or
               The students in our Fashion                                   interior designers. While they learn
               Dezign program have perhaps    The fledgling fashion designers   many useful practical skills – how
               the most personal connection to   at DezignKidz not only have   to sew a straight seam, how to
               their finished projects, as they   themselves as clients; sometimes   hammer a nail, how to make a floor
               are creating something that    they get to design for a celebrity   plan – the real lesson they take
               they intend to wear. The design   or a character in a favorite book or   with them is how to take their ideas
               framework is that it must look good,   film. DK Challenges are a unique   from concept to completion. It is
               flatter their individual body type   and beloved part of the program in   a lesson they can apply wherever
               AND reflect their personal style.   which the students work in teams to   their futures takes them – whether
               Naturally, it must also fit properly,   design a “look” for a specific person   they are building a skyscraper, a
               be comfortable to wear and not fall   or event. Perhaps they will design   new iPhone app, or a lesson plan
               apart at an inopportune time. To   a touring outfit for Taylor Swift, a   to inspire future generations of
               achieve this, the aspiring designer   wardrobe for a tropical vacation, or,   innovators.
               must first look inward. If they are   in the case of a recent challenge,
               sporty and casual, a dress covered   a costume for a character in The   Kathy Bonte is a designer and educator with
                                                                             over 30 years design experience across a
                                                                             variety of media–from print, web and film to
                                                                             more recent forays into fashion accessories
                                                                             and home decor. In 2009, with her partner
                                                                             Durga Kalavagunta, she co-founded
                                                                             DezignKidz, a Silicon Valley organization
                                                                             dedicated to providing creative enrichment   ICAF.org
                                                                             programs to elementary and middle school-
                                                                             aged children.                    15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[JOHN






                                              EDSON









         ChildArt | October–December 2016
         John is a 25-year design industry veteran and leader of LUNAR,
         a global product and experience design consultancy firm working
         at the intersection of consumer insights, industrial design, engineering,

         and manufacturing for a wide range of client companies in a variety
         of industries.





       16]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[My name is John Edson, and I am   had just begun discussions about   in-house ability to help clients create
               the President of LUNAR, a product   how we might turn LUNAR into a   new-to-the-world products and
               design and development firm    partnership structure so that leaders   services, and that led to teaming up
               founded in Silicon Valley in 1984   could become owners and owners   with LUNAR.
               – the year that Apple made the   could rotate in and out over time.
               first Macintosh computer. LUNAR   Founded in 1984, we were eager to   For almost a quarter-century, Jeff
               has been my home since 1993    create something lasting for LUNAR,   Smith, one of LUNAR’s founders, has
               when I joined after graduating from   a legacy of the founders that was   been my unintentional mentor. By
               Stanford University with a master’s   sustainable and would take our   unintentional, I mean he is not the
               degree from what was then called   values and practice forward.  guy to reflect on an interaction and
               the Joint Program in Design. I also                           purposely draw out teachings. He
               studied mechanical engineering at   Over most of its history, McKinsey   leads and coaches by example, an
               The University of Texas. In addition   has focused on helping clients   approach that is gentle, empathetic,
               to my day job, I have been teaching   with their business strategies and   and open to all possibilities.
               at Stanford in the undergraduate   organizational models – in short,   Despite the fact I have always
               product design program for the last   helping them figure out what to do   favored creative problem solving
               two decades.                   and how to structure themselves
                                              for greater success. Over the past   and been a designer at heart, my
               In May 2015 – in a move that   decade or two, McKinsey has    early career was more strongly
               surprised the design world – LUNAR   grown well beyond these staples   associated with markers of a fixed
               joined forces with McKinsey &   into areas that are operational,   mindset. I was idealistic and maybe
               Company, a 90-year-old global   including marketing, IT and so on,   a bit smug. I suppose that is not
               management-consulting firm. When   with considerable interest in product   uncommon for most of us. It just
               McKinsey first contacted me, we   development. However, there was no   took me longer than I would have
                                                                                                                 ICAF.org


                                                                                                               17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[preferred to grow out of that. Jeff’s   business-consulting firm. I did   interesting things happen on a
               creative leadership eventually cut   not get a call back after my first   budget, and coaching our team
               through my inflexible, deterministic   interview, so a good friend (who had   from their own challenges into new
               approach.                      accepted a job) interceded on my   opportunities, the type of stuff that
                                              behalf.  As a result, I got a second   happens every day.
               In particular, Jeff’s ability to tackle   interview; however, I was passed
               tough challenges with artful and   over once again. They really were   Perhaps the biggest single hard
               novel thinking has often come as a   not interested in me!    thing that I did was take up the
               welcome surprise. I cannot count
               the number of times someone in a   It is rather satisfying to me that now
               meeting has said: “we have to do   I’ve ended up where I am because   Professional work takes
               this or else.” In response, Jeff often   I’ve spent the last 25 years doing   place most often in teams,
               says something like: “Well, maybe –   what I love, and here I am at the
               why don’t we try two ways and see   center of things in the present   so learning to move back
               which one we like better.” One of   context – being sought after by the   and forth between these
               his formative books is Jim Collins’   big daddy of business consulting.
               Built to Last. In the 1990s, Jeff often   It is so simple and so powerful to   two modes, while also
               referred to Collins’ concepts of “the   find the thing you’re good at, that   finding an environment
               tyranny of the or” and “the genius of   you love because it will lead to the
               and” – the idea that the best answer   greatest success. For me, the best   that respects both, is
               might include seemingly ideas that   is yet to come!          especially helpful to the
               at first seem mutually exclusive.                             creative individual.
               Practicing Jeff’s growth mindset   I like to think about challenges as
               approach has transformed me into a   opportunities. It can be trite, but   invitation to write a book about
                                              for me, I believe that the language
         ChildArt | October–December 2016  Becoming part of the McKinsey   find our way through to something   design and the link to their incredible
               more resilient thinker, designer, and
                                              we use can be a big influencer of
               problem solver.
                                                                             lessons learned from Apple’s use of
                                              our mindsets. Things happen. We
                                                                             success. Steve Jobs had died, and
                                              new; that is a big part of my role. To
               team makes me pinch myself for
                                              use that wording, the opportunities
                                                                             Wiley figured it would be a good
               personal reasons too, and I think
                                                                             time to publish such a book, Design
               there is a lesson in here for all of us.
                                              I face on a daily basis are a mixed
                                                                             Like Apple, I figured I could write it.
               In 1989, I interviewed at Andersen
                                              bag: creating programs for clients
       18      Consulting, another respected   that will deliver impact, making   We were on a timeline because the]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[longer we waited, the less relevant it   the physical world, and wonderful   place most often in teams, so
               would be.                        and insightful things happen when   learning to move back and forth
                                                our hands work with physical   between these two modes, while
               To be totally honest, it was the   materials to make things.    also finding an environment that
               hardest creative act that I have ever                           respects both, is especially helpful
               undertaken. It taxed my ability to   Case in point: one of my favorite   to the creative individual.
               bring a continual renewal to the   designers is a graphic designer
               project, to tell good stories, to find   named Becky Brown. I got to   3. I was not an athletic kid. I did
               original thoughts. One Saturday   work alongside her at LUNAR for   some individual sports like bike
               night at 2 a.m. while I was in my   some number of years. While   riding and swimming, but not
               home office pounding away on my   everything that Becky produces   competitively and I was not
               laptop, I thought to myself, “get a   ends up in some Adobe product   dedicated. I married into an
               life, John!” I did, but not until we   on the computer, when developing   athletic family – my father-in-law
               hit send on the final manuscript,   her ideas, the computer does not   was the Stanford Women’s Tennis
               secured all the copyright        bind her. She is a prolific collector   coach for over two decades, and
               permissions and selected the color   of beautiful and inspiring objects,   his father coached Billy Jean King.
               for the end papers. Now I have a   and she will often work with pen   I have worked alongside athletes
               book, and I’m thinking about what   and paper and copy machine   and had many student athletes in
               the next one will be.            and scissors when developing a   my classes. I have become more
                                                concept. It is a joy to watch, and it   active as an adult.
               Looking back on the experience, I   fuels her amazing creativity.
               think the challenge was two-fold.                             Reflecting on these experiences, I
               First, a book is a ton of work.   2. Young people need to learn how   am convinced that being involved
               Bringing the required creativity is   to work alongside others. My   in an active, competitive situation
               tough. Second, I worked with a   children have engaged in project-  contributes a lot to a person’s
               professional writer; however, as the   based learning at school. It took   confidence and persistence, two
               author of the book – this experience   me until I was a senior in college   foundational characteristics of the
               can draw out the perfectionist in   to figure out the power of working   best creatives. It is not an exclusive
               even the most prolific creative.  In   with other students while figuring   thing; it does not mean if you are
               the end, I am proud of the product,   out problem sets. This approach   not active that you are not creative,
               even though I can find myriad    is especially powerful with   but organized competitive situations
               imperfections. The experience has   students who are teaching others   build habits and muscles that
               opened so many doors for LUNAR;   as well as learning. Nevertheless,   can transfer into creative ability –
               and for me as well.              it is also not the only thing. At   specifically, they teach us not be
                                                most places in industry, there is a   satisfied with the first answer but to
               I share three insights with young   big emphasis on working together   push through to something original.
               creative problem-solvers:        and collaborating.

               1. Young creative problem-solvers   That said, it is best not just to
                 can benefit from diving into   work well with others, but also
                 opportunities to be hands-on.    learn how to work effectively on
                 Much of the lives of adults and   your own. About half of us are
                 especially the lives of young   introverts, and if we are shoving
                 people, are dominated by digital   everyone into these group settings
                 experiences. Mobile, social media,   to learn and work, we miss
                 entertainment, gaming, and     out on a big source of creative
                 immediate access to information   capacity. In my experience,
                 is shaping our creativity, and in   more than half of self-identified
                 fact, our entire way of thinking.    creatives are introverts, so this
                 However, we would be missing   effect is even more pronounced
                 out if we lose our connection with   for us. Professional work takes
                                                                                                                 ICAF.org


                                                                                                               19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[DEBBIE







                              MILLMAN








         ChildArt | October–December 2016  Debbie Millman is one of the most influential designers working


               today, author of six books, host of the podcast Design Matters,
               creative and editorial director of Print magazine, and co-founder
               of the world’s first graduate program in branding at the School
               of Visual Arts in New York City.





       20]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[I suddenly felt encouraged
        to think; I felt encouraged
        to voice my opinion, and I
        felt encouraged to have a
        point of view.





















               My name is Debbie Millman, and I am   changed my life. I grew up in a   another nickel so that I would not
               a native New Yorker, and have lived in   turbulent family situation; my   have to lie to my parents. I am
               all the boroughs except the Bronx. I   parents divorced when I was eight-  grateful to have had teachers who
               was born in Brooklyn; then my family   years-old, then my mother was   encouraged me to develop my ability
               moved to Howard Beach, Queens   married to a criminal for four years.   to write; they truly believed in me.
               until I was in 3rd grade, then to   I did not see my father during that
               Staten Island when I was about to go   time; he was also someone who was   The same thing happened during
               into the 6th grade. When my parents   emotionally intense. My teachers at   my in the first year in college. I
               divorced, my mother moved my   school gave me a feeling of stability   went from a high school of 400
               brother and me to Long Island where   that I needed.          students to a college of 20,000 – I
               I graduated from high school before                           felt miserable, really small and
               attending the State University of New   I received a tremendous amount   lonely, and out of my league. All of
               York (SUNY) at Albany. I have lived in   of kindness from my teachers.   that changed when I took a class
               Manhattan for the past 33 years and   Every day my mother would give   with Professor Helen Regueiro Elam.
               am a total public (and state) school   me a nickel to buy milk for lunch   Professor Elam helped me realize
               student.                       at school. One day I lost the nickel   that I am intellectually gifted. She
                                              while walking through the hall of the   took what I said seriously, she asked
               My teachers had far greater    school. I was desperate to find it and  questions, and I responded – then
               influence on me than my parents   became terrified of being punished   she replied with “what an interesting
               did. In essence, my teachers   for losing it. My teacher Mrs. Vanoff   idea” or “what a great thought.”
                                                                                                                 ICAF.org
                                              saw me crying, and she gave me


                                                                                                               21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[I think that reading is
                                                                            the key to the universe.
                                                                            Curiosity is the birthplace
                                                                            of imagination.












































         ChildArt | October–December 2016















       22]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[I suddenly felt encouraged to think; I   About eight or ten years after   One of the common denominators
               felt encouraged to voice my opinion,   graduating from college, I still had   in my life is getting a tremendous
               and I felt encouraged to have a   no clue what I was going to do with   amount of joy out of making things
               point of view. I credit her with giving   the rest of my life. By accident, I   – whether it is a podcast, a lesson
               me a sense of my own capability   found a job as a sales person in   plan, or a business proposal. I feel
               and intelligence – she has had a   a consulting firm that designed   happy creating something that was
               profound influence on how I teach   brands for companies. That is   not there before.
               my own students. Now I try to do   when I finally realized that I had an
               the same thing for the students in   instinctive understanding of brands.   Two years ago, I interviewed Dani
               my program and classes.        My father was a pharmacist, and   Shapiro, the writer. One of Dani’s
                                              I spent a lot of time in his store   key beliefs has stayed with me ever
               I started my career as a designer   and grew up around brands. I also   since: she believes that confidence
               with the only marketable skill that   worked as a cashier in his store and   is highly overrated and it is more
               I had. When I was at SUNY, I wrote   had a firsthand understanding of   important to have courage. To have
               for the student newspaper, and   consumer experiences. I met the   the courage to stick with something
               I became the Arts and Feature   founder of Sterling Brands, Simon   long enough to have repeated
               editor in my senior year. As editor   Williams, in 1995 – I started working   success – the courage to take that
               of the paper, I was also responsible   at Sterling then and have been there   first step, especially when you have
               for the layout and design. I found   ever since. My role at the company   no foundation of success to fall
               the experience to be something   has expanded over time; in turn, it   back on, that is what I learned from
               remarkable, like magic. I loved   created the foundation of my career   Dani.
               doing it as much if not more than   today.
               the editing, writing, and assigning                           I think that reading is the key to the
               stories. I learned there was not   Now I am much more interested   universe. Curiosity is the birthplace
               much I could do with an English   in working on brands that have the   of imagination. I loved reading so
               degree; I did not want to be an   capacity to influence the world in   much when I was a kid. It was my
               advertising account executive in an   a positive way. I want to make the   solace along with my teachers.
               agency. I developed an old school   world a better place through creating   As an adult, I recreated and re-
               skill of layout drafting, so my first   compelling visual communications   read nearly all of the books in my
               paying jobs were working as a   of the company’s message.     childhood library, the books that had
               freelance designer paste-up artist.                           the greatest influence on me as the
                                                                             person who I have become today.
                                                                                                                 ICAF.org



                                                                                                               23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[MEGAN







                                              NEESE








         ChildArt | October–December 2016  Megan Neese is a senior manager of Future Lab at Renault-Nissan


               Alliance, a global cross-functional team tasked with identifying
               new business opportunities. Neese holds a bachelor's degree in
               industrial design and master's degree in product development
               from Carnegie Mellon University.





       24]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[My name is Megan Neese, and    with ten to twenty people in a   five to seven years’ before they are
               I a senior manager at Nissan. I   specific neighborhood. For example,   ready to sell. Our job is to wonder
               am a designer by training and   we collaborate with Scoot Networks   about the main concept of the car,
               an advanced planner and future   in San Francisco to study, prototype   who we are designing for, and why
               strategist by trade. I grew up in   and test out a new mobility concept.   it needs to exist. We also come up
               Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania in a very   We are looking into how people   with two catchy word phrases that
               creative household. Our house was   feel and experience; we talk with   will make it come to life. Our team
               full of crafts where we could make   the people to gather their feedback   included many disciplines including
               whatever we wanted at any time, a   and input on how they are using the   engineering, product planning,
               true source of inspiration. I went to   scooters, is it changing their life   marketing teams, and anthropology;
               Carnegie Mellon University where   compared to what we anticipated.   we were all excited to take part in
               I earned my Bachelor’s degree in                              early focus groups, concept making,
               Industrial Design and a Master’s in   Without a doubt, my mother had the   and workshops.
               Product Development. The graduate   greatest influence on my creative
               program was all about collaboration,   self. My mom was the art director
               filled with a mix of designers,   for the Mr. Rogers’ Neighborhood
               engineers, and business students;   show; she created a safe place for   Just as with rough and
               we all studied one another’s area   us to invent at home; supplies were   digital prototyping, digital
               of learning as cross-functional   at the ready without any expectation   sketching has its place.
               teams. We explored innovations and   on what we should make.
               product strategies, which is literally   She would bring home all these   Choosing which form to
               what I do now in my career.    weird supplies from work; like fifty   use and why is important
               Grounded in design strategy and   cardboard boxes to build things in   – especially during early
               organizational design, I work with   a big space in our kitchen such as   thinking and collaborations.
               a cross-functional team in a group   storefronts or own version of Super
               called Future Lab at the Nissan-  Mario World. We were constantly
               Renault Alliance. Future Lab studies   building whole worlds out of random
               how we get around and how we   pieces of inspiration; like huge rolls
               might live in the future. We begin   of 10’ tall gold foil paper. We would
               by looking at society – how we   wrap things up as treasures, make
               live today and how we might live   mazes, and then go on exhaustive
               in the future. We study how people   hunts that could take weeks.
               commute from one part of the city   Had my mom not set the stage for
               to another, where they go to get   our creative culture, not only would I
               coffee, etc. We use this information   be a different person – but so would
               to envision products and services   all the kids in neighborhood. We
               for the future. Our cross-functional   were all best friends running through
               team brings diverse perspectives   each other’s backyards and playing.
               such as urban planning, sociology,   My mom would challenge us with
               and business to dream up new ideas   things like the volcano experiment
               and concepts.                  with baking soda and vinegar – for
               We often immerse ourselves into a   the next three weeks; our whole
               different context by asking, “What   neighborhood was making them!
               is happening in Singapore right   My greatest accomplishment was
               now?” We build “Living Labs” of little,   with the Advanced Planning Team
               real-world experiments where we try   for the Nissan Rouge, which is
               out futures. We combine hardware,   now a current product. Advanced
               software, services, and systems   planning works on future products
                                                                                                                 ICAF.org


                                                                                                               25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[around the world met to dive into   create huge trucks. The people I
                                              day-in-the-life walkthroughs focused   worked with had different types
                                              on the imagined future owner of the   of responsibilities such as the
                                              Rouge, a mother of small children.   sound and tone a door makes
                                              We brought in strollers, diaper bags,   when it closes or how our products
                                              and experienced what our future   appear in brochures. It was a huge
                                              mom would. Where would she shop?   challenge to collaborate on such
                                              What kind of things would she carry   diversified large-scale projects,
                                              with her in the car? How would she   difficult to maintain excitement
                                              open the trunk, get everything in, get   and alignment with what we
                                              everything out, all while caring for   were building and why. It was an
                                              screaming children?            overwhelming responsibility, yet
                                                                             we were able to find inspiration in
                                              At the time, I did not have kids –   great ideas and poetic concepts
                                              nor did some of my teammates.   that everyone could become excited
                                              We all learned a great deal, what it   about, could immediately visualize
                                              was like to live the life of a mother;   and bring it life. We provoked
                                              fully understand her needs. Our   thinking through a great concept,
                                              workshops made the future real,   or idea, and just letting go as it
                                              far more real than reading a report.   sailed through the organization over
                                              These insights led to innovative   time. To communicate like this in
                                              product design solutions with   a succinct and global way was a
                                              clear expectations of what it is like   constant challenge.
                                              to manage daily activities within
                                              limited windows of time based   We have learned that, to be
                                              on a child’s needs. It was a great   successful at these collaborative
                                              accomplishment because that car is   efforts, writing a report is not a
                                              doing very well in the market and is   viable option. However, producing
                                              a tribute to some of our early work.   a two-minute video to distil the
                                              Our research was the bay leaf in the   content into three key themes is.
               One of our biggest challenges was   soup so to speak; we added a sense   I have faced this same dilemma
               collaborating within a giant global   of flavor that otherwise would not   for ten years, each time I feel like I
               corporation; team members were   have been there.             should be better only to reconfirm
               from all around the world – China,   We face a continuous challenge   that these are truly difficult
               Europe, and Brazil. We had to   of working across countries,   challenges and hard to solve
               explore the basic needs of our users   cultures, time zones, experiences,   creative problems. I call this is the
               from many markets, like what the   and disciplines with every product   ice cream headache, something I
               dimensions of the car needed to be   we design. This challenge is good   experience when there are so many
               based on how wide the roads are or   in that what we are designing is   aspects to consider, opinions, and
               how big the families are.      great stuff; however, it is difficult to   versions of a solution. When this
                                                                             happens, we give some time, let the
                                              prepare for sometimes. In design
               We conducted ethnography studies
         ChildArt | October–December 2016  aspects of a car – like the need to   a designer in individual or small   Three bits of advice come to mind
                                                                             process naturally evolve, and then
                                              school, we learned to think like
               to learn more about functional
                                                                             come back to it.
                                              groups; then in graduate school,
               be flexible with the configuration
                                              we were more interdisciplinary but
                                                                             to share with young learners in the
               of the trunk space and the size
                                                                             21st century:
                                              always in a small group of 5-7 and
               of the backseat. To tackle these
                                              independent from the other teams.
               design problems, we found creative
                                                                               1. In our digital world, there is
               ways to hold three-day immersion
                                                                                 often pressure to form quick
                                              Once I became a designer, I
       26      workshops. Thirty people from   experienced what it was like to   new concepts, build them, and]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[release them using a variety of   shop helped me develop      ideas. In one of our projects,
                   approaches. Sometimes our      ideas. Throughout my           we sketched how people moved
                   team addresses challenges      childhood, I experienced       around the San Francisco Bay
                   quickly; sometimes we step     tangible connections           Area on the transit system to
                   back and ask big questions.    with simple materials like     visually capture our learning
                   We ask, what is the purpose    cardboard or paper to create   process through physical
                   of the concept? What role is   rough prototypes; skills that   sketches. I encourage young
                   the concept fulfilling? In what   we frequently use in our    creative problem-solvers not to
                   way is the concept helping the   Living Labs at Nissan to     be afraid to sketch on paper in
                   situation? These responses     bring something from the       real time before they formalize
                   help to clarify many aspects   future to life. Once you start   their ideas and concepts with
                   of our design process without   experiencing, feeling, and    a digital tool; visible ideas
                   spending a bunch of time       touching an idea, it becomes   developed over time. Showing
                   making things just because we   closer to reality. Sometimes   your thinking process allows
                   can do it quickly. Otherwise,   digital prototyping can replace   everyone in the room to see
                   it compromises the art of      this physical approach;        and react to your concepts.
                   designing the concept; a one-  however, it is important to be   Just as with rough and digital
                   day brainstorming session is   thoughtful about which to use   prototyping, digital sketching
                   not enough time to conduct     and why.                       has its place. Choosing
                   research and develop valuable                                 which form to use and why
                   ideas.                       3. Just as designers know how    is important – especially
                                                  to sketch cars, a coffee maker,   during early thinking and
                 2. Having experienced a tactile   or a train, non-designers can   collaborations.
                   design education, making       use their playful imagination to
                   things with my hands in the    sketch and communicate their
                                                                                                                 ICAF.org


                                                                                                               27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[SEEING BY DOING





                                                       by Robert Coven



               What would it be like to re-design   their own by describing their findings
               your learning experiences at   to their peers (rather than relying on
               school, so all that you do becomes   me). Conceptual Modeling provides
               interesting and meaningful to you?   my students with opportunities to
               To tackle this challenge, all you   think in unique and thoughtful ways.   uncomfortable. In fact, it is to be
               need is likely already inside of you   Through the construction of visual   expected. As you experience this
               – a sense of curiosity, willingness   representations, my learners create   way of learning, you will become
               to use your imagination, and the   meaning, develop their own theories,   more adept and confident. Your
               motivation to ask good questions.   and form new understandings.   classmates and your teacher will
               By practicing critical thinking skills,   The Conceptual Modeling process   ask many questions about your
               you can create your own way to see   challenges how I teach as well. I   ideas and elements of your model
               the world around you while gaining   must be prepared to support my   design. Your teacher will also guide
               new insights, diving deep into new   students as they develop new   you as you dive more deeply into
               information, exploring tons of ideas,   interests and dig deeper into the   the investigation (without telling you
               sorting through problems, and   content.                      what to do).
               making good choices… all of which                             The Conceptual Modeling Process
               will be with you forever to use at any   In small groups, my students   has four phases; each essential to
               time!                          develop a greater sense of
                                              independence with their learning;   learning by way of inquiry:
               To this end, my high school    they do not expect me to provide   1. Preparation Phase
               history students engage in     all the “right” questions or answers.   Your teacher will introduce a
               a powerful approach called     Students demonstrate what they   general topic to learn about;
                                              know about the real world by asking
               Conceptual Modeling to come
                                                                               then you will develop questions
         ChildArt | October–December 2016  have come to believe about the   this uncertainty is an important part   challenge. When ready, you will
                                              questions, knowing in advance that
               up with new ideas, interpret
                                                                               to investigate a problem set or
                                              there are not pre-defined answers;
               meaning, and share what they
                                                                               gather information, make sense
                                              of the learning process. Head’s up:
               world. As they communicate their
                                                                               of initial insights, and sift, sort,
               ideas, sometimes my students
                                              please do not become concerned
                                                                               and identify the most important
               misunderstand parts of the
                                              if, during the first time you go
                                                                               content. The goal is to select the
               concepts. Often they figure out how
                                              through the modeling process,
                                                                               best topics that directly support
               to undo these misconceptions on
                                              you feel confused, possibly a bit
       28                                                                      the main idea.]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[2. Development Phase             and present as well as provide
                 In small collaborative groups   guidance for the future. Students
                 of three, you will construct   come to understand that history is
                 diagrams (these are the        an integrated and interconnected
                 “models”) that will serve as visual   system, influenced by common
                 representations of your new ideas   forces, not a set of random
                 and understandings, big ideas,   events. All of this becomes
                 and supporting details using   part of a student’s transformed
                 large personal-size whiteboards   worldview.
                 (2’x3’). As your group develops a
                 visual model, all are encouraged   3. Presentation Phase
                 to discuss and explain rationales   Now is the time for your group   that follow aim to motivate you to
                 behind ideas and arguments,    to present findings to your    seek insight from within and from
                 and, of course, to listen. These   peers and explain how your   your peers.
                 models present your thesis and   design represents your theory.   4. Reflection Phase
                 arguments and act as evidence of   Sometimes theories and diagrams   While in revision mode, you will
                 your learning process as you draw   are well developed and sometimes   have the opportunity to test your
                 and explain the reasoning behind   they are less comprehensive. It   theories and interpretations
                 your work. At this point in the   all depends on where you are in   to investigate whether your
                 learning process, inconsistencies   the learning process regarding   outcomes line up with what you
                 are often identified which may   misconceptions, investigations,   originally thought. When ready,
                 require revisions to the diagram   and conclusions. The purpose of   your teacher will ask you to
                 and initial ideas.             group discussions is to reveal any   generate a brief one-to-two-page
                                                inconsistencies rather than finding
                 Your ideas will begin to take   fault, more to identify differences   analytical essay. Because this
                 shape as you gather materials   and missing or unrelated      assignment takes place after the
                 from your teacher’s information   elements.                   presentation phase, it allows you
                 along with your own research.                                 time to reflect on your work and
                 The best models are simple,    After the presentation, your group   learn from your peers.
                 clear visual metaphors         can revise your model as you   Modeling instruction holds
                 or diagrams representing       continue to develop your ideas   tremendous promise for all your
                 perceived influential entities,   and raise new questions as you   classes. It offers your teachers
                 relationships, and patterns. The   see fit. As you gain confidence,   an effective method to engage
                 models are simplified abstract   you learn to separate yourself   you as you retain and understand
                 representations that portray   from your work, which will allow   the new concepts – to become
                 different situations. The goal   for greater insights. In modeling,   adept and confident in applying
                 is not to create a work of art or   there is no single correct answer,   understandings to new scenarios.
                 representational cartoon, but   nor one way to arrive at a solution.   By constructing your own theory and
                 rather a visual tool for discussion.  After the group presentations, the   arguments, you will have a deep and
                                                class will meet in a seminar and
                 For example, my history students   look for threads that might unite   permanent understanding of history
                 often use their visual models to   the group models into a broader   and be able to transfer the skills and
                 describe new understandings    explanation of historical events.   concepts you have learned to other
                 about the past. In the process,   The models and the discussions   fields of study.
                 they develop a metaphor to depict
                 the patterns they have recognized
                 while studying historical data
                 such as economic cycles. The                                Robert Coven is an award-winning high
                                                                             school history teacher dedicated to helping
                 metaphors and patterns help                                 students become full participants in
                 them make sense of the past                                 their education. Coven uses conceptual
                                                                             modeling to provide students the means
                                                                             to break through conceptual barriers and   ICAF.org
                                                                             come to understand threshold concepts.
                                                                                                               29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[AYSE







                                              BIRSEL









         ChildArt | October–December 2016  Ayse Birsel has been designing award-winning products for


               over twenty years. She is the co-founder of Birsel + Seck, an
               innovative New York design studio that creates partnerships

               with leading brands and Fortune 500 companies. She teaches at
               the School of Visual Arts and has taught at the Pratt Institute.




       30]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[My name is Ayse Birsel, and I grew   systems approach to designing   in creative problem solving to take
               up in Turkey in Izmir; I earned my   products, to my life.    an active role in designing their own
               bachelor’s degree in industrial                               lives, creatively, just like a project.
               design (ID) at Middle East Technical   Design the Life You Love evolved
               University. After graduation, I   over time as I figured out how to   Three people have had a
               attended Pratt Institute in New York   apply my design process to my   tremendous influence on my love for
               City (NYC) to earn my master’s in ID   biggest project, “The Design of   design thinking and design; without
               as a Fulbright Scholar. I have lived   My Life.” The journey began as   them, I would not be who I am today.
               in NYC for almost 30 years where   an experiment. Then I began to
               I co-founded Birsel + Seck with my   collaborate with a friend of mine,   1. My father is a lawyer and
               husband Bibi Seck, an innovative   Shirley Moulton, at the newly formed   a renaissance man who is
               design firm. We work with large   ACADEMi of Life, a place to learn   interested in art, music, and
               Fortune 500 companies like General   the lessons that we do not learn at   history. While living in Izmir, my
               Electric, Toyota, Herman Miller,   school. Shirley was quite interested   parents would often take us
               Tiffany, and Target. Our design   in “The Design of My Life” and asked   to Ephesus, an ancient Roman
               services deliver award-winning   me to conduct a workshop at the   City that is very close to my
               results; we combine our thinking   ACADEMi.                     hometown, on family outings.
               with our clients’ expertise. I also                             There we would walk around and
               teach a Studio Intensive at the   The workshop grew through word   visit the ruins from the Roman
               School of Visual Arts.         of mouth, and that caused me to   Empire. I remember being six-
                                              realize many people were interested   years-old, super bored because I
               I recently published a book, Design   in becoming the designers of their   did not understand what we were
               the Life you Love, which is about   own life. After people continually   doing there.
               applying my design process,    requested, I spent the next three
               Deconstruction and Reconstruction™  years writing the book. I would love   One day my dad realized that I
                                                                                                                 ICAF.org
               (De: Re), a thoughtful and intuitive   for young people who are interested   was not interested, he said, “Look


                                                                                                               31]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[at the marble lined streets – do   3. Bruce Hannah was our   process. Yet we rarely elaborate on
                 you see the grooves interwoven   chairperson at Pratt; he gave   our own process, nor do not write
                 into the road? During Ancient   me my first job after graduating.   about it, try to put it on paper. I
                 Roman times, horse-drawn       Bruce taught me how to be a   am glad that I was able to do that,
                 chariots used to go up and down   designer with a sense of the   to take a journey inside of me to
                 these streets.” Suddenly, I could   profession, how to solve problems   understand the source of my ideas
                 see it in my mind; I could imagine   in creative ways, how to be user-  and the transformation that happens
                 life back then. I became so    centered, and how to develop   when one starts thinking about
                 curious and engaged that I finally   designs as if they are gifts to   something differently.
                 felt connected to a moment in   other people, whether your client
                 history. That was the beginning of   or the end user. Bruce taught me   Herein lays the connection between
                 my imagination when I learned to   what it means to be a human-  my work in product design, design
                 put myself in different places and   centered designer.     strategy, and Design the Life you
                 time to visualize what was going                            Love. My work allows me to teach
                 on. The power of my imagination   My biggest accomplishment has   how I think to other people; I really
                 began with the Roman chariots.  been developing my own design   enjoy that because it makes me feel
                                              process. The foundation of all   connected to people and gives me a
               2. Rowena Reed-Kostellow, one   my favorite projects, all the great   sense of purpose. Designers have a
                 of my teachers from Pratt, had   collaborations with wonderful   different way of thinking: optimistic,
                 developed her own process for   people, is my process. Developing   holistic, collaborative, empathic, and
                 teaching three-dimensional (3-D)   my process was like a journey into   asking ‘what if’ questions, that can
                 design to students. She taught   my head and heart to figure out   inspire people of all ages, designers,
                 us how to design in 3-D by way of   how I think creatively. We all have a   and non-designers alike.
                 rules and exercises – similar to   process that we intuitively use when
                 teaching music students how to   we do things. Each of us has our
                 excel by developing their inner ear   own personal approach, an internal
                 and sense of rhythm. In our case,
                 we developed a keen sense of
                 sight, proportion, and movement
                 in space.

                 I owe Rowena a great deal, not
                 only for what she taught us
                 about design but specifically
                 the ability to develop structures
                 and frameworks around abstract
                 concepts and three-dimensional
                 design. Much of my inspiration
                 around design and developing my
                 design process is due to Rowena’s
         ChildArt | October–December 2016  people can understand, learn, and
                 example, to take complex ideas
                 and create processes so many

                 excel. She was also my friend,
                 in fact, my first friend in New
                 York. I was twenty; Rowena was
                 80-something; I remember her
                 very fondly.



       32]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[The economic downturn of 2008
                was a difficult challenge; it changed
                the landscape for us overnight. I
                had already founded my partnership
                with Bibi, Birsel + Seck; we were
                doing very well working with long-
                term clients, doing what we love.
                However, the shift in the economy
                caused most of our clients to bring   Suddenly, I could see
                design in-house – a logical step
                given new budget constraints, the   it in my mind; I could
                need to save money. Because we   imagine life back then.
                were an external studio, we were   I became so curious
                one of the first to go. It made   and engaged that I
                sense. However I felt blindsided;
                we went from a successful, active,   finally felt connected
                creative studio to being quiet. This   to a moment in history.
                experience was a major intellectual
                and emotional shift; it shook our
                sense of place in the world.   1. Empathy is an essential skill for   creativity, vision, and pioneering
                                                young creative problem-solvers to   are still of great value; the process
                As a result, I had a lot of time on   learn, to be able to place yourself   becomes enhanced, richer when
                my hands, and did not quite know   in another person’s shoes, to   a network of people with different
                what to do with myself. One of my   come to understand what it is   expertise collaborate.
                longest collaborators, Leah Caplan,   like to feel and think like them.
                suggested I use this time to think   Designers practice empathy each   3. I conclude my talks about Design
                about how I think because, she   time they solve a problem for   the Life you Love by saying, “today
                said, “You think differently.” This   other people; however, everyone   there are no road maps, create
                way of thinking became my lifeline,   can learn to develop the skill.   your own road map to create
                and the beginning of my process,   We all have the capacity to   an original life.” The world is
                Deconstruction: Reconstruction.   develop our ability to empathize   changing so fast; traditional road
                In a way, the challenge became   with others, to become a more   maps of how to create a good
                an opportunity: to change my    creative, peaceful, and connected   life do not work anymore, which
                life and to formalize my process,   global culture.            is an incredible challenge and
                which, once in place, transformed                              a wonderful opportunity at the
                our business. Now we teach our   2. Collaboration is the other skill   same time. We can thoughtfully
                clients how to deconstruct and   for the 21st Century. Kids learn   design our own maps, create our
                reconstruct, which in turn develops   how to collaborate, a great   own pathways, rules, rituals, and
                deeper collaborations with design   ability. The act of individualistic   habits. The key is to embrace
                managers, value-driven design   thinking was of high value when   creativity, use an optimistic
                projects, and company culture. An   I was growing up and then,   approach with empathy for others
                incredibly difficult experience, albeit   initially, as a designer. Today   and ourselves, to collaborate with
                a blessing.                     the converse is true. The world   people in our lives, our family,
                                                benefits most from collaborative   friends and people we work with,
                Empathy, collaboration, and     thinking; together we are stronger   to design and live original lives.
                creativity are essential to you as a   with a balance of diverse and   An original life, is not that the
                21st Century Learner:           complementary thinking – we    definition of a life well lived?
                                                can pull each other up. Individual
                                                                                                                 ICAF.org



                                                                                                               33]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[PAUL







                                              HATCH








         ChildArt | October–December 2016  Paul Hatch is CEO of the Chicago branch of industrial design firm


               TEAMS Design, which he opened in 1998. TEAMS Design now has
               five branches with a total of over 1,000 design awards.

               In 2014, Paul founded Design House, a non-profit with a mission
               to help revitalize local manufacturing. He is also co-author of two




       34      books about the impact of Design and Technology on business.]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[My name is Paul Hatch, and I am   or improved products like power   projects on the side, so my day job
               the CEO of TEAMS Design. I studied   tools, appliances, mobile phones, or   is quite different – it’s all design
               industrial design in the United   footwear.                   and manufacturing, just in different
               Kingdom at a four-year art college.                           places and different ways.
               After graduating, I worked as an   In addition to my work at TEAMS, I
               industrial designer for five years at   also manage a project on the side   There are several people who have
               TEAMS Design in Germany and then   called DesignHouse. DesignHouse   influenced me, the most important
               in 1998 moved to Chicago to open   is a non-profit organization focused   being the late Bill Moggridge. Bill
               their U.S. branch.             on helping to revitalize local   was the co-founder of IDEO, a well-
                                              manufacturers within the United   known company in our industry.
               My official title is Chief Executive   States. For the most part, industrial   In 1989 while studying industrial
               Officer, which means I manage the   designers create mass-produced   design at college, Moggridge
               work that comes in, collaborate with   things made in factories in countries   was a guest lecturer and shared
               our in-house designers, talk with   such as China. The purpose of   his philosophy on design. I was
               clients, and offer ideas. Industrial   DesignHouse is to find ways to   already heading in the direction
               designers often develop innovative   bring some of that manufacturing   of industrial design, but what he
               ideas that have never existed before   back to the U.S. We help local   showed us opened my eyes to what
               and improve things that already   manufacturers understand how   user-centered design can truly be.
               exist. Based on ideas, we draw   design can them make something   User-centered design begins with
               and create things on paper and   better, more cost-efficient, or less   those who use and buy the product.
               make small-scale physical models.   expensive so that they can compete   The goal is to improve the impact
               Our job is to assist companies   with overseas manufacturers.   the product has on the user’s habits
               as they bring to consumers new   Everyone has their little passion   when they use the product and







































                                                                                                                 ICAF.org



                                                                                                               35]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[thus improve someone’s life. As   which was silver so users could   the audience stood around the
               designers, we have a responsibility   see it. The handle was a radical   circle and jeered or joined as they
               to make things more profitable for   white to create a feeling of reverse   chose.
               a company as well as better for the   coloration as well as a “swingful”
               user.                            look. I am proud that this design   We tested the experience that
                                                made it to market. With great   first night with twenty people; we
               Bill Moggridge had a substantial   effort, designers can make truly   had no idea what to expect. The
               impact on me then and now at     innovative ideas happen. One   audience was invigorated and
               TEAMS and DesignHouse. I am      must apply passion, make sense   excited, and wanted to repeat
               thankful for mentors and beacons   of complex information, and stand   the experience. We then offered
               like Bill Moggridge, who choose   up for their ideas. Design work is   regular meetups with an ever-
               to reach out to young people as   a challenge – without it, there is   increasing number of participants.
               they learn about design and life. It   no sense of achievement.   A local television station took
               is important to understand other                                interest and filmed one of our
               people’s perspectives, how they see   2. Fight Club was a pivotal idea   “fights,” which turned into a TV
               life.                            that came to life as a result of   show pilot proposal. While the
                                                a book club when we invited    show did not move forward, it
               There are three special          designers to meet up and discuss   was interesting to see how a little
               accomplishments I would like to   various books. We realized we   creative idea can grow into such
               share with you:                  lacked a sense of passion – that   a compelling experience. When
                                                is when we came up with Flight   we see the chance to create
               1. My first achievement took place   Club. Based on an illegal fistfight   and try out something new and
                 during an internship when I    movie, our version took on     worthwhile, sometimes it works
                 designed a cheese knife. I worked   similar passion, environment, and   and sometimes not. We can all
                 hard to get the details right – it   atmosphere. We channeled our   make a difference – take a few
                 had a nice ergonomic curvature   interactions via productive verbal   risks, apply good ideas, and aim
                 that worked well in the hand.   discourse rather than destructive   to change people’s lives for the
                 Coated with Teflon, the thin   physical contact. We designed the   better.
                 shape of the blade glides through   experience to be intense, rough   3. Designing the Bosch Power
         ChildArt | October–December 2016  from the frustration of slicing   “fights” in a darkened warehouse,   endeavor I’m very proud. Used
                 the cheese, unlike most knives
                                                and ready, and full of passion.
                 that stick. The inspiration came
                                                                               Box Jobsite Radio was another
                                                Similar to the movie, we held the
                 cheese and the messy process
                                                                               in the construction industry,
                                                used a single source of light, and
                 of scraping it off. The nonstick
                                                                               the Bosch Power Box Jobsite
                                                chalked a circle for two people
                 cheese knife cut as if it were
                                                                               Radio had to be rough and ready.
                                                to engage in a verbal debate on
                 slicing an apple. The blade itself
                                                                               During our research, we studied
                                                a chosen subject matter. Each
                 was black except the blade edge,
                                                                               electricians and carpenters; they
                                                stated his or her argument and
       36]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[I am thankful for
               mentors and beacons
               like Bill Moggridge,
               who choose to reach
               out to young people as
               they learn about de-
               sign and life.








                 were constantly sawing, drilling,
                 and cutting with many types of
                 power tools. Numerous cords
                 tangled everywhere because
                 they had multiple extensions
                 connected. We learned that
                 job sites had small, beaten-up,
                 cheap radios, often placed in a   up in the U.K., I faced a crossroad   Everyone is a designer; we all
                 corner next to the power supply.   dilemma when deciding which   are creative problem-solvers.
                 We found radios splashed with   direction to go after high school.   We naturally look at things with
                 concrete and dents.          I choose art college, and I am   judgment and are skeptical of
                                              amazed that my parents supported   certain things. We are annoyed if
               These insights led us to the concept   me. I do not regret choosing a   something does not work the way
               of creating a power extension unit   creative path, going to art college,   that we want it to, and we think
               that was also a radio. Additional   knowing that it meant specialized   about how it could work better. Each
               ideas bubbled up such as the need   curriculum without a focus on   one of us can learn to influence the
               for a large box to charge batteries,   math and science. I wanted to do   world around us, understand nature,
               mobile phones, or other items. We   something that I enjoyed and was   and nurture positive change. Begin
               wanted to ensure the success of the   passionate about, something that is   by noticing things around you. How
               design, so we articulated our vision,   personal to me and therefore I can   do you feel about them, how do
               made sure to include other people   do well. Initially, I thought I would   other people feel about them? When
               on the project, and communicated   do graphic design, but discovered I   you use something, does it feel like
               our plan to Bosch so all could see   wanted a field that would challenge   it is making your life easier in some
               the benefits of the design. Big   me to get better and better for   small way? How could it be more
               breakthrough ideas take a lot of   a lifetime. Initially, I explored   enjoyable or function better?
               work and energy – it was critical to   sculpture in 3-dimensional form,
               invite the right people to share in the   which transformed into functional   Record these memories; over time,
               passion. The result was beneficial   sculpture, solving problems, and   you will have reference points to
               because we faced the challenge   inventions – product design. I finally   help solve problems later. On a
               while reaching for success.    found a discipline that balanced my   daily basis, become more aware

                                              creative and rational learning needs.   of your surroundings—the things
               When I was 16 years old, I truly   I went with my gut as well as my   around you, the environment
               enjoyed math, science, and rational   head to make that decision, and I   around you—and constantly think
               thinking. Also, I was an artist at   am very thankful that my parents   about how the world could be a
               school and loved drawing comics   supported me in that decision at   better place. We all want to fit in
               at home on the weekends. Growing   such an early age.         to the future, even if that future is
                                                                             filled with the unknown.
                                                                                                                 ICAF.org


                                                                                                               37]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[A DESIGN-BASED

                                      GAME CHALLENGE






                                                                             by Courtney Bryant


               It is 8:30 a.m. on the first day of   design group. We discussed new   Returning to that worrisome first
               school. You approach your first   products they were developing for   day of class, my fourth graders
               class as a new fourth grader. You   teenage boys. I asked him if they   received their first Brief, all while I
               see many new faces. Your hands   had any plans to shift their design   wore a ridiculous contraption on my
               are sweaty, your mouth is dry, and   ideas to include teenage girls.   head. When I demonstrated how it
               you do not know why you are in the   A second or two passed and he   worked, they learned it was a Nerf
               Engineering Design class. What is   said, “Well, not exactly, but that’s a   Passer. Wide-eyed and quizzical
               Engineering Design you ask?    thought.”                      looks followed my every move as I
                                                                             modeled creative confidence – I can
               Fortunately, you do not have to   Later, I started thinking about that   wear something silly and will do so
               wonder for very long. Your teacher   conversation while I was redesigning  willingly if it helps me communicate
               has a plan!                    a challenge I had tackled during a   my fabulous idea.  My students will
                                              college design class. I re-imagined   remember this as a proud moment
               I imagine most students like feel   the challenge to become a wearable   just as they will remember the end of
               this as they enter the Design Lab   Nerf game piece to pass a small ball   the unit.
               at Drew Charter School for the   around from one person to another.
               first time. The learning space   Considering both girls and boys, I   Next, we began the “Need to Know”
               can seem a bit intimidating for   wondered about how to encourage   phase; we call it Research in our
               a newbie. Tools look scary, and   social and physical interaction   class. Students decided what they
               large tables obviously encourage   through the piece that they design.   knew already and what they needed
               group interaction – not your normal   I wanted to incorporate at least   to know to be successful. Then they
               looking classroom environment. No
                                              two different simple machines
                                                                             went on a hunt for answers. Students
         ChildArt | October–December 2016  can become comfortable with using   that used gravity and were made   masks. They measured head sizes.
               surprise, a different way of teaching
                                                                             observed real objects like hats and
                                              (like a wheel, pulley, screw, etc.)
               needs to take place so students
                                              of durable materials. When my
                                                                             Students studied simple machines,
               new tools and interacting with their
                                                                             and we experimented with real
                                              students engaged in the challenge,
               classmates all while practicing the
                                                                             simple machines in our TinkerYard
                                              they quickly realized this was an
               Design Process.
                                              individual project, but that they
                                                                             at school. Students wrapped up their
                                                                             research by making notes about what
                                              needed to communicate with each
               Enter the Nerf Passer Challenge.
                                              Dropping the ball is an epic fail that
               several years ago in their product
                                              everyone wants to avoid.
       38      A friend of mine worked at Nerf   other to achieve group success.   they found.]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[After conducting research, students   as each student dug deeper to   so that we could achieve success.
               began sketching ideas with pencil   confirm their hypothesis (plan of   They believed me; the can-do spirit
               and paper: Idea Development.   making something work). When   returned. Not on the next try or the
               Students sketched from multiple   their idea did not work as they   try after that, but soon they did it.
               viewpoints: front, side, top, bottom,   had hoped, they asked others for   You would have thought we won
               rear, etc. Then they received   help and used equipment (tools).   the Super Bowl. The designers wore
               feedback – all centered around ball   Students who would have likely   their Nerf crowns around school the
               safety, aesthetics (how it looks),   avoided one another other in the   rest of the day!
               end user appeal (how well it works   hallway ended up working together,
               while being used), and use of simple   united around a common goal. As   The Nerf Passer Challenge initiated
               machines. Students often changed   we neared the due date, students   a mindset (how you are thinking
               their sketches after receiving   repeatedly tested their products to   and feeling) shift: students
               feedback from their classmates and   ensure success. As they tried the   began to think of themselves as
               teacher.                       ball in their device, they engaged   designers.  Most of my students
                                              in the Test phase. Once students   will not become a professional
               Once they were happy with their   identified problems, they moved   designer, but the things that they
               sketches, students moved on to   into the next phase: Evaluation and   learned will serve them well in
               the next phase. First, students   Modification. Students corrected   any endeavor they undertake in
               generated a quick copy-paper,   issues and continued to evaluate the   the future. Students learned the
               small-scale Prototype. The small   performance of their passers. When   design process, how to creatively
               3-D model allowed others to    satisfied, they stepped in to advise   solve problems, how to conduct
               examine the benefits of the design   and help classmates. A can-do spirit   research, how to collaborate, how to
               before attachment takes place.   permeated and – due in part to a   communicate, how to prototype or
               Several copy-paper models were   group success mentality built on the   create a model of their thinking to
               necessary for some students    fact that we would not have success   test an idea. Additionally, students
               before they felt ready to advance to   unless every student played and   who participated in the project now
               the durable materials prototype. I   could pass – every single student   feel as though they can tackle any
               invited students to bring in “found”   finished.              task and they are frequently hungry
               materials. To level the playing field                         for more. Moreover, after completing
               and encourage design that is good   On Nerf Passing Day, every designer   the Nerf Passer Challenge with their
               for the environment, I discourage   wore their device and walked to the   teammates, students learned to
               students from buying supplies   flagpole. We received some weird   prepare for future projects because
               for the project. Instead, they used   looks and snickers from bystanders,   they learned to be supportive within
               recycled cardboard, chipboard,   but none of the designers seemed   a constructively critical classroom
               foam, and plastic containers to   to notice or care. We circled up in   culture. These students now know
               create their working prototype.   front of the flag, and each designer   that their teacher is not the only
               Students used hot glue and duct   stood up and explained how their   “smart” person in the room and
               tape to stick things together. Tools   device functioned. Designers were   that they all have the potential to
               that had once seemed scary now   encouraged to listen to their peers   offer a positive influence on their
               became necessary to construct their   so they could act as a support   classmate’s design. When students
               idea. My students asked me to train   system or coach during the passing   made that final pass of the ball
               them in the safe use of sanders,   experience. The ball made it through   on the last day of the unit, all
               saws, and drills.              the first four or five people and   culminated with satisfied grins –
                                              then fell. I told them they could try   because they are now empowered
               Throughout the Build process,   again – as many times as needed   to solve wicked problems.
               students interacted and provided
               feedback as they tested their ideas.
               The whirlwind of ideas about how
               to transfer the ball continuously                             Courtney Bryant has taught students
                                                                             in various settings in Cleveland,
               traveled from designer to designer                            Charlotte, and Atlanta. Currently, she
                                                                             is the STEAM Project Manager and    ICAF.org
                                                                             Engineering Design Teacher at Drew
                                                                             Charter School in Atlanta.        39]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[CERTIPORT

                           AND THE ICAF








                                                              Certiport selected the ICAF as Charitable Partner
                                                              for the 2016 Adobe Certified Associate Awards.
                                                              As an honored Charitable Partner, ICAF participated
                                                              in the 2016 Adobe Certified Associate (ACA) World
                                                              Championship presented by Certiport, Inc. in Orlando,
                                                              Florida. This global competition received more than
                                                              230,000 entries worldwide from 67 countries who
                                                              competed to demonstrate their mastery of Adobe
                                                              products. Thirty student finalists participated in the final
                                                              round of competition and designed a digital marketing flyer
                                                              for ICAF’s 6th Arts Olympiad using Adobe Photoshop CC,
                                                              Adobe Illustrator CC, and Adobe InDesign CC.

                                                              Assessment of the student’s design work included creative
                                                              and technical skills, as well as each competitor’s ability to
                                                              implement the ICAF’s vision and message. The competitors,
                                                              who ranged from ages 13 to 22, had an impressive sense
                                                              of mastery with Adobe products combined with incredible
                                                              creative talent. The students were professional, inspiring,
                                                              and exceeded our expectations.
















         ChildArt | October–December 2016  1ST PLACE   2ND PLACE             3RD PLACE












               from Mexico

       40      Lourdes Gimena Anquiano Bermúdez   Ng Hwa Ee Nicholas from Malaysia  Cheung Kuok Pan from Macau]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[CANNES LIONS


                                    AND THE ICAF









               Designers and advertising professionals from around   The winners were honored at an awards ceremony
               the world convene annually at the Cannes Lions in the   presided by the head of the jury, Mr. Ije Nwokorie, CEO of
               South of France. At this international festival of creativity   Wolff Olins in London, famous for designing the logo for
               in 2014, the organizers selected the ICAF as a “client” for   the London 2012 Olympics.
               the Young Lions Competition.
                                                              The jury was comprised of some of the world’s leading
               The ICAF asked the contestants to design a logo for its   designers and advertising executives.
               5th World Children’s Festival (WCF) scheduled to take
               place in Washington, D.C. in the summer of 2015. The   Now you can be the judge and tell us which of the three
               contestants were comprised of teams of two young   logo designs you like the most! Email us at childart@icaf
               designers each from ad agencies in 19 countries: Belarus,   .org or post your comments at Facebook.com/ICAF.org
               Brazil, China, Colombia, Costa Rica, Denmark, Dominican
               Republic, Germany, Greece, Italy, Japan, Nigeria, Norway,   To learn more about the World Children’s Festival, visit
               Poland, Portugal, Romania, Russia, Sri Lanka, and Sweden.   www.WorldChildrensFestival.org where you will discover
                                                              stories about WCF2015 – and please do join us at our
               The process took one full day to design the WCF logos.  next festival in June, 2019.



































               GOLD                           SILVER                        BRONZE
               Designed by Stefanie Golla and   Designed by Tobias Eriksson and Li Jian    Designed Eliu Bueno and Danilda Estevez
               Dominique Winkel of Kolle Rebbe    of Essen International in Sweden.  of Lowe Worldwide in Dominican Republic.
               in Germany.                                                                                       ICAF.org

                                                                                                               41]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[LEARNING FROM DESIGN!




















               Arnold Wasserman             Peter Scupelli         Mauro Porcini            John Edson
                Collective Invention    Carnigie Mellon University     PepsiCo                 LUNAR













                Debbie Millman              Megan Neese              Ayse Birsel            Paul Hatch
                  Design Matters         Renault-Nissan Alliance     Birsel + Seck         TEAMS Design














              Doris Wells-Papanek            Kathy Bonte            Robert Coven          Courtney Bryant
             Design Learning Network          DezignKidz            Cary Academy         Drew Charter School






                  ENGAGE                          CONTRIBUTE                         FOLLOW US




        The ICAF invites your participation in the   Please adopt the ICAF as your charity   FACEBOOK.com/ICAF.org
        6th Arts Olympiad, the world’s largest art   of choice by making a tax-deductible
        program for schoolchildren. Commencing   donation today. You can support the    TWITTER.com/ICAF_org
        in classrooms worldwide in 2017, the Arts   ICAF when you purchase from Amazon
        Olympiad leads to community celebrations   or eBay, donate through JustGive.org    INSTAGRAM @intlchildartfoundation
        in 2018, followed by the 6th World Children’s   or mail us a check at:   EMAIL childart@icaf.org
        Festival in 2019, and culminates in 2020
        with a traveling exhibition of the winning   International Child Art Foundation   ONLINE www.icaf.org
        artworks. Please visit www.icaf.org/  P.O. Box 58133
        ArtsOlympiad/ for more information.  Washington, DC 20037, USA           CALL  202.530.1000]]></page></pages></Search>