<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="40"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[From the Editor                                        From the Guest Editor                                           VOLUME 20, ISSUE 2, NUMBER 60                                                     OCTOBER – DECEMBER 2020


                                                               It is an honor to serve as guest editor of the Adolescent      CONTENTS
                                                               Brain Cognitive Development (ABCD) Study Issue of ChildArt.
        [I]t never ceases to amaze me that all the richness of   When we began this journey in winter 2019, I had a vision that
         our mental life—all our feelings, our emotions, our   we could bring the science of the ABCD Study to life through
         thoughts, our ambitions, our love life, our religious   the artistic lens of the researchers, families, and our partners.     Letters from the Editors    •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  2
    “ sentiments and even what each of us regards as           I am humbled to see this vision realized via the contributions
         his own intimate private self—is simply the activity   and enthusiasm from colleagues at the International Child Art          Science and Art Come Together in the National Institutes of Health’s ABCD Study   •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •   4
                                       ”
          of these little specks of jelly in your heads, in your   Foundation (ICAF), the National Endowment for the Arts, the
                  brains. There is nothing else.               National Institute on Drug Abuse, and many others.                      Understanding Your Amazing Brain: The Promise of the ABCD Study     •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  6
                             — V. S. Ramachandran              This issue of ChildArt introduces the reader to the ABCD Study, the     Your Adolescent Brain: It’s a Construction Zone   •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •   8
                                                               intersection of art and neuroscience, and the potential impact of
                                                               the arts on health and well-being. The ABCD Study has promise
                                                               to bridge many different areas of science and yield discoveries
        Today we face the uncertainties and suffering                                                                                     Art + Science = Power                                                                                                                             9
        caused by Covid-19. Soon, advances in artificial       beyond what we had originally imagined. With each year and
                                                               each data release, we are introduced to the opportunities this
        intelligence, automation, and robotics will bring      study opens for the research community toward something                    Artist Profile: Craig Alan   •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 12
        about what we call the fourth industrial revolution,   greater and more impactful. This issue begins to demonstrate the   1
        which will blend our physical, digital, and biological   power of science and the power of art—and when combined, this            Connecting with STEM through Movement and Dance    •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 14
        worlds. This will fundamentally alter the way we       force can instill hope, understanding, and meaning.
        live and work, think and learn, imagine and create.                                                                               Music’s Harmony on the Developing Brain: Data from the ABCD Study   •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 16
        Socially appropriate responses and solutions to these   “ Science and art have in common intense seeing, the wide-                Scientist Profile: John Iverson   •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 19
                                                                   eyed observing that generates empirical information.
        challenges require greater creativity and mutual                                                    ”
        empathy. This makes a deeper understanding of the                                            —Edward Tufte
        human brain imperative.                                To Ashfaq Ishaq and Katty Guerami at ICAF, thank you for
                                                               entrusting our team—we are grateful for your collegiality                  Essence of Art = Expression                                                          20
        We are delighted that the National Institutes of Health
        is funding a $400 million research project on the brain   and for continuously recognizing the power of the arts for              Artist Profile: Srinjoy Gangopadhyay     •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 22
        and human development, involving nearly 12,000         the well-being of children. To Sunil Iyengar at the National      2
                                                               Endowment for the Arts, thank you for joining us as we explored
        schoolchildren over ten years. Within the pages of     and mastered this inaugural and successful collaboration.                  In Her Own Words: A conversation with Melissa Menzer, Ph.D.   •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 24
        this issue of ChildArt you will get a first look at what   To Mehron Zadeh at Connect Contemporary, Inc., thank you
        researchers are learning, what questions continue to be   for answering my call for help and connecting us with Craig             When Science Meets Art   •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 26
        explored, and what contributes to brain health.        Alan and Srinjoy Gangopadhyay—whose artistic journeys are                  When Art Meets Science   •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 28
        We are most grateful to the NIH for partnering with    inspiring and empowering. To Eric Wargo (Assistant Guest Editor)
        us to bring to you this special issue of ChildArt      and Oslo (Designer Extraordinaire): thank you; without your
        to highlight the Adolescent Brain Cognitive            technical and creative “magic” this issue would not have come
        Development  (ABCD) Study and the intersection of      together as beautifully as it did. To the many authors and artistic        Neuroscience = Art                                                                    30
                  SM
        the arts and neuroscience.                             contributors—thank you for your patience; this would not have     3
                                                               been possible without your dedication to the ABCD Study and the            How Neuroscience Helps Answer the Question: What Is Beauty?   •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 32
        We thank the ABCD Study® families, researchers, and    value of the arts in development.
        staff for their contributions; the scientists and artists   And to you, the reader, I hope you enjoy, discover, and create...the      The ABCD Data Treasure Chest   •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 35
        that share our enthusiasm for the arts through their   opportunities are endless.
        contributions; and Dr. Katia Delrahim Howlett for
        putting this special issue together as Guest Editor.                                                                           Resources    •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 38
        You will enjoy learning something new about yourself
        and others because one thing we all share is the                                                                               Credits    •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 39
        human brain.                                              Katia Delrahim Howlett, Ph.D., M.P.P., M.B.A.
                                                                     Deputy Director, Division of Extramural Research
                                                                               National Institute on Drug Abuse, NIH           Disclaimer: Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development Study is supported by grants from the National Institutes of Health (NIH), but the content of this magazine does
                                                                                                                               not necessarily reflect the views of NIH. References or links in this magazine to an external website or any specific commercial products, processes, services, manufac-
                                                                                                                               turers, or companies do not constitute endorsement or recommendation by the NIH or any of the ABCD Study Sites.
                                                                Learn more about the developing teen brain and get answers      ABCD Study®, Teen Brains. Today’s Science. Brighter Future.®, and the ABCD Study Logos are registered marks of the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services
                                                                     to your questions about drugs and your body at                      (HHS). Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development  Study, is a service mark of the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services (HHS).
                                                                                                                                                                       SM
                               Ashfaq Ishaq, Ph.D.                          teens.drugabuse.gov/childart.                          The views and opinions expressed in this Special Issue are those of the authors only and do not necessarily represent the views, official policy, or position
                                                                                                                                                    of the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services or any of its affiliated institutions or agencies.]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[From the Editor  From the Guest Editor  VOLUME 20, ISSUE 2, NUMBER 60                    OCTOBER – DECEMBER 2020


 It is an honor to serve as guest editor of the Adolescent   CONTENTS
 Brain Cognitive Development (ABCD) Study Issue of ChildArt.
 [I]t never ceases to amaze me that all the richness of   When we began this journey in winter 2019, I had a vision that
 our mental life—all our feelings, our emotions, our   we could bring the science of the ABCD Study to life through
 thoughts, our ambitions, our love life, our religious   the artistic lens of the researchers, families, and our partners.   Letters from the Editors    •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  2
 “ sentiments and even what each of us regards as   I am humbled to see this vision realized via the contributions
 his own intimate private self—is simply the activity   and enthusiasm from colleagues at the International Child Art   Science and Art Come Together in the National Institutes of Health’s ABCD Study   •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •   4
 ”
 of these little specks of jelly in your heads, in your   Foundation (ICAF), the National Endowment for the Arts, the
 brains. There is nothing else.  National Institute on Drug Abuse, and many others.  Understanding Your Amazing Brain: The Promise of the ABCD Study     •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  6
 — V. S. Ramachandran  This issue of ChildArt introduces the reader to the ABCD Study, the   Your Adolescent Brain: It’s a Construction Zone   •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •   8
 intersection of art and neuroscience, and the potential impact of
 the arts on health and well-being. The ABCD Study has promise
 to bridge many different areas of science and yield discoveries
 Today we face the uncertainties and suffering      Art + Science = Power                                                                                                                             9
 caused by Covid-19. Soon, advances in artificial   beyond what we had originally imagined. With each year and
 each data release, we are introduced to the opportunities this
 intelligence, automation, and robotics will bring   study opens for the research community toward something      Artist Profile: Craig Alan   •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 12
 about what we call the fourth industrial revolution,   greater and more impactful. This issue begins to demonstrate the   1
 which will blend our physical, digital, and biological   power of science and the power of art—and when combined, this      Connecting with STEM through Movement and Dance    •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 14
 worlds. This will fundamentally alter the way we   force can instill hope, understanding, and meaning.
 live and work, think and learn, imagine and create.      Music’s Harmony on the Developing Brain: Data from the ABCD Study   •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 16
 Socially appropriate responses and solutions to these   “ Science and art have in common intense seeing, the wide-     Scientist Profile: John Iverson   •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 19
 eyed observing that generates empirical information.
 challenges require greater creativity and mutual   ”
 empathy. This makes a deeper understanding of the   —Edward Tufte
 human brain imperative.  To Ashfaq Ishaq and Katty Guerami at ICAF, thank you for
 entrusting our team—we are grateful for your collegiality      Essence of Art = Expression                                                          20
 We are delighted that the National Institutes of Health
 is funding a $400 million research project on the brain   and for continuously recognizing the power of the arts for      Artist Profile: Srinjoy Gangopadhyay     •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 22
 and human development, involving nearly 12,000   the well-being of children. To Sunil Iyengar at the National   2
 Endowment for the Arts, thank you for joining us as we explored
 schoolchildren over ten years. Within the pages of   and mastered this inaugural and successful collaboration.      In Her Own Words: A conversation with Melissa Menzer, Ph.D.   •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 24
 this issue of ChildArt you will get a first look at what   To Mehron Zadeh at Connect Contemporary, Inc., thank you
 researchers are learning, what questions continue to be   for answering my call for help and connecting us with Craig      When Science Meets Art   •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 26
 explored, and what contributes to brain health.   Alan and Srinjoy Gangopadhyay—whose artistic journeys are      When Art Meets Science   •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 28
 We are most grateful to the NIH for partnering with   inspiring and empowering. To Eric Wargo (Assistant Guest Editor)
 us to bring to you this special issue of ChildArt   and Oslo (Designer Extraordinaire): thank you; without your
 to highlight the Adolescent Brain Cognitive   technical and creative “magic” this issue would not have come
 Development  (ABCD) Study and the intersection of   together as beautifully as it did. To the many authors and artistic      Neuroscience = Art                                                                    30
 SM
 the arts and neuroscience.  contributors—thank you for your patience; this would not have   3
 been possible without your dedication to the ABCD Study and the      How Neuroscience Helps Answer the Question: What Is Beauty?   •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 32
 We thank the ABCD Study® families, researchers, and   value of the arts in development.
 staff for their contributions; the scientists and artists   And to you, the reader, I hope you enjoy, discover, and create...the      The ABCD Data Treasure Chest   •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 35
 that share our enthusiasm for the arts through their   opportunities are endless.
 contributions; and Dr. Katia Delrahim Howlett for
 putting this special issue together as Guest Editor.  Resources    •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 38
 You will enjoy learning something new about yourself
 and others because one thing we all share is the   Credits    •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  •  • 39
 human brain.  Katia Delrahim Howlett, Ph.D., M.P.P., M.B.A.
 Deputy Director, Division of Extramural Research
 National Institute on Drug Abuse, NIH  Disclaimer: Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development Study is supported by grants from the National Institutes of Health (NIH), but the content of this magazine does
        not necessarily reflect the views of NIH. References or links in this magazine to an external website or any specific commercial products, processes, services, manufac-
        turers, or companies do not constitute endorsement or recommendation by the NIH or any of the ABCD Study Sites.
 Learn more about the developing teen brain and get answers    ABCD Study®, Teen Brains. Today’s Science. Brighter Future.®, and the ABCD Study Logos are registered marks of the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services
 to your questions about drugs and your body at    (HHS). Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development  Study, is a service mark of the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services (HHS).
                                                SM
 Ashfaq Ishaq, Ph.D.  teens.drugabuse.gov/childart.   The views and opinions expressed in this Special Issue are those of the authors only and do not necessarily represent the views, official policy, or position
                             of the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services or any of its affiliated institutions or agencies.]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[And now we know that art also heals. Listening to
        Science and Art Come Together in                                                                                       music, for example, produces changes in the brain and
                                                                                                                               body that can reduce stress and promote psychological
                                                                                                                               well-being, which in turn has a beneficial impact on
        the National Institutes of Health’s                                                                                    physical health. Making music or drawing or creating
                                                                                                                               art in other ways also has health benefits. Performing
        ABCD Study                                                                                                             with or for other people can connect us directly,
                                                                                                                               but even creating or enjoying art on our own can
                                                                                                                               be healing. It may be that some of the therapeutic
                                                                                                                               benefits of appreciating and making art come from
                                                                                                                               how it enhances our feeling of human connection and
        Art is one of the most basic, and oldest, human        letters and words. But                                          belonging even in solitude.
        activities. Forty thousand years ago, humans living    we also communicate
        in what is now southern Germany carved human and       with our bodies, and                                            Art and Science
        imaginative human-animal figurines from mammoths’      with pictures and
        ivory. They painstakingly fashioned flutes from the bones   objects and songs.                                         In my work life, I’m a scientist who studies the brain. But
        of eagles, so we know they played and enjoyed music.   Thus, we are able to                                            in my spare time, I’m a painter. I like to create imaginary
        Meanwhile, humans in France painted realistic horses,   express our inner                                              landscapes, such as “Childhood Landscape” (left) and                      “City Landscape” by Nora Volkow
        bison, and lions on the walls of caves—paintings that   experience. Art creates                                        “City Landscape” (right).
        the famous Spanish artist Pablo Picasso thought were   a special kind of social                                        Science and art are similar in many ways. Both an      New York City at night. I enjoyed looking at the windows
        unsurpassed by any paintings made since then.          interaction between                                             artist and a scientist must be able to think creatively, to   and seeing people interacting with one another in words I
                                                               the person who
        Art defines us as a species—no other animal makes                                                                      find hidden associations, and to imagine new solutions   couldn’t hear. Yet we were connected, because we were all
        pictures or sculptures or music as we know it, even our   creates an artwork                                           to problems. Then, they both have to figure out the most   experiencing the same moment in time.
        closest primate relatives, chimpanzees and bonobos.*    and the person who                                             elegant way to experiment and test their solutions. An
                                                     1
        Our ability to imagine and make symbols is unique, and   receives it.                  “Childhood Landscape”           artwork can feel like an experiment—it might attempt to   Butterflies of the Soul
        it starts when we’re very young children. When a toddler   The feeling of awe                 by Nora Volkow           uncover a hidden perspective, create a new association, or
        creatively transforms a spoon into an airplane or a box into   and mystical connection                                 investigate a complex feeling.                         In other ways, however, art and science are very different
        a house, these are early symbols; they’ll use many others   that art can produce is                                    When I paint, I allow unseen shapes to guide the contours   from each other. Science is a collective effort that proceeds
        throughout their life to communicate, understand, and   a humanizing force. When we listen to a piece of music,        of the colors and forms in ways that feel right to me   cautiously in investigating problems, while art can be
        manage their physical and social world. Imagination is play   admire a painting, or read a novel, we’re interacting with   emotionally. Above are two paintings that show how I   very personal and playful. In science, the aim is to explore
        with a purpose; it plays a crucial behind-the-scenes role in   the mind of the person who created it, via the sensations   uncover feelings and perceptions by allowing these shapes   and understand reality, while art can create a completely
        our ability to think.                                  and the emotions in our body that the work elicits.             to emerge. The painting at the left is my rendering of a   new reality. The artist has the freedom to explore and
                                                                                                                                                                                      understand the world in a new way. Those new ways of
        Art is not only something we do; it is something we need.   Through experiencing art, we have special access to the    huge yellow wall in the house I grew up in. As a child, I   understanding can then inspire the scientist to observe the
        It’s the most basic form of culture—the complex systems   experiences of other human beings, even ones whose           enjoyed looking at that wall. The paint was peeling and the   world differently, too.
        of symbols we share with other people. Culture allows us   lives may be very different from ours or who lived in other   color in some places had been changed by the rain; I could
        to coordinate our activities with others and cooperate with   times in history. In this way, it activates our imagination and   see a variety of creatures lurking in those flaws.    Some people are both scientists and artists, including in
        them. Humans are social creatures; we’re totally dependent   enables us to empathize while expanding our experience.   The painting at the right is inspired by the landscapes of   my own field of neuroscience, the study of the brain and
        on interaction with others. We communicate our feelings   Society, culture, and civility—cooperation with our fellow                                                          nervous system. Almost 150 years ago, a pathologist in
                                                                                                                                                                                                                     2
        and intentions to them with the symbols of language—   humans—would be unthinkable without art.                                                                               Spain named Santiago Ramon y Cajal  observed unique
                                                                                                                                                                                      cells in tissues from animal brains under a microscope. He
                                                                                                                                                                                      was the first to describe the tree-like shape of nerve cells
                                                                                                                                                                                      (or neurons) and the amazingly complex ways they connect
                            Nora D. Volkow, M.D.                                                                                                                                      with each other. To share his discoveries, he made exquisite
                            Director, National Institute on Drug Abuse                                                                                                                ink drawings of neurons, allowing other people to see for
                            National Institutes of Health                                                                                                                             the first time the sublimity of the brain at the cellular level.
                                                                                                                                                                                      Today, his drawings are also recognized as works of art.
                                                                                                                                                                                      Ramon y Cajal didn’t yet know exactly how neurons
                                                                                                                                                                                      worked or communicated with each other. But what he
        * Bowerbirds in Australia and New Guinea construct house installations to attract a mate. Some of these are quite beautiful and are considered by
         some people to be artistic creations, although they are constrained by their unique purpose. This is different from the “open” purpose of human art.                         saw through his microscope enabled him to sense what
        1  https://www.discovermagazine.com/planet-earth/how-closely-related-are-humans-to-apes and https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2012/06/                                          neuroscientists now take for granted: that these amazingly
         bonobos-join-chimps-closest-human-relatives#:~:text=Ever%20since%20researchers%20sequenced%20the,them%20our%20closest%20                                                     complex structures are the very basis of everyone’s
         living%20relatives
        2  https://www.famousscientists.org/santiago-ramon-y-cajal/                                                                                                                                   Continued on page 37]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[And now we know that art also heals. Listening to
 Science and Art Come Together in   music, for example, produces changes in the brain and
        body that can reduce stress and promote psychological
        well-being, which in turn has a beneficial impact on
 the National Institutes of Health’s   physical health. Making music or drawing or creating
        art in other ways also has health benefits. Performing
 ABCD Study  with or for other people can connect us directly,
        but even creating or enjoying art on our own can
        be healing. It may be that some of the therapeutic
        benefits of appreciating and making art come from
        how it enhances our feeling of human connection and
 Art is one of the most basic, and oldest, human   letters and words. But   belonging even in solitude.
 activities. Forty thousand years ago, humans living   we also communicate
 in what is now southern Germany carved human and   with our bodies, and   Art and Science
 imaginative human-animal figurines from mammoths’   with pictures and
 ivory. They painstakingly fashioned flutes from the bones   objects and songs.   In my work life, I’m a scientist who studies the brain. But
 of eagles, so we know they played and enjoyed music.   Thus, we are able to   in my spare time, I’m a painter. I like to create imaginary
 Meanwhile, humans in France painted realistic horses,   express our inner   landscapes, such as “Childhood Landscape” (left) and   “City Landscape” by Nora Volkow
 bison, and lions on the walls of caves—paintings that   experience. Art creates   “City Landscape” (right).
 the famous Spanish artist Pablo Picasso thought were   a special kind of social   Science and art are similar in many ways. Both an   New York City at night. I enjoyed looking at the windows
 unsurpassed by any paintings made since then.   interaction between   artist and a scientist must be able to think creatively, to   and seeing people interacting with one another in words I
 the person who
 Art defines us as a species—no other animal makes   find hidden associations, and to imagine new solutions   couldn’t hear. Yet we were connected, because we were all
 pictures or sculptures or music as we know it, even our   creates an artwork   to problems. Then, they both have to figure out the most   experiencing the same moment in time.
 closest primate relatives, chimpanzees and bonobos.*    and the person who   elegant way to experiment and test their solutions. An
 1
 Our ability to imagine and make symbols is unique, and   receives it.   “Childhood Landscape”    artwork can feel like an experiment—it might attempt to   Butterflies of the Soul
 it starts when we’re very young children. When a toddler   The feeling of awe   by Nora Volkow  uncover a hidden perspective, create a new association, or
 creatively transforms a spoon into an airplane or a box into   and mystical connection   investigate a complex feeling.   In other ways, however, art and science are very different
 a house, these are early symbols; they’ll use many others   that art can produce is   When I paint, I allow unseen shapes to guide the contours   from each other. Science is a collective effort that proceeds
 throughout their life to communicate, understand, and   a humanizing force. When we listen to a piece of music,   of the colors and forms in ways that feel right to me   cautiously in investigating problems, while art can be
 manage their physical and social world. Imagination is play   admire a painting, or read a novel, we’re interacting with   emotionally. Above are two paintings that show how I   very personal and playful. In science, the aim is to explore
 with a purpose; it plays a crucial behind-the-scenes role in   the mind of the person who created it, via the sensations   uncover feelings and perceptions by allowing these shapes   and understand reality, while art can create a completely
 our ability to think.   and the emotions in our body that the work elicits.   to emerge. The painting at the left is my rendering of a   new reality. The artist has the freedom to explore and
                                                               understand the world in a new way. Those new ways of
 Art is not only something we do; it is something we need.   Through experiencing art, we have special access to the   huge yellow wall in the house I grew up in. As a child, I   understanding can then inspire the scientist to observe the
 It’s the most basic form of culture—the complex systems   experiences of other human beings, even ones whose   enjoyed looking at that wall. The paint was peeling and the   world differently, too.
 of symbols we share with other people. Culture allows us   lives may be very different from ours or who lived in other   color in some places had been changed by the rain; I could
 to coordinate our activities with others and cooperate with   times in history. In this way, it activates our imagination and   see a variety of creatures lurking in those flaws.    Some people are both scientists and artists, including in
 them. Humans are social creatures; we’re totally dependent   enables us to empathize while expanding our experience.   The painting at the right is inspired by the landscapes of   my own field of neuroscience, the study of the brain and
 on interaction with others. We communicate our feelings   Society, culture, and civility—cooperation with our fellow   nervous system. Almost 150 years ago, a pathologist in
                                                                                              2
 and intentions to them with the symbols of language—   humans—would be unthinkable without art.   Spain named Santiago Ramon y Cajal  observed unique
                                                               cells in tissues from animal brains under a microscope. He
                                                               was the first to describe the tree-like shape of nerve cells
                                                               (or neurons) and the amazingly complex ways they connect
 Nora D. Volkow, M.D.                                          with each other. To share his discoveries, he made exquisite
 Director, National Institute on Drug Abuse                    ink drawings of neurons, allowing other people to see for
 National Institutes of Health                                 the first time the sublimity of the brain at the cellular level.
                                                               Today, his drawings are also recognized as works of art.
                                                               Ramon y Cajal didn’t yet know exactly how neurons
                                                               worked or communicated with each other. But what he
 * Bowerbirds in Australia and New Guinea construct house installations to attract a mate. Some of these are quite beautiful and are considered by
 some people to be artistic creations, although they are constrained by their unique purpose. This is different from the “open” purpose of human art.  saw through his microscope enabled him to sense what
 1  https://www.discovermagazine.com/planet-earth/how-closely-related-are-humans-to-apes and https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2012/06/  neuroscientists now take for granted: that these amazingly
 bonobos-join-chimps-closest-human-relatives#:~:text=Ever%20since%20researchers%20sequenced%20the,them%20our%20closest%20  complex structures are the very basis of everyone’s
 living%20relatives
 2  https://www.famousscientists.org/santiago-ramon-y-cajal/                   Continued on page 37]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Understanding Your Amazing                                                                                             puts some people at risk for health problems, and to learn   What is MRI?

                                                                                                                               what makes some people able to recover from difficult
        Brain: The Promise of the                                                                                              experiences more easily than other people do.             MRI, short for magnetic resonance imaging, is a
                                                                                                                               In March 2020, all of our lives changed dramatically
                                                                                                                                                                                         procedure that uses magnets to take three-dimensional
                                                                                                                               because of the coronavirus called COVID-19. This gave
                                                                                                                                                                                         (3D) pictures of the body. MRI scans do not use radiation
        ABCD Study                                                                                                             the ABCD Study researchers an unexpected opportunity      or x-rays, and they’re safe and painless. Researchers in
                                                                                                                               to learn how kids’ and teens’ experiences related to the
                                                                                                                                                                                         the ABCD Study use MRI to collect 3D images of the
                                                                                                                               COVID-19 pandemic affect them now and in the future.
                                                                                                                               Because the COVID-19 situation is always changing, the    brain. Some of the MRI scans in the ABCD Study collect
                                                                                                                                                                                         pictures of the brain that show details about its physical
                                                                                                                               researchers are asking the ABCD Study participants and    structures. Another type of MRI, called functional MRI
        The human brain is the most complex organ in           researchers in the fields of adolescent development,            families questions about these experiences every month.   (fMRI), lets researchers see which parts of the brain are
        the body. It’s made up of eighty-five billion nerve cells,   psychology, and neuroscience to launch the Adolescent     In the four years since the ABCD Study began,             active while a person plays a game or does a task.
        or neurons. Neurons in the brain connect to each other,   Brain Cognitive Development Study (ABCD Study).              researchers have already started to understand more about
        creating a complex network that allows people to make   Starting in 2016, ABCD Study researchers enrolled nearly       how certain traits and experiences (such as sleep, art and   The MRI scanner is about the size of a play tunnel. Once
        art, feel emotion, and solve problems. Every one of us has a   12,000 kids ages nine and ten. For ten years, researchers   music education, family conflict, and screen time) relate   a person is inside, the researcher checks to make sure
        unique brain network that makes us who we are.         will work with these youth to understand the different          to brain differences and other outcomes like the ability to   the person feels as comfortable as possible. Then the
        When you’re born, you have a different brain than you’ll   influences that affect their brain development and their    learn and understand new information, and problems with   researcher moves to a room nearby to take the pictures.
                                                                                                                                                                                         During the scans, the person must lie perfectly still so
        have as an adult. A baby’s brain starts out with at least 100   general health. Researchers will use magnetic resonance   mental health. [To learn about one of these findings, check   the machine can collect very clear images of their brain.
        billion neurons. By age three, your brain has approximately   imaging (MRI; see box) to study the kids’ brain structure and   out the article in this issue titled, “Music’s Harmony on the   The MRI scanner makes a lot of noise, which is caused
        one quadrillion connections called “synapses”—many more   function, and their biological and behavioral development.   Developing Brain: Data From the ABCD Study.”]             by vibrating metal coils inside the machine. It can
        than you need. As you grow and your brain develops, some   Researchers use questionnaires to ask youth about their     So far, most of these studies have only looked at these   sound like a foghorn! Many people wear earbuds and
        synapses get stronger, but many others are gradually lost.   physical and mental health; their experiences with sports,   things at a single point in time. But because the ABCD   headphones to block out the sound.
        This is normal! By the time you’re twelve years old, your   art and music classes, and any drug use; and their family,   Study is collecting data over many years, researchers will be
        brain has reached its full physical size—but, as you have   school, and neighborhood environments, among other         able to examine how these experiences change the brain    How does MRI see the
        new experiences as a teen and young adult, your brain   things.                                                        as people grow up. By helping us examine and understand
        connections continue to be refined well into your twenties.                                                            the amazingly complex brain, the ABCD Study may help      brain so well?
                                                               Researchers will also ask them to play certain games to
        We know all this, and much more, thanks to             measure their brain and cognitive function and will collect     future generations of teens to live better, healthier lives.   A computer program uses the MRI pictures of the brain
        neuroscience—the study of the nervous system, which    biospecimens (such as blood, saliva, etc.) to examine the                                                                 to create high-definition 3D images. The images show
        includes your brain. But there’s still a lot to figure out,   effects of genetics, puberty, and exposure to things such                                                                  the physical structures in the brain from top
        especially about the developing brain in children and   as heavy metals (lead, for example) and drugs of abuse                                                                           to bottom and from side to side. Pictures from
        teens. That’s because new experiences influence how    on brain development. The researchers will continue to                                                                            an fMRI can show what the brain looks like
        the brain develops. And kids and teens have a lot of new   monitor these areas every year or two until the youth are                                                                     while a person is thinking about something
        experiences! Whether those experiences are exciting,   nineteen and twenty years old.                                                                                                    like a funny joke or a difficult math problem,
        baffling, overwhelming, or frightening, they shape who                                                                                                                                   or while playing a game. When part of the
        you are and who you’ll become—usually without you even   The Promise of the ABCD Study                                                                                                   brain is working hard, it needs more oxygen,
        realizing it.
                                                               The youth participating in the ABCD Study are as diverse                                                                          just like your lungs need more oxygen when
        A look into the growing brain                          as the United States. Approximately half are female, 15                                                                           they’re working hard. fMRI lets scientists
                                                               percent are Black, 20 percent are Hispanic, and 52 percent                                                                        see when a part of the brain is using more
        How exactly do these changes happen in the brain?      are white. Participants come from seventeen different                                                                             or less oxygen. For example, when you do
        Scientists and researchers at the National Institutes   states, from big cities and small towns, and from different                                                                      a math problem, more oxygen flows to the
        of Health (NIH) are trying to answer this question and   economic backgrounds. A large and diverse study like this                                                                       parts of your brain that are working to solve
        many others. The NIH—the government agency that        makes it possible to investigate what contributes to normal                                                                       the problem. If you do this while having an
        supports research about the body and behavior—funded   differences in brain development, to understand what                                                                              fMRI, scientists can see your brain “in action.”
                                                                                                                                                                                                 So, fMRI helps scientists see which parts of
                                                                                                                                                                                                 the brain are important for thinking about
                     By Gayathri J. Dowling, Ph.D.                                                                                                                                               different things.
                     Director, Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development Study
                     Division of Extramural Research
                     National Institute on Drug Abuse
                     National Institutes of Health                                                                                                                         Art by Gaya Dowling]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Understanding Your Amazing   puts some people at risk for health problems, and to learn   What is MRI?

        what makes some people able to recover from difficult
 Brain: The Promise of the   experiences more easily than other people do.   MRI, short for magnetic resonance imaging, is a
        In March 2020, all of our lives changed dramatically
                                                                  procedure that uses magnets to take three-dimensional
        because of the coronavirus called COVID-19. This gave
                                                                  (3D) pictures of the body. MRI scans do not use radiation
 ABCD Study  the ABCD Study researchers an unexpected opportunity   or x-rays, and they’re safe and painless. Researchers in
        to learn how kids’ and teens’ experiences related to the
                                                                  the ABCD Study use MRI to collect 3D images of the
        COVID-19 pandemic affect them now and in the future.
        Because the COVID-19 situation is always changing, the    brain. Some of the MRI scans in the ABCD Study collect
                                                                  pictures of the brain that show details about its physical
        researchers are asking the ABCD Study participants and    structures. Another type of MRI, called functional MRI
 The human brain is the most complex organ in   researchers in the fields of adolescent development,   families questions about these experiences every month.  (fMRI), lets researchers see which parts of the brain are
 the body. It’s made up of eighty-five billion nerve cells,   psychology, and neuroscience to launch the Adolescent   In the four years since the ABCD Study began,   active while a person plays a game or does a task.
 or neurons. Neurons in the brain connect to each other,   Brain Cognitive Development Study (ABCD Study).  researchers have already started to understand more about
 creating a complex network that allows people to make   Starting in 2016, ABCD Study researchers enrolled nearly   how certain traits and experiences (such as sleep, art and   The MRI scanner is about the size of a play tunnel. Once
 art, feel emotion, and solve problems. Every one of us has a   12,000 kids ages nine and ten. For ten years, researchers   music education, family conflict, and screen time) relate   a person is inside, the researcher checks to make sure
 unique brain network that makes us who we are.   will work with these youth to understand the different   to brain differences and other outcomes like the ability to   the person feels as comfortable as possible. Then the
 When you’re born, you have a different brain than you’ll   influences that affect their brain development and their   learn and understand new information, and problems with   researcher moves to a room nearby to take the pictures.
                                                                  During the scans, the person must lie perfectly still so
 have as an adult. A baby’s brain starts out with at least 100   general health. Researchers will use magnetic resonance   mental health. [To learn about one of these findings, check   the machine can collect very clear images of their brain.
 billion neurons. By age three, your brain has approximately   imaging (MRI; see box) to study the kids’ brain structure and   out the article in this issue titled, “Music’s Harmony on the   The MRI scanner makes a lot of noise, which is caused
 one quadrillion connections called “synapses”—many more   function, and their biological and behavioral development.   Developing Brain: Data From the ABCD Study.”]   by vibrating metal coils inside the machine. It can
 than you need. As you grow and your brain develops, some   Researchers use questionnaires to ask youth about their   So far, most of these studies have only looked at these   sound like a foghorn! Many people wear earbuds and
 synapses get stronger, but many others are gradually lost.   physical and mental health; their experiences with sports,   things at a single point in time. But because the ABCD   headphones to block out the sound.
 This is normal! By the time you’re twelve years old, your   art and music classes, and any drug use; and their family,   Study is collecting data over many years, researchers will be
 brain has reached its full physical size—but, as you have   school, and neighborhood environments, among other   able to examine how these experiences change the brain   How does MRI see the
 new experiences as a teen and young adult, your brain   things.   as people grow up. By helping us examine and understand
 connections continue to be refined well into your twenties.   the amazingly complex brain, the ABCD Study may help   brain so well?
 Researchers will also ask them to play certain games to
 We know all this, and much more, thanks to   measure their brain and cognitive function and will collect   future generations of teens to live better, healthier lives.   A computer program uses the MRI pictures of the brain
 neuroscience—the study of the nervous system, which   biospecimens (such as blood, saliva, etc.) to examine the   to create high-definition 3D images. The images show
 includes your brain. But there’s still a lot to figure out,   effects of genetics, puberty, and exposure to things such   the physical structures in the brain from top
 especially about the developing brain in children and   as heavy metals (lead, for example) and drugs of abuse   to bottom and from side to side. Pictures from
 teens. That’s because new experiences influence how   on brain development. The researchers will continue to   an fMRI can show what the brain looks like
 the brain develops. And kids and teens have a lot of new   monitor these areas every year or two until the youth are   while a person is thinking about something
 experiences! Whether those experiences are exciting,   nineteen and twenty years old.  like a funny joke or a difficult math problem,
 baffling, overwhelming, or frightening, they shape who                    or while playing a game. When part of the
 you are and who you’ll become—usually without you even   The Promise of the ABCD Study  brain is working hard, it needs more oxygen,
 realizing it.
 The youth participating in the ABCD Study are as diverse                  just like your lungs need more oxygen when
 A look into the growing brain  as the United States. Approximately half are female, 15   they’re working hard. fMRI lets scientists
 percent are Black, 20 percent are Hispanic, and 52 percent                see when a part of the brain is using more
 How exactly do these changes happen in the brain?   are white. Participants come from seventeen different   or less oxygen. For example, when you do
 Scientists and researchers at the National Institutes   states, from big cities and small towns, and from different   a math problem, more oxygen flows to the
 of Health (NIH) are trying to answer this question and   economic backgrounds. A large and diverse study like this   parts of your brain that are working to solve
 many others. The NIH—the government agency that   makes it possible to investigate what contributes to normal   the problem. If you do this while having an
 supports research about the body and behavior—funded   differences in brain development, to understand what   fMRI, scientists can see your brain “in action.”
                                                                           So, fMRI helps scientists see which parts of
                                                                           the brain are important for thinking about
 By Gayathri J. Dowling, Ph.D.                                             different things.
 Director, Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development Study
 Division of Extramural Research
 National Institute on Drug Abuse
 National Institutes of Health                       Art by Gaya Dowling]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[develops during childhood and adolescence. They do this         environment, it “prunes” away the connections it doesn’t   skill, like talking or reading, may not be needed anymore
                                                               by using tools like magnetic resonance imaging (MRI),           use anymore—like cutting dead roses from a bush. At the   after it masters those skills. Once the energy is used to
                                                               which can open a window into a teen’s head (without             same time, connections that are essential for achieving   connect visual symbols (letters) into meaningful words and
                                                               opening their skull!). We’ve learned that the brain structure   today’s and tomorrow’s goals become more “hard wired,”   phrases, the energy for those brain regions may be better
                                                               tends to grow or mature from the back to the front, and         so they work more quickly. The brain maturation process is   spent on new skills like learning algebra, how to play a
                                                               from the bottom to the top. The regions of the brain that       like building a freeway between two cities for faster travel,   musical instrument, how to draw, or how to drive.
                                                               mature last include the frontal lobes. These are responsible    instead of relying on unpaved back roads.              So, we’re getting closer to an answer for the question of
                                                               for what we call “executive functioning”; they’re kind of       This makes sense when you think of the brain as        when adolescence ends and adulthood begins. We’re
                                                               like the brain’s “boss.” Development of the frontal lobes       using a limited supply of energy to keep all of a      learning more from studies like the Adolescent Brain
                                                               allows for better control over the parts of the brain that      person’s “lights on” all the time. Energy that supports   Cognitive Development Study (ABCD Study), which is
                                                               are responsible for your emotions, your actions/behavior,       brain connections and neurons that aren’t really helping   examining how the brain, thoughts, and behaviors develop
                                                               how you process risks and rewards, and how you make             you to achieve any goals may not be worth the “cost,” if   in diverse children and adolescents from ages nine to about
                                                               decisions, among other things.                                  there isn’t enough energy left to support the new thoughts,   twenty. Eventually, we’ll understand better how every
                                                               Let’s look at an example. Picture a preschool child whose       skills, and behaviors that happen as you grow up. The kinds   experience a person has—in their brain and their outside
        During adolescence, as you become adults, a lot of     needs and desires aren’t being met. For this child, the         of energy and connections your brain needs to learn a new   environment—helps to shape them for adulthood.
        changes take place in your body. But defining exactly   obvious answer may be to have a tantrum, or just to take
        what “adolescence” is,
        seem. We do know  Your Adolescent Brain: It’s a Construction Zone
        and when it occurs,
        isn’t as easy as it may

        that, in general,
        adolescence begins
        in puberty; this happens for girls between the ages of nine   the object they want from another child (likely leading to
        and ten, and one to two years later for boys. The hormones   more tantrums). By the time this child has reached age ten
        associated with puberty cause changes in the body that   or twelve, they’ve probably learned through experience
        lead to physical sexual maturity. But it isn’t clear when   that there are better ways to get what they need or want,
        adolescence ends—or, in other words, when bodies reach   like using words and conversation. Their frontal lobes are
        their adult form.                                      “coming online” and controlling their brain’s emotional
                                                               regions, so their social interactions are appropriate for
        Adolescence is a very busy time, both inside and out. An
        adolescent’s behavior, thinking, and emotional control are   their age. This brain maturation (the process of becoming
        changing at the same time that social expectations are   mature) continues until a person is in their mid-twenties.
        rapidly changing for them. This is all part of the normal   A sixteen-year-old may think it’s a good idea to drive a car
        process of becoming an adult. As children navigate from   as fast as she can to get to a pool party; when she’s twenty
        elementary school into middle and high school, they    or twenty-five (after a few speeding tickets, or worse), she
        begin to become independent from their family; this is   might be better able to hold herself back and reduce the
        especially important during adolescence, as teens prepare   risks that go with getting what she wants as quickly as
        for adulthood. But when does “adolescence” end and     possible. These are the frontal lobes in action.
        “adulthood” begin in the brain?                        But what, exactly, is the brain “doing” to make this
        The adolescent brain is like a construction zone. Physical   maturation happen? Scientists are beginning to find out.
        maturity can be observed on the outside, but what defines   We’ve learned that the brain produces far more brain cells
        “adulthood” may be related more to what’s going on     (called neurons) and connections between its different
        between an adolescent’s ears. Scientists have learned a   systems than it needs later to process information,
        lot in the last few decades about how the brain typically   thoughts, and behavior in adulthood. Over time, as the
                                                               brain has more experiences in a teen’s social and physical


                      By Elizabeth Sowell, Ph.D.
                      ABCD Study Principal Investigator
                      Children’s Hospital Los Angeles
                      Professor of Pediatrics                                                                                                                                                                      Art by Elizabeth Sowell
                      Keck School of Medicine of University of Southern California]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[develops during childhood and adolescence. They do this   environment, it “prunes” away the connections it doesn’t   skill, like talking or reading, may not be needed anymore
 by using tools like magnetic resonance imaging (MRI),   use anymore—like cutting dead roses from a bush. At the   after it masters those skills. Once the energy is used to
 which can open a window into a teen’s head (without   same time, connections that are essential for achieving   connect visual symbols (letters) into meaningful words and
 opening their skull!). We’ve learned that the brain structure   today’s and tomorrow’s goals become more “hard wired,”   phrases, the energy for those brain regions may be better
 tends to grow or mature from the back to the front, and   so they work more quickly. The brain maturation process is   spent on new skills like learning algebra, how to play a
 from the bottom to the top. The regions of the brain that   like building a freeway between two cities for faster travel,   musical instrument, how to draw, or how to drive.
 mature last include the frontal lobes. These are responsible   instead of relying on unpaved back roads.   So, we’re getting closer to an answer for the question of
 for what we call “executive functioning”; they’re kind of   This makes sense when you think of the brain as   when adolescence ends and adulthood begins. We’re
 like the brain’s “boss.” Development of the frontal lobes   using a limited supply of energy to keep all of a   learning more from studies like the Adolescent Brain
 allows for better control over the parts of the brain that   person’s “lights on” all the time. Energy that supports   Cognitive Development Study (ABCD Study), which is
 are responsible for your emotions, your actions/behavior,   brain connections and neurons that aren’t really helping   examining how the brain, thoughts, and behaviors develop
 how you process risks and rewards, and how you make   you to achieve any goals may not be worth the “cost,” if   in diverse children and adolescents from ages nine to about
 decisions, among other things.   there isn’t enough energy left to support the new thoughts,   twenty. Eventually, we’ll understand better how every
 Let’s look at an example. Picture a preschool child whose   skills, and behaviors that happen as you grow up. The kinds   experience a person has—in their brain and their outside
 During adolescence, as you become adults, a lot of   needs and desires aren’t being met. For this child, the   of energy and connections your brain needs to learn a new   environment—helps to shape them for adulthood.
 changes take place in your body. But defining exactly   obvious answer may be to have a tantrum, or just to take
 what “adolescence” is,
 seem. We do know  Your Adolescent Brain: It’s a Construction Zone
 and when it occurs,
 isn’t as easy as it may

 that, in general,
 adolescence begins
 in puberty; this happens for girls between the ages of nine   the object they want from another child (likely leading to
 and ten, and one to two years later for boys. The hormones   more tantrums). By the time this child has reached age ten
 associated with puberty cause changes in the body that   or twelve, they’ve probably learned through experience
 lead to physical sexual maturity. But it isn’t clear when   that there are better ways to get what they need or want,
 adolescence ends—or, in other words, when bodies reach   like using words and conversation. Their frontal lobes are
 their adult form.   “coming online” and controlling their brain’s emotional
 regions, so their social interactions are appropriate for
 Adolescence is a very busy time, both inside and out. An
 adolescent’s behavior, thinking, and emotional control are   their age. This brain maturation (the process of becoming
 changing at the same time that social expectations are   mature) continues until a person is in their mid-twenties.
 rapidly changing for them. This is all part of the normal   A sixteen-year-old may think it’s a good idea to drive a car
 process of becoming an adult. As children navigate from   as fast as she can to get to a pool party; when she’s twenty
 elementary school into middle and high school, they   or twenty-five (after a few speeding tickets, or worse), she
 begin to become independent from their family; this is   might be better able to hold herself back and reduce the
 especially important during adolescence, as teens prepare   risks that go with getting what she wants as quickly as
 for adulthood. But when does “adolescence” end and   possible. These are the frontal lobes in action.
 “adulthood” begin in the brain?   But what, exactly, is the brain “doing” to make this
 The adolescent brain is like a construction zone. Physical   maturation happen? Scientists are beginning to find out.
 maturity can be observed on the outside, but what defines   We’ve learned that the brain produces far more brain cells
 “adulthood” may be related more to what’s going on   (called neurons) and connections between its different
 between an adolescent’s ears. Scientists have learned a   systems than it needs later to process information,
 lot in the last few decades about how the brain typically   thoughts, and behavior in adulthood. Over time, as the
 brain has more experiences in a teen’s social and physical


 By Elizabeth Sowell, Ph.D.
 ABCD Study Principal Investigator
 Children’s Hospital Los Angeles
 Professor of Pediatrics                                                                    Art by Elizabeth Sowell
 Keck School of Medicine of University of Southern California]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[“                                                                               How has art




                                                                                                                                  Art relaxes me; it helps me take my mind off things and
                                                                                                                               allows me to re-center myself. It’s gratifying to start with an
                                                                                                                                                                                                           helped you
                                                                                                                                image in my mind and develop it as different components

                                                                                                                                                 come to me while I’m working.

                                                                                                                                 Art also helps me see the world differently. For instance,                during this
                                                                                                                                                                                                           COVID-19
                                                                                                                                when looking at a landscape (in real life, a photograph, or
                                                                                                                                a painting), I can identify the three “grounds”: foreground,               time?

                                                                                                                                     middle ground, and background. This allows me to
                                                                                                                                appreciate everything I see around me much more deeply.
                                                                                 Art by                                                                                                              ”
                                                                                 Cricket L.                                                                                                  —Emma C.







          Art + Science  = Power






                                         “



                                                I see art in nature. Sometimes I see it in a leaf that

            What types of                       looks like it’s been painted. Sometimes it’s the way
                                                 a squirrel moves. I think water is very much like a
           art do you see                        dance—water reflects trees and plants, but also


                    in nature?                    flowers, and sometimes dances are supposed to
                                                 look like flowers. Water moves. The way it moves
                                                looks like a dance. The sky, that’s another brilliant

                                                  piece of art. I love the way clouds move, but my
                                                  favorite part about the sky is that in sunrise and

                                                sunset the sky changes colors. I like to paint nature
                                                 landscapes because trees look very different from
                                                                                           ”
                                                  each other; mountains too. Also, there are many
                                                 colors in a natural landscape. That’s what makes                                                                                                              Art by
                                                                  them so fun to paint.                                                                                                                        Aaron G.


                                                                                                  —Michelle C.]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[“                                                                               How has art




           Art relaxes me; it helps me take my mind off things and
        allows me to re-center myself. It’s gratifying to start with an
                                                                                    helped you
          image in my mind and develop it as different components

                          come to me while I’m working.

           Art also helps me see the world differently. For instance,               during this
                                                                                    COVID-19
         when looking at a landscape (in real life, a photograph, or
         a painting), I can identify the three “grounds”: foreground,               time?

              middle ground, and background. This allows me to
         appreciate everything I see around me much more deeply.
 Art by                                                                       ”
 Cricket L.                                                           —Emma C.







 Art + Science  = Power






 “



 I see art in nature. Sometimes I see it in a leaf that

 What types of   looks like it’s been painted. Sometimes it’s the way
 a squirrel moves. I think water is very much like a
 art do you see   dance—water reflects trees and plants, but also


 in nature?  flowers, and sometimes dances are supposed to
 look like flowers. Water moves. The way it moves
 looks like a dance. The sky, that’s another brilliant

 piece of art. I love the way clouds move, but my
 favorite part about the sky is that in sunrise and

 sunset the sky changes colors. I like to paint nature
 landscapes because trees look very different from
 ”
 each other; mountains too. Also, there are many
 colors in a natural landscape. That’s what makes                                       Art by
 them so fun to paint.                                                                  Aaron G.


 —Michelle C.]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[The          Power                                                                                                         As far back as he can remember, Craig Alan has            Artist Profile:
                                                                                                                               been creating. As a kid, he found an artistic outlet by
                                                                                                                               drawing with crayons on his parents’ walls. Craig continued
                                                                                                                               to work on his art (not only on walls!) and gradually got
                                                                                                                               better at it. In spite of his expressive drawings with crayons
                                                                                                                               and his parents’ encouragement, Craig never imagined that
                                                                                                                               he would become a painter.
                                                                                                                               Craig went to elementary and middle school in California.
                                                                                                                               He says, “I remember when I was as young as eight, our
                                                                                                                               teacher would write stories, and we illustrated the stories
                                                                                                                               with five drawings. We did this assignment one day a week.   basically how I went from jock to art student to painter,” he
                                                                                                                               It was one of my favorite parts of school.” His creativity   explains.
                                                                                                                               blossomed throughout his childhood and early adulthood.   As an artist, Craig has a restless eye. His work refers
                                                                                                                               Today, Craig Alan’s art is exhibited across North America   to numerous artistic styles, including pop-surrealism,
                                                                                                                               and in Europe, where he has become a one-of-a-kind voice   magic realism, neoexpressionist abstraction, and natural
                                                                                                                               in the visual arts.                                    representation. His most recent work, which he calls the

                                                                                                                               Craig knows the power of art. “Art is incredibly important   “Populus Series”—a few pieces of which are featured in
                                                                                                                               for kids, for many reasons,” he says. Here are a few reasons   this article—includes original images of hundreds of tiny
                                                                                                                               he thinks this is true:                                people on a white background. At first glance, the paintings
                                                                                                                                                                                      look like aerial photographs, but a closer inspection reveals
                                                                                                                                   •  Creating art helps you be yourself and not be afraid
                                                                                                                                    to express yourself—even without using words or your   that they’re painted by hand. Craig hopes that viewers of
                                                                                                                                    voice.                                            his paintings will realize “that we are all part of something
                                                                                                                                                                                      greater than ourselves, and if we work together, we could
                                                                                                                                   •  Art can help you solve problems. It’s a great way to   achieve greater balance…not in a religious sense, but
              Craig Alan’s story is inspiring for kids who, like him, enjoy
                                                                                                                                    experiment and try new things. When you try art, you   rather a universal sense.”
           creating new things. It might also hold a lesson for parents                                                             always answer the question, “What if?”
           who may not recognize the artistry and imagination in their kids’                                                       •  Getting lost in your imagination can turn
                                                                                                                                    your ideas inside out and upside down—that’s
               crayon wall art. Who knows where it could lead them?                                                                 a really beautiful thing!

                                                                                                                                   •  Art can help you tell a story in your own way.
                                                                                                                                    There is no better way to build your confidence.
                                                                                                                                   •  Sometimes, we can learn things more
                                                                                                                                    easily if we have a visual or a picture to help
                                                                                                                                    us understand it. Artists are needed in all areas
                                                                                                                                    of education to help represent math, science,
                                                                                                                                    language arts, and history in visual ways. We
                                                                                                                                    can inject the creativity of art into all aspects of
                                                                                                                                    life and learning.
                                                                                                                               Craig focused on soccer in college and was offered
                                                                                                                               an athletic scholarship. It was stressful for him to
                                                                                                                               balance college classwork, soccer, and friendships,
                                                                                                                               and his grades began to suffer. To help improve
                                                                                                                               his grades, Craig took an art class. His first class—
                                                                                                                               pottery—had an unexpected and important
                                                                                                                               benefit: It helped him make sense of everything.
                                                                     of              Art                                       School became easier for Craig; he actually wanted
                                                                                                                               to learn because he saw how his classwork and
                                                                                                                               lessons applied to his life. “I threw myself into [art],
                                                                                                                               and it ended up changing my whole perspective on
                                                                                                                               learning,” Craig says. He connected with a publisher
                                                                                                                               and started on his path in the art world. “That’s]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[The  Power  As far back as he can remember, Craig Alan has       Artist Profile:
        been creating. As a kid, he found an artistic outlet by
        drawing with crayons on his parents’ walls. Craig continued
        to work on his art (not only on walls!) and gradually got
        better at it. In spite of his expressive drawings with crayons
        and his parents’ encouragement, Craig never imagined that
        he would become a painter.
        Craig went to elementary and middle school in California.
        He says, “I remember when I was as young as eight, our
        teacher would write stories, and we illustrated the stories
        with five drawings. We did this assignment one day a week.   basically how I went from jock to art student to painter,” he
        It was one of my favorite parts of school.” His creativity   explains.
        blossomed throughout his childhood and early adulthood.   As an artist, Craig has a restless eye. His work refers
        Today, Craig Alan’s art is exhibited across North America   to numerous artistic styles, including pop-surrealism,
        and in Europe, where he has become a one-of-a-kind voice   magic realism, neoexpressionist abstraction, and natural
        in the visual arts.                                    representation. His most recent work, which he calls the

        Craig knows the power of art. “Art is incredibly important   “Populus Series”—a few pieces of which are featured in
        for kids, for many reasons,” he says. Here are a few reasons   this article—includes original images of hundreds of tiny
        he thinks this is true:                                people on a white background. At first glance, the paintings
                                                               look like aerial photographs, but a closer inspection reveals
            •  Creating art helps you be yourself and not be afraid
              to express yourself—even without using words or your   that they’re painted by hand. Craig hopes that viewers of
              voice.                                           his paintings will realize “that we are all part of something
                                                               greater than ourselves, and if we work together, we could
            •  Art can help you solve problems. It’s a great way to   achieve greater balance…not in a religious sense, but
 Craig Alan’s story is inspiring for kids who, like him, enjoy
              experiment and try new things. When you try art, you   rather a universal sense.”
 creating new things. It might also hold a lesson for parents   always answer the question, “What if?”
 who may not recognize the artistry and imagination in their kids’   •  Getting lost in your imagination can turn
              your ideas inside out and upside down—that’s
 crayon wall art. Who knows where it could lead them?   a really beautiful thing!

            •  Art can help you tell a story in your own way.
              There is no better way to build your confidence.
            •  Sometimes, we can learn things more
              easily if we have a visual or a picture to help
              us understand it. Artists are needed in all areas
              of education to help represent math, science,
              language arts, and history in visual ways. We
              can inject the creativity of art into all aspects of
              life and learning.
        Craig focused on soccer in college and was offered
        an athletic scholarship. It was stressful for him to
        balance college classwork, soccer, and friendships,
        and his grades began to suffer. To help improve
        his grades, Craig took an art class. His first class—
        pottery—had an unexpected and important
        benefit: It helped him make sense of everything.
 of   Art  School became easier for Craig; he actually wanted
        to learn because he saw how his classwork and
        lessons applied to his life. “I threw myself into [art],
        and it ended up changing my whole perspective on
        learning,” Craig says. He connected with a publisher
        and started on his path in the art world. “That’s]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[clay that conducts electricity), and a range of other tools   like this helps students make
        Connecting with STEM Through                                                                                           and materials.                                         connections between the

                                                                                                                                                                                      arts and their own physical,
                                                                                                                               Education researchers study the “making” process, the
        Movement and Dance                                                                                                     products the students create, and interview the students   mental, and emotional
                                                                                                                                                                                      well-being.
                                                                                                                               to learn the thoughts behind their “making.” This helps
                                                                                                                               the researchers understand how youth make sense of     In a current version,
                                                               In a summer program for youth ages nine to                      new ideas, think about their old ideas, and translate their   youth are using hip hop
                     By Dionne N. Champion,                    fourteen, five students sit on the floor of a                               understanding through choreography,        art, music, and dance
                     Ph.D., M.Ed.                              large room and work together to develop a scientific                          props, sound, and other ways of making.   as part of a research
                     Assistant Research Professor              representation of the human nervous system. After they                         In the dance makerspace, STEM is not    project supported by
                     Dance and STEM                            read their research notes from the day before, they stand                       just STEM, movement can be more        the National Science
                     University of Florida                     up and hold hands in a circle. Their sketchbook and notes                       than just movement, and the pathways   Foundation. “The Hip
                     Center for Arts in Medicine               lay on the floor, along with a few tools and an energy stick                    to learning are limitless. The students   Hop Making Camp”
                     College of the Arts                                                                                                      choose how they want to use their own   project aims to create a
                                                               made with lights in a plastic tube that illuminates when
                                                               someone holds both ends. Their conversation becomes                            interests to create meaningful STEM     learning environment that
                                                               a mix of talk, movement, and sound effects. They move                         experiences. They decide how to research   other teachers and students
                                                                                                                                                                                      can use, combining creative ways
                     Jill Sonke, M.A.                          quickly around the space—running, jumping, spinning.                                                                   of “making,” computer programs, and
                     Director                                  At first glance, this composition of sights and sounds                                                                 parts of hip hop culture. Students learn how electrical
                     Center for Arts in Medicine               could easily be interpreted as a chaotic and unfocused          In the dance makerspace, STEM is                       engineering is part of the history of hip hop (for example,
                     University of Florida                     activity. Are the children playing a new kind of game?                                                                 how the crossfader was invented to switch between
                     College of the Arts                       Actually, they’re doing complicated work, using their            not just STEM, movement can be                        records). They learn about how hip hop pioneers like DJ
                     Assistant Director                        minds, knowledge, imagination, and dance to represent                                                                  Kool Herc created by “making do” with materials that they
                     Shands Arts in Medicine                   the human nervous system—specifically, how the brain            more than just movement, and the                       already had, and they’re challenged to invent their own

                                                               communicates with the body. They’re developing a project        pathways to learning are limitless.                    hip hop STEM creations by “making do” with materials
                                                               in the “dance makerspace.”                                                                                             available in the space. They learn to make computer art,
                     Sara Jo Nixon, Ph.D.                      Makerspaces are “informal sites for creative production                                                                and to program music with free software. They also create
                     ABCD Study Principal Investigator         in art, science, and engineering where people of all                                                                   dances and develop rules about how the dances should
                     University of Florida                     ages blend digital and physical technologies to explore         their own questions and construct their own creative   be performed, then they create and program computer
                     Director, University of Florida Center for                                            1                   solutions.
                      Addiction Research & Education           ideas, learn technical skills, and create new products.”                                                                               Continued on page 37
                     Professor, Departments of Psychiatry      “Making” activities combine engineering, art, and design. 2     The dance makerspace camps—designed
                      and Psychology, College of Medicine,     The dance makerspace, however, is a little different. Like      and facilitated by Dr. Dionne Champion, a
                      College of Liberal Arts and Sciences     other makerspaces, it’s filled with materials, tools, and       researcher at the University of Florida Center
                     Co-Vice Chair for Research, Department    technologies students can use. There are workstations           for Arts in Medicine—have taken many forms.
                      of Psychiatry                            with access to tablets and electricity where groups can         In one series of camps, students worked in
                     Director, University of Florida           collaborate. But in the dance makerspace, participants also     groups to explain a scientific fact or event using
                                                                         3
                      Neurocognitive Laboratory                have a dance studio, where they develop their ideas by          choreography and technology. These groups
                                                               using movement, music, and art.                                 completed projects about the nervous system,

                     Linda B. Cottler, Ph.D.,                  The dance makerspace was designed as part of a four-week        the solar system, health conditions, blood flow,
                                                                                                                               volcanic eruptions, and the chemistry of
                                                               summer camp program in Gary, Indiana, for young African
                     M.P.H., FACE                              American dancers. One of the program’s goals is to get          mood rings. Working with community
                     ABCD Study Principal Investigator         students interested in the fields of science, technology,       arts programs to develop activities
                     University of Florida                     engineering, and math (STEM). Research has shown that
                     Associate Dean for Research, College of            students ages nine to fourteen become much                                                                           Dionne Champion, Jill Sonke, and Linda Cottler
                      Public Health and Health Professions
                     Dean’s Professor                                     less interested in STEM, particularly girls and      1  Sheridan, K., Halverson, E. R., Litts, B., Brahms, L., Jacobs-Priebe, L., & Owens, T. (2014). Learning in the making: A comparative case study of
                                                                                                 4
                     Director-CTSI Community Engagement                    African American children. Youth from               2 three makerspaces. Harvard Educational Review, 84(4), 505-531.
                      Program                                               underrepresented communities who aren’t              Wagh, A., Gravel, B., Tucker-Raymond, E., & Klimczack, S. (2016, October). Negotiating tensions between aesthetics, meaning and technics as
                     Department of Epidemiology, Colleges of                STEM learners, but are interested in dance,         opportunities for disciplinary engagement. In Proceedings of the 6th Annual Conference on Creativity and Fabrication in Education (pp. 58-65).
                                                                                                                                ACM.
                      Public Health and Health Professions                  attend the camp five days a week. They’re          3  Hlubinka, M., Dougherty, D., Thomas, P., Chang, S., Hoefer, S., Alexander, I., & McGuire, D. (2013). Makerspace playbook: School edition.
                      and Medicine                                          challenged to combine dance-making with             Retrieved from: https://makered.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/Makerspace-Playbook-Feb-2013.pdf.
                                                                            technology, using kid-friendly electronic          4  Haynes, L. (2008). Studying STEM: What are the barriers? London, England: Institute of Engineering and Technology.
                                                                           items (such as lights, electronic boards, and]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[clay that conducts electricity), and a range of other tools   like this helps students make
 Connecting with STEM Through   and materials.                 connections between the

                                                               arts and their own physical,
        Education researchers study the “making” process, the
 Movement and Dance   products the students create, and interview the students   mental, and emotional
                                                               well-being.
        to learn the thoughts behind their “making.” This helps
        the researchers understand how youth make sense of     In a current version,
 In a summer program for youth ages nine to   new ideas, think about their old ideas, and translate their   youth are using hip hop
 By Dionne N. Champion,   fourteen, five students sit on the floor of a   understanding through choreography,   art, music, and dance
 Ph.D., M.Ed.   large room and work together to develop a scientific   props, sound, and other ways of making.   as part of a research
 Assistant Research Professor  representation of the human nervous system. After they   In the dance makerspace, STEM is not   project supported by
 Dance and STEM  read their research notes from the day before, they stand   just STEM, movement can be more   the National Science
 University of Florida  up and hold hands in a circle. Their sketchbook and notes   than just movement, and the pathways   Foundation. “The Hip
 Center for Arts in Medicine  lay on the floor, along with a few tools and an energy stick   to learning are limitless. The students   Hop Making Camp”
 College of the Arts    choose how they want to use their own   project aims to create a
 made with lights in a plastic tube that illuminates when
 someone holds both ends. Their conversation becomes   interests to create meaningful STEM   learning environment that
 a mix of talk, movement, and sound effects. They move   experiences. They decide how to research   other teachers and students
                                                               can use, combining creative ways
 Jill Sonke, M.A.   quickly around the space—running, jumping, spinning.    of “making,” computer programs, and
 Director  At first glance, this composition of sights and sounds   parts of hip hop culture. Students learn how electrical
 Center for Arts in Medicine  could easily be interpreted as a chaotic and unfocused   In the dance makerspace, STEM is   engineering is part of the history of hip hop (for example,
 University of Florida  activity. Are the children playing a new kind of game?   how the crossfader was invented to switch between
 College of the Arts  Actually, they’re doing complicated work, using their   not just STEM, movement can be   records). They learn about how hip hop pioneers like DJ
 Assistant Director  minds, knowledge, imagination, and dance to represent   Kool Herc created by “making do” with materials that they
 Shands Arts in Medicine  the human nervous system—specifically, how the brain   more than just movement, and the   already had, and they’re challenged to invent their own

 communicates with the body. They’re developing a project   pathways to learning are limitless.  hip hop STEM creations by “making do” with materials
 in the “dance makerspace.”                                    available in the space. They learn to make computer art,
 Sara Jo Nixon, Ph.D.  Makerspaces are “informal sites for creative production   and to program music with free software. They also create
 ABCD Study Principal Investigator   in art, science, and engineering where people of all   dances and develop rules about how the dances should
 University of Florida  ages blend digital and physical technologies to explore   their own questions and construct their own creative   be performed, then they create and program computer
 Director, University of Florida Center for   1  solutions.
 Addiction Research & Education  ideas, learn technical skills, and create new products.”    Continued on page 37
 Professor, Departments of Psychiatry   “Making” activities combine engineering, art, and design. 2   The dance makerspace camps—designed
 and Psychology, College of Medicine,   The dance makerspace, however, is a little different. Like   and facilitated by Dr. Dionne Champion, a
 College of Liberal Arts and Sciences  other makerspaces, it’s filled with materials, tools, and   researcher at the University of Florida Center
 Co-Vice Chair for Research, Department   technologies students can use. There are workstations   for Arts in Medicine—have taken many forms.
 of Psychiatry  with access to tablets and electricity where groups can   In one series of camps, students worked in
 Director, University of Florida   collaborate. But in the dance makerspace, participants also   groups to explain a scientific fact or event using
 3
 Neurocognitive Laboratory  have a dance studio, where they develop their ideas by   choreography and technology. These groups
 using movement, music, and art.   completed projects about the nervous system,

 Linda B. Cottler, Ph.D.,   The dance makerspace was designed as part of a four-week   the solar system, health conditions, blood flow,
        volcanic eruptions, and the chemistry of
 summer camp program in Gary, Indiana, for young African
 M.P.H., FACE  American dancers. One of the program’s goals is to get   mood rings. Working with community
 ABCD Study Principal Investigator   students interested in the fields of science, technology,   arts programs to develop activities
 University of Florida  engineering, and math (STEM). Research has shown that
 Associate Dean for Research, College of   students ages nine to fourteen become much   Dionne Champion, Jill Sonke, and Linda Cottler
 Public Health and Health Professions
 Dean’s Professor  less interested in STEM, particularly girls and   1  Sheridan, K., Halverson, E. R., Litts, B., Brahms, L., Jacobs-Priebe, L., & Owens, T. (2014). Learning in the making: A comparative case study of
 4
 Director-CTSI Community Engagement   African American children. Youth from   2 three makerspaces. Harvard Educational Review, 84(4), 505-531.
 Program  underrepresented communities who aren’t    Wagh, A., Gravel, B., Tucker-Raymond, E., & Klimczack, S. (2016, October). Negotiating tensions between aesthetics, meaning and technics as
 Department of Epidemiology, Colleges of   STEM learners, but are interested in dance,   opportunities for disciplinary engagement. In Proceedings of the 6th Annual Conference on Creativity and Fabrication in Education (pp. 58-65).
         ACM.
 Public Health and Health Professions   attend the camp five days a week. They’re   3  Hlubinka, M., Dougherty, D., Thomas, P., Chang, S., Hoefer, S., Alexander, I., & McGuire, D. (2013). Makerspace playbook: School edition.
 and Medicine  challenged to combine dance-making with   Retrieved from: https://makered.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/Makerspace-Playbook-Feb-2013.pdf.
 technology, using kid-friendly electronic   4  Haynes, L. (2008). Studying STEM: What are the barriers? London, England: Institute of Engineering and Technology.
 items (such as lights, electronic boards, and]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Music’s Harmony on the


        Developing Brain:


        Data from the ABCD Study




        By Tim Brown, Ph.D.
        Associate Professor of Neurosciences
        Sentia Lab for Childhood Systems Neuroscience                                                                                                                                 many common school skills like naming letters or counting.
        Altman Clinical and Translational Research Institute                                                                                                                          We also found the reverse is true: Many kids who are the
        University of California, San Diego                                                                                                                                           best at these early academic tasks aren’t as good as many
        School of Medicine                                                                                                                                                            of their classmates at hitting the right notes when they’re
                                                                                                                                                                                      singing. We’ve also measured children’s abilities to tap to a
        John R. Iversen, Ph.D.                                                                                                 questions, too. For example, does a child who studies how   rhythm, which showed similar results. Taken together, what
                                                                                                                               to play a musical instrument get better in school because
        Associate Research Scientist, Institute for Neural Computation                                                                                                                we found suggests that musical abilities at this age might
        Associate Director, Swartz Center for Computational Neuroscience                                                       of music … or do kids who do well in school already also do   develop separately from other skills that are commonly
        University of California, San Diego                                John Iversen                                        well at music, or get more chances to take lessons?    measured in school.
                                                                                                                               Our research team has started a project called EARLI (Early
                                                                                                                               Academic Readiness and Learning Intervention) to explore   One lesson from this research is that musical skills can
                                                                                                                               some of these questions. In this project, funded by the   provide a new window into a child’s strengths. This
                                                                                                                               National Endowment for the Arts and private donations,   information could help families and teachers approach
        Music is an important part of human culture, and the idea that it’s important for learning has been around             we’re seeing if a fun, daily program of group singing   each child from a place where they’re already strong to
        at least since ancient times. Confucius and Socrates wrote that music training contributes to a refined mind and       lessons—developed by an experienced teacher from the   help improve other skills. To go along with our EARLI study,
        harmonious society. Now, researchers are looking at how music might help kids learn.                                   San Diego Children’s Choir—helps young children do     we’re also taking a deep dive into what the ABCD Study has
                                                                                                                               better as they enter kindergarten.                     found out; in fact, music is the most frequently reported
        Encouraging children to reach their full potential, while celebrating individual differences, is complicated. Researchers                                                     arts activity in the ABCD Study. With a grant funded by
        approach this challenge in many ways—from small studies that test the effects of a particular music training program on   We first worked with kids to get an idea of how each one’s   the National Institutes of Health, we’re also exploring
        children’s abilities to think and do different tasks, to very large studies like the Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development Study   skills were already developing in areas like language, math,   connections between how much music experience
        (ABCD Study). The ABCD Study is examining connections between a child’s experiences with music and their other abilities   attention, hearing, melody, and rhythm. Then, some of the   each child has; measures such as math performance,
        and outcomes.                                                                                                          children began taking a half hour singing lesson four times   language, and memory; and changes in the child’s brain
                                                                                                                               a week for two months. After that, we repeated our initial
        Past research has suggested that music might improve a child’s language skills and their ability to pay attention, and that                                                   structure over a period of time. By combining the ABCD
        kids involved in music might come to school more often and stick with school longer. But this research has raised a lot of   research to see if the music training changed the path of   Study’s results with very detailed studies like EARLI, we’re
                                                                                                                               each child’s development (for example, did it speed up?).   continuing to learn about how music may affect—and
                                                                                                                               It was important to check if it was really the music that   improve—children’s health and education.
                                                                                                                               had any effect, so we also worked with children who did
                                                                                                                               not get the music training. We did this research in schools
                                                                   Better
                                                                                                                               and involved the children’s teachers, families, and school
                                                                                                                               administrators, in order to get “the big picture” about the
                                                                                                                               children’s learning.
                                                            Vocabulary
                                                              Score                                                            So far, we’ve focused on one question: Does a child’s
                                                                                                                               musical abilities match their academic skills like reading
                                                                                                                               and math? Previous research has shown that children who
                                                                                                      Children with
                                                                                                    low vocabulary and         do well on one kind of school skill, like naming letters, also
                                                                                                     excellent singing         tend to be good at other school skills, like counting—even
                                                                                                                               though those skills may seem pretty different. Do early
                                                                                               Better                          developing musical abilities act this way, too?
                Tim Brown                                                           Singing
                                                                                     Score                                     Our results suggest that they don’t. Using a task that
                                                                                                                               requires kids to sing the same notes they hear from a music
                                                              Vocabulary and singing scores for students in the EARLI study    teacher, we found that some of the very best singers at pre-  In-school singing training in a transitional kindergarten class.
                                                                       (each dot is the score for one student).                kindergarten ages don’t do as well as their classmates at]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[Music’s Harmony on the


 Developing Brain:


 Data from the ABCD Study




 By Tim Brown, Ph.D.
 Associate Professor of Neurosciences
 Sentia Lab for Childhood Systems Neuroscience                 many common school skills like naming letters or counting.
 Altman Clinical and Translational Research Institute          We also found the reverse is true: Many kids who are the
 University of California, San Diego                           best at these early academic tasks aren’t as good as many
 School of Medicine                                            of their classmates at hitting the right notes when they’re
                                                               singing. We’ve also measured children’s abilities to tap to a
 John R. Iversen, Ph.D.  questions, too. For example, does a child who studies how   rhythm, which showed similar results. Taken together, what
        to play a musical instrument get better in school because
 Associate Research Scientist, Institute for Neural Computation  we found suggests that musical abilities at this age might
 Associate Director, Swartz Center for Computational Neuroscience  of music … or do kids who do well in school already also do   develop separately from other skills that are commonly
 University of California, San Diego  John Iversen  well at music, or get more chances to take lessons?  measured in school.
        Our research team has started a project called EARLI (Early
        Academic Readiness and Learning Intervention) to explore   One lesson from this research is that musical skills can
        some of these questions. In this project, funded by the   provide a new window into a child’s strengths. This
        National Endowment for the Arts and private donations,   information could help families and teachers approach
 Music is an important part of human culture, and the idea that it’s important for learning has been around   we’re seeing if a fun, daily program of group singing   each child from a place where they’re already strong to
 at least since ancient times. Confucius and Socrates wrote that music training contributes to a refined mind and   lessons—developed by an experienced teacher from the   help improve other skills. To go along with our EARLI study,
 harmonious society. Now, researchers are looking at how music might help kids learn.   San Diego Children’s Choir—helps young children do   we’re also taking a deep dive into what the ABCD Study has
        better as they enter kindergarten.                     found out; in fact, music is the most frequently reported
 Encouraging children to reach their full potential, while celebrating individual differences, is complicated. Researchers   arts activity in the ABCD Study. With a grant funded by
 approach this challenge in many ways—from small studies that test the effects of a particular music training program on   We first worked with kids to get an idea of how each one’s   the National Institutes of Health, we’re also exploring
 children’s abilities to think and do different tasks, to very large studies like the Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development Study   skills were already developing in areas like language, math,   connections between how much music experience
 (ABCD Study). The ABCD Study is examining connections between a child’s experiences with music and their other abilities   attention, hearing, melody, and rhythm. Then, some of the   each child has; measures such as math performance,
 and outcomes.   children began taking a half hour singing lesson four times   language, and memory; and changes in the child’s brain
        a week for two months. After that, we repeated our initial
 Past research has suggested that music might improve a child’s language skills and their ability to pay attention, and that   structure over a period of time. By combining the ABCD
 kids involved in music might come to school more often and stick with school longer. But this research has raised a lot of   research to see if the music training changed the path of   Study’s results with very detailed studies like EARLI, we’re
        each child’s development (for example, did it speed up?).   continuing to learn about how music may affect—and
        It was important to check if it was really the music that   improve—children’s health and education.
        had any effect, so we also worked with children who did
        not get the music training. We did this research in schools
 Better
        and involved the children’s teachers, families, and school
        administrators, in order to get “the big picture” about the
        children’s learning.
 Vocabulary
 Score  So far, we’ve focused on one question: Does a child’s
        musical abilities match their academic skills like reading
        and math? Previous research has shown that children who
 Children with
 low vocabulary and  do well on one kind of school skill, like naming letters, also
 excellent singing  tend to be good at other school skills, like counting—even
        though those skills may seem pretty different. Do early
 Better  developing musical abilities act this way, too?
 Tim Brown  Singing
 Score  Our results suggest that they don’t. Using a task that
        requires kids to sing the same notes they hear from a music
 Vocabulary and singing scores for students in the EARLI study   teacher, we found that some of the very best singers at pre-  In-school singing training in a transitional kindergarten class.
 (each dot is the score for one student).  kindergarten ages don’t do as well as their classmates at]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[Scientist Profile




                                                                                                                               John Iversen





                                                                                                                                      You’re a lifelong percussionist. How did you get interested in drums? Do you still play regularly?

                                                                                                                                      They say I was playing the pots and pans before I could walk. Some other fortunate things encouraged me:
                                                                                                                                      I had two uncles who were drummers, an elementary school with a serious instrumental music program
                                                                                                                                      starting in first grade, and understanding parents. It went both ways: My drum mentor fed my scientific side
                                                                                                                                      and turned me on to computers and electronics. I played a drum set for many years, and began Japanese
                                                                                                                                      Taiko drumming (a dynamic, athletic form of group drumming performance) while I was in graduate school
                                                                                                                                      in Boston. Later, I co-founded a Taiko group in San Diego, and it’s still going strong. Recently, I’ve returned
                                                                                                                                      to the drum set, jamming with a close guitarist friend (who’s also a music neuroscientist). Even when I’m not
                                                                                                                                      playing, I’m pretty tuned into the rhythms all around us.


                                                                                                                                      Research shows that music and rhythm can change the brain and have positive effects on mental
                                                                                                                                      health. Is this something you’ve noticed in your own experience as a
                                                                                                                                      drummer?
                                                                                                                                      My own drumming experience has certainly motivated many of the scientific
                                                                                                                                      questions I’m passionate about, such as how the brain perceives and makes
                                                                                                                                      rhythms, and how this relates to language and attention skills. Personally,
                                                                                                                                      drumming has been a profoundly positive part of my life. There’s nothing like the
                                                                                                                                      connection of making music with other people and sharing our energy with an
                                                                                                                                      audience. Drumming is physical; it can require such a focus that there’s no way to
                                                                                                                                      hang on to negative emotions. I like to say it helped get me through grad school in
                                                                                                                                      one piece!

                                                                                                                                      It’s pretty cool that you get to merge your interests in music and the brain.
                                                                                                                                      What made you decide to pursue a professional career in neuroscience
                                                                                                                                      rather than, say, percussion?
                                                                                                                                      I couldn’t agree more! It turns out that a lot of scientists studying music and the
                                                                                                                                      brain, including Tim Brown, my coauthor in this issue, have a background in music.
                                                                                                                                      We’re very fortunate to have found a way to combine our passions. Why did I take
                                                                                                                                      the path I did? I realized I didn’t have the chops to be a professional drummer, and as a teenager, I reasoned
                                                                                                                                      that it was more possible to be a scientist with a lifelong hobby of music than the reverse. I was drawn to
                                                                                                                                      studying the brain by the hope that someday I’d do research relevant to people’s lives. I studied physics and
                                                                                                                                      then neuroscience, focusing on how the brain changes after a person loses their hearing. Only later, after
                                                                                                                                      I got my Ph.D., did I bring my interests in the brain and rhythms back together. The great news is that the
                                                                                                                                      study of music, the brain, health, and education is growing, thanks to support from the National Institutes
                                                                                                                                      of Health, the National Endowment for the Arts, and the National Science Foundation.




                                                                                                                                                By Elizabeth Hoffman, Ph.D.
                                                                                                                                                Scientific Program Manager
                                                                                                                                                Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development Study
                                                                                                                                                Division of Extramural Research
                                                                                                                                                National Institute on Drug Abuse
                                                                                                                                                National Institutes of Health]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[Scientist Profile




        John Iversen





               You’re a lifelong percussionist. How did you get interested in drums? Do you still play regularly?

               They say I was playing the pots and pans before I could walk. Some other fortunate things encouraged me:
               I had two uncles who were drummers, an elementary school with a serious instrumental music program
               starting in first grade, and understanding parents. It went both ways: My drum mentor fed my scientific side
               and turned me on to computers and electronics. I played a drum set for many years, and began Japanese
               Taiko drumming (a dynamic, athletic form of group drumming performance) while I was in graduate school
               in Boston. Later, I co-founded a Taiko group in San Diego, and it’s still going strong. Recently, I’ve returned
               to the drum set, jamming with a close guitarist friend (who’s also a music neuroscientist). Even when I’m not
               playing, I’m pretty tuned into the rhythms all around us.


               Research shows that music and rhythm can change the brain and have positive effects on mental
               health. Is this something you’ve noticed in your own experience as a
               drummer?
               My own drumming experience has certainly motivated many of the scientific
               questions I’m passionate about, such as how the brain perceives and makes
               rhythms, and how this relates to language and attention skills. Personally,
               drumming has been a profoundly positive part of my life. There’s nothing like the
               connection of making music with other people and sharing our energy with an
               audience. Drumming is physical; it can require such a focus that there’s no way to
               hang on to negative emotions. I like to say it helped get me through grad school in
               one piece!

               It’s pretty cool that you get to merge your interests in music and the brain.
               What made you decide to pursue a professional career in neuroscience
               rather than, say, percussion?
               I couldn’t agree more! It turns out that a lot of scientists studying music and the
               brain, including Tim Brown, my coauthor in this issue, have a background in music.
               We’re very fortunate to have found a way to combine our passions. Why did I take
               the path I did? I realized I didn’t have the chops to be a professional drummer, and as a teenager, I reasoned
               that it was more possible to be a scientist with a lifelong hobby of music than the reverse. I was drawn to
               studying the brain by the hope that someday I’d do research relevant to people’s lives. I studied physics and
               then neuroscience, focusing on how the brain changes after a person loses their hearing. Only later, after
               I got my Ph.D., did I bring my interests in the brain and rhythms back together. The great news is that the
               study of music, the brain, health, and education is growing, thanks to support from the National Institutes
               of Health, the National Endowment for the Arts, and the National Science Foundation.




                         By Elizabeth Hoffman, Ph.D.
                         Scientific Program Manager
                         Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development Study
                         Division of Extramural Research
                         National Institute on Drug Abuse
                         National Institutes of Health]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[“

                                                                                                                                Like so many others, the coronavirus pandemic has taken so much from me. I have

                                                                                                                               been affected physically, mentally, and socially. I am tired of being home, and I wish
                                                                         This sand dollar reminds me of my family                we all could have the same amount of freedom that we had before this pandemic
                                                                         vacations in Maine. We go to Maine
                                                                        “y year and we are happy there and                    began. Luckily, I have still been able to continue dancing. Dance has not only allowed
                                                                         ever
                                                                         find sand dollars and enjoy the beach.                 me to stay active, it has also taken a big weight off of my shoulders especially with
                                                                         We couldn’t go this year. So, I couldn’t                 all of the added stress and fear I have gathered throughout quarantine. I dance
                                                                         see my turtle and frogs. I miss them. I
                                                                                                   ”
                                                                         created this gyotaku art for school. And               because it makes me happy. Dance allows me to express myself in a way that only I
                                                                         every time I look at it, I feel happy.                can. Each movement varies from person to person which is why so much emotion can
                                                                                              —Camden M.                       be expressed while dancing. The dance community is very tight knit. I do my absolute
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                ”
                                                                                                                               best to understand, and provide everyone with the same amount of love and support
                                                                                                                              that they give to me. Although the light at the end of the tunnel is not visible yet, I will
                                                                                                                                   continue to move forward and dance will be next to me every step of the way.


                                                                                                                                                                                                                              —Olivia T.
       Essence of Art  = Expression





                           “



                                   A lot of time, people don’t know how to express themselves.

                                 They have trouble communicating and showing their emotions.
                                 The arts can help with that. I have been able to express myself
                                                                                                                                Meanwhile the world is facing a
                                    through music and writing. I love to express my feelings by
                                                                                                                                 crisis, Art is a way of expression
                                     playing my violin and writing short stories. For example,                               “ and escape from negativity.
                                  sometimes I am dealing with family issues and I don’t want to                                     Art is a passage to another
                                                                                                                                     dimension where I’m able
                                   talk about it. When I play my violin or write, I can deal with                                  to create my own world. Art

                                    those feelings and express them. Also, those activities have                                   simply makes me feel better
                                                                                                                                and precise about the way I see
                                             helped me to express my feelings about what’s going                                            my environment.

                                                on in the world right now with the coronavirus and                                 Many people have different
                                                  the Black Lives Matter Movement. It was a lot to                              ways of expression, but I choose
                                                                                                                                   Art. Art is everywhere, if you
                                                  deal with, but these hobbies have helped me get                                  allow your imagination you
                                                                                                                                                      ”
                                                   through it. Expressing feelings means that I will                                     can create anything!
                                                                                                ”                                                                                                                                      21
                                                  have less stress. Stress leads to bad health. So,                                            —Kamila D.
                                             doing my hobbies and expressing my feelings leads to
                                                    good health, mentally and physically.

                                                                                                     —Sarah S.]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[“

          Like so many others, the coronavirus pandemic has taken so much from me. I have

        been affected physically, mentally, and socially. I am tired of being home, and I wish
 This sand dollar reminds me of my family   we all could have the same amount of freedom that we had before this pandemic
 vacations in Maine. We go to Maine
 “y year and we are happy there and   began. Luckily, I have still been able to continue dancing. Dance has not only allowed
 ever
 find sand dollars and enjoy the beach.   me to stay active, it has also taken a big weight off of my shoulders especially with
 We couldn’t go this year. So, I couldn’t   all of the added stress and fear I have gathered throughout quarantine. I dance
 see my turtle and frogs. I miss them. I
 ”
 created this gyotaku art for school. And   because it makes me happy. Dance allows me to express myself in a way that only I
 every time I look at it, I feel happy.   can. Each movement varies from person to person which is why so much emotion can
 —Camden M.  be expressed while dancing. The dance community is very tight knit. I do my absolute
                                                                                                         ”
        best to understand, and provide everyone with the same amount of love and support
        that they give to me. Although the light at the end of the tunnel is not visible yet, I will
            continue to move forward and dance will be next to me every step of the way.


                                                                                                       —Olivia T.
 Essence of Art  = Expression





 “



 A lot of time, people don’t know how to express themselves.

 They have trouble communicating and showing their emotions.
 The arts can help with that. I have been able to express myself
         Meanwhile the world is facing a
 through music and writing. I love to express my feelings by
          crisis, Art is a way of expression
 playing my violin and writing short stories. For example,   “ and escape from negativity.
 sometimes I am dealing with family issues and I don’t want to   Art is a passage to another
              dimension where I’m able
 talk about it. When I play my violin or write, I can deal with   to create my own world. Art

 those feelings and express them. Also, those activities have   simply makes me feel better
          and precise about the way I see
 helped me to express my feelings about what’s going   my environment.

 on in the world right now with the coronavirus and   Many people have different
 the Black Lives Matter Movement. It was a lot to   ways of expression, but I choose
            Art. Art is everywhere, if you
 deal with, but these hobbies have helped me get   allow your imagination you
                                ”
 through it. Expressing feelings means that I will   can create anything!
 ”                                                                                                              21
 have less stress. Stress leads to bad health. So,   —Kamila D.
 doing my hobbies and expressing my feelings leads to
 good health, mentally and physically.

 —Sarah S.]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Artist Profile














                                                                                                                                        Childhood






                                                                                                                                             and






            Srinjoy Gangopadhyay was born into                                                                                            Utopia
            a family of artists in Kolkata, India.
            His father was a very popular illustrator
            and studio artist, and as a child, Srinjoy was                                                                     filled with Hindu and Buddhist mythological stories   in the world, made me aware of the contradictions
            surrounded by paint, paper, canvas, and                                                                            and religious art. The books on ancient Indian Art   between Utopia and reality,” he admits. “This, in turn,
            the smell of oil paint. His father’s studio had                                                                    fascinated Srinjoy, especially the amazing monumental   made me interested in exploring ‘Utopia’ in my art.” To do
            books and catalogs about many artists—               with a brush in his hand, painting right next to him. After   murals in the Ajanta Caves. He                                              this, he is influenced by the
            ranging from the great masters of Renaissance Art to   a while, Srinjoy asked his father for “that brush” he was   also read graphic novels like                                               visual language of “Pop” and
            Modern Art and the Surrealists. “From a very young age,”   painting with. “I thought it was the brush that made all   the “Amar Chitra Katha” series,                                          Urban Art: internet memes,
            he says, “I would turn the pages and immerse myself in   the difference!”                                          with its stories from the worlds                                            colorful vintage Bollywood
            the ocean of paintings they showed.” Later, he read about                                                          of mythological Hindu and                                                   billboards, Dada collages,
            many artists’ lives and their artistic journeys.     Srinjoy’s uncle, who was into advertising and graphic
                                                                 design, used to play a game with him. He would draw a         Buddhist Gods, as well as Marvel                                            and street art/graffiti culture.
            On his first day of school, Srinjoy came home and made   few lines on a blank piece of paper; then he’d challenge   and DC comics.                                                             In his “ICON” series
            drawings of the school, his new friends, parents, and cars.   Srinjoy to draw something that incorporated those    In his current art practice,                                                of paintings, he uses
            His father was very enthusiastic about his early creations:   lines—filling in the blanks to finish the drawing. It   he has focused on the theme of                                           popular images of famous
            He framed a few of Srinjoy’s drawings to hang in the   was Srinjoy’s favorite game. In addition to visiting art    “Utopia,” or a perfect world. He                                            personalities; he reinterprets
            family home. There was no shortage of art materials in   exhibitions, he also got to meet many of his father’s     has always been drawn to images                                             how these personalities
            their house, and Srinjoy was lucky to play with them.   famous artist friends. His childhood was not only filled   and stories of utopias. Srinjoy                                             are generally seen, placing
            “When I played with my clay, my father would select one   with art but also with an understanding of the larger    says, “Perhaps seeing my father                                             celebrities such as Marilyn
            of the figures from my crazy mess and announce that   “art world.” He says, “I believed that I was born to be an   as a successful artist, as well as                                          Monroe and characters such
            it was a masterpiece.” Srinjoy’s father would display the   artist and that I belonged in the art world,” Srinjoy says.   reading about and seeing the                                         as Mickey Mouse in stories
            clay figure in a showcase in their house, alongside his   Eventually, he made art his career.                      works of the greatest artists in                                            where we wouldn’t expect to
            collection of artifacts from around the world.
                                                                 Srinjoy’s father never imposed any rules or guidelines on     history, gave me a utopian image                                            see them. When the unique
            Srinjoy also spent many evenings with his father visiting   him to paint in a particular way. He inspired Srinjoy to   of the art world.” And of course,                                       digital collage is created,
            the studios of artisans and potters. Srinjoy says, “On these   be intuitive and to find his own creative expression. As   he adds, Bollywood movies and                                        Srinjoy incorporates it into
            magical evenings, I would explore the amazing artworks   a result, Srinjoy believed that he could somehow create   the huge, colorful, hand-painted                                            his painting. In this way, the
            that were being made. I can still smell the clay in those   his own new kind of artistic technique. He was always   billboards for them could look like utopias, too.   “ICON” collection helps us to see the world differently—
            studios and see the artists’ tools scattered everywhere.”   very fond of collaging and assemblage. Another favorite   Utopias can be inspiring models of hope. As Srinjoy got   just as Srinjoy’s early experiences with art helped him to
            When he was really young, Srinjoy would often invade   was scribbling on printed images from newspapers or         older, he learned that utopias can’t always be achieved.   create a world all his own.
            his father’s studio when he was busy painting, and sit   magazines to create a new image. His childhood was        “Confronting the failed utopias in my personal life, and]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Artist Profile














                 Childhood






                      and






 Srinjoy Gangopadhyay was born into     Utopia
 a family of artists in Kolkata, India.
 His father was a very popular illustrator
 and studio artist, and as a child, Srinjoy was   filled with Hindu and Buddhist mythological stories   in the world, made me aware of the contradictions
 surrounded by paint, paper, canvas, and   and religious art. The books on ancient Indian Art   between Utopia and reality,” he admits. “This, in turn,
 the smell of oil paint. His father’s studio had   fascinated Srinjoy, especially the amazing monumental   made me interested in exploring ‘Utopia’ in my art.” To do
 books and catalogs about many artists—  with a brush in his hand, painting right next to him. After   murals in the Ajanta Caves. He   this, he is influenced by the
 ranging from the great masters of Renaissance Art to   a while, Srinjoy asked his father for “that brush” he was   also read graphic novels like   visual language of “Pop” and
 Modern Art and the Surrealists. “From a very young age,”   painting with. “I thought it was the brush that made all   the “Amar Chitra Katha” series,   Urban Art: internet memes,
 he says, “I would turn the pages and immerse myself in   the difference!”  with its stories from the worlds   colorful vintage Bollywood
 the ocean of paintings they showed.” Later, he read about   of mythological Hindu and   billboards, Dada collages,
 many artists’ lives and their artistic journeys.   Srinjoy’s uncle, who was into advertising and graphic
 design, used to play a game with him. He would draw a   Buddhist Gods, as well as Marvel   and street art/graffiti culture.
 On his first day of school, Srinjoy came home and made   few lines on a blank piece of paper; then he’d challenge   and DC comics.  In his “ICON” series
 drawings of the school, his new friends, parents, and cars.   Srinjoy to draw something that incorporated those   In his current art practice,   of paintings, he uses
 His father was very enthusiastic about his early creations:   lines—filling in the blanks to finish the drawing. It   he has focused on the theme of   popular images of famous
 He framed a few of Srinjoy’s drawings to hang in the   was Srinjoy’s favorite game. In addition to visiting art   “Utopia,” or a perfect world. He   personalities; he reinterprets
 family home. There was no shortage of art materials in   exhibitions, he also got to meet many of his father’s   has always been drawn to images   how these personalities
 their house, and Srinjoy was lucky to play with them.   famous artist friends. His childhood was not only filled   and stories of utopias. Srinjoy   are generally seen, placing
 “When I played with my clay, my father would select one   with art but also with an understanding of the larger   says, “Perhaps seeing my father   celebrities such as Marilyn
 of the figures from my crazy mess and announce that   “art world.” He says, “I believed that I was born to be an   as a successful artist, as well as   Monroe and characters such
 it was a masterpiece.” Srinjoy’s father would display the   artist and that I belonged in the art world,” Srinjoy says.   reading about and seeing the   as Mickey Mouse in stories
 clay figure in a showcase in their house, alongside his   Eventually, he made art his career.   works of the greatest artists in   where we wouldn’t expect to
 collection of artifacts from around the world.
 Srinjoy’s father never imposed any rules or guidelines on   history, gave me a utopian image   see them. When the unique
 Srinjoy also spent many evenings with his father visiting   him to paint in a particular way. He inspired Srinjoy to   of the art world.” And of course,   digital collage is created,
 the studios of artisans and potters. Srinjoy says, “On these   be intuitive and to find his own creative expression. As   he adds, Bollywood movies and   Srinjoy incorporates it into
 magical evenings, I would explore the amazing artworks   a result, Srinjoy believed that he could somehow create   the huge, colorful, hand-painted   his painting. In this way, the
 that were being made. I can still smell the clay in those   his own new kind of artistic technique. He was always   billboards for them could look like utopias, too.   “ICON” collection helps us to see the world differently—
 studios and see the artists’ tools scattered everywhere.”   very fond of collaging and assemblage. Another favorite   Utopias can be inspiring models of hope. As Srinjoy got   just as Srinjoy’s early experiences with art helped him to
 When he was really young, Srinjoy would often invade   was scribbling on printed images from newspapers or   older, he learned that utopias can’t always be achieved.   create a world all his own.
 his father’s studio when he was busy painting, and sit   magazines to create a new image. His childhood was   “Confronting the failed utopias in my personal life, and]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[In Her Own Words:



        A conversation with Melissa Menzer, Ph.D.



        Tell us what you do at the National Endowment          participate in certain activities, and what that could mean for
        for the Arts.                                          their development. Also in college, I graduated with degrees in
                                                               both psychology and studio art. I also interned in a research lab
        Working at the National Endowment for the Arts brings together
        my two main interests: psychological research and the arts.   at the University of Maryland; we studied children’s and teens’
                                                               relationships with their families and with other kids and teens, and
        The Arts Endowment is a federal agency that gives people the           how those relationships affected the young
        opportunity to participate in the arts, exercise their imaginations,   people’s development.
        and develop their creativity. I work in
        the Office of Research & Analysis, which                               Can you discuss this line of research a
        conducts and supports research on the                                  little more?
        importance and the impact of the arts for                              Humans are social beings, so our
        people and communities.                                                relationships with family and friends—

        For example, I produced a research report                              especially people we’re close with—are
        about the social and emotional benefits for          Melissa Menzer    important to how healthy and satisfied
        young children when they participate in                                we feel. Even how we feel and think about
        the arts. [To read this report, go to arts.gov/                        those relationships can affect our well-being.
        sites/default/files/arts-in-early-childhood-dec2015-rev.pdf.]   There’s a lot of research on this topic.
                                                               Did you find there are certain things about studying art
        For another project, I guest-edited (with Dr. Adam Winsler at                                                                                                                        Art by
        George Mason University) a special section in the journal Early   that are similar to being a psychology researcher?                                                                 Alexandria J.
        Childhood Research Quarterly about how children benefit from   Well, they’re certainly different fields. But I feel like they’re a good
        being exposed to the arts and making art, with eight different   combination and help to create balance in my life. There’s an art
        articles from researchers around the world. [To view a webinar on   to doing research. And, some artists conduct research before they
        these research articles, see arts.gov/stories/video/new-research-  even start on an art project, to find out the best way to express
        arts-early-childhood-symposium.]                       what they’re trying to show.
        Are there any studies in recent years that you find    [As for research,] it’s very important to have a curious mind and
        especially noteworthy?                                 the drive to know how something works, or to figure something
                                                               out. Psychology researchers put a lot of thought into how we
        Yes. Studies that explain how the arts influence health and   approach our research questions. You think about the people
        biology—particularly for children—help us understand   you’re trying to study, or what makes the most sense for that
        how important the arts are for human functioning and child   particular group.
        development. One project that we supported through a grant   This issue of ChildArt is about the ABCD Study. Why is the
        shows how taking part in art activities can “get under your skin”   study so special?
        in a good way and reduce your stress level. [To read this research
        article, go to arts.gov/sites/default/files/Research-Art-Works-  Longitudinal studies (studies that run for a period of time),
        WestChester.pdf.]                                      especially large ones like the ABCD Study, can be really exciting.
                                                               You can track people across time to see if specific experiences
        How did you become interested in child developmental   relate to things that happen later.
        psychology as an area of research?
                                                               For the arts, the ABCD Study helps the Arts Endowment better
        In college, I volunteered to work with young children and their   understand the links between the arts and how people develop.
        caregivers during large play group sessions and arts activities. I   Specifically, we hope to learn how teens’ participation in the arts is
        enjoyed seeing the ways the children and families interacted. This   related to how they develop now and in the future.
        experience encouraged me to think about why the kids would
                                                               Do you still “do” art?
                                                               I took art and music lessons and courses when I was younger.
                                                               In college, I focused on painting, drawing, and print-making.
        By Sunil Iyengar                                       Now, I think of myself as an arts consumer! I go to visual art,                                   Art by
        Director, Office of Research & Analysis                music, dance, theatre, and poetry events; I also read fiction and                                Colin S.
        National Endowment for the Arts                        nonfiction books, listen to music and audiobooks, and watch films.]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[In Her Own Words:



 A conversation with Melissa Menzer, Ph.D.



 Tell us what you do at the National Endowment    participate in certain activities, and what that could mean for
 for the Arts.  their development. Also in college, I graduated with degrees in
 both psychology and studio art. I also interned in a research lab
 Working at the National Endowment for the Arts brings together
 my two main interests: psychological research and the arts.   at the University of Maryland; we studied children’s and teens’
 relationships with their families and with other kids and teens, and
 The Arts Endowment is a federal agency that gives people the   how those relationships affected the young
 opportunity to participate in the arts, exercise their imaginations,   people’s development.
 and develop their creativity. I work in
 the Office of Research & Analysis, which   Can you discuss this line of research a
 conducts and supports research on the   little more?
 importance and the impact of the arts for   Humans are social beings, so our
 people and communities.   relationships with family and friends—

 For example, I produced a research report   especially people we’re close with—are
 about the social and emotional benefits for   Melissa Menzer  important to how healthy and satisfied
 young children when they participate in   we feel. Even how we feel and think about
 the arts. [To read this report, go to arts.gov/  those relationships can affect our well-being.
 sites/default/files/arts-in-early-childhood-dec2015-rev.pdf.]   There’s a lot of research on this topic.
 Did you find there are certain things about studying art
 For another project, I guest-edited (with Dr. Adam Winsler at        Art by
 George Mason University) a special section in the journal Early   that are similar to being a psychology researcher?   Alexandria J.
 Childhood Research Quarterly about how children benefit from   Well, they’re certainly different fields. But I feel like they’re a good
 being exposed to the arts and making art, with eight different   combination and help to create balance in my life. There’s an art
 articles from researchers around the world. [To view a webinar on   to doing research. And, some artists conduct research before they
 these research articles, see arts.gov/stories/video/new-research-  even start on an art project, to find out the best way to express
 arts-early-childhood-symposium.]   what they’re trying to show.
 Are there any studies in recent years that you find   [As for research,] it’s very important to have a curious mind and
 especially noteworthy?  the drive to know how something works, or to figure something
 out. Psychology researchers put a lot of thought into how we
 Yes. Studies that explain how the arts influence health and   approach our research questions. You think about the people
 biology—particularly for children—help us understand   you’re trying to study, or what makes the most sense for that
 how important the arts are for human functioning and child   particular group.
 development. One project that we supported through a grant   This issue of ChildArt is about the ABCD Study. Why is the
 shows how taking part in art activities can “get under your skin”   study so special?
 in a good way and reduce your stress level. [To read this research
 article, go to arts.gov/sites/default/files/Research-Art-Works-  Longitudinal studies (studies that run for a period of time),
 WestChester.pdf.]   especially large ones like the ABCD Study, can be really exciting.
 You can track people across time to see if specific experiences
 How did you become interested in child developmental   relate to things that happen later.
 psychology as an area of research?
 For the arts, the ABCD Study helps the Arts Endowment better
 In college, I volunteered to work with young children and their   understand the links between the arts and how people develop.
 caregivers during large play group sessions and arts activities. I   Specifically, we hope to learn how teens’ participation in the arts is
 enjoyed seeing the ways the children and families interacted. This   related to how they develop now and in the future.
 experience encouraged me to think about why the kids would
 Do you still “do” art?
 I took art and music lessons and courses when I was younger.
 In college, I focused on painting, drawing, and print-making.
 By Sunil Iyengar  Now, I think of myself as an arts consumer! I go to visual art,   Art by
 Director, Office of Research & Analysis  music, dance, theatre, and poetry events; I also read fiction and   Colin S.
 National Endowment for the Arts  nonfiction books, listen to music and audiobooks, and watch films.]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[When Science Meets Art





        Dr. Hina Inam tells ChildArt Guest Editor, Dr. Katia Howlett,

        about her Artistic Journey to Medicine

                                  “        Every child is an artist.




                                                                           ”
                                   The problem is to remain an artist

                                              once they grow up.


                                                                         —Pablo Picasso



        This was a favorite quote of mine when I was
        growing up. As a young child, I often sat on the stairs with
        my sketchbook, drawing my thoughts. This passion stayed
        with me, and eventually it became a part of my profession.
        Strange as it may sound, surgery and the arts are closely
        connected. Just as a painter thinks about and executes
        a painting, a surgeon is an artist creating masterpieces                                                                      Hina Inam
        in the operating room (OR). I simply shifted from having
        paintbrushes in my hand to a scalpel.
        Along my career path, the International Child Art
        Foundation (ICAF) has played a big role. I was once a shy
        little girl, but going to the United States representing my
        country at the World Children’s Festival and meeting all
        those incredibly talented kids, gave me confidence. Art
        became my speech; it became my passion. When I felt
        happy, I’d draw. When I felt sad, I’d find comfort in art. It also   Hina at the 1999 World Children’s Festival
        plays an important role in who I am today.                       on the National Mall in Washington, DC
        It all began on a long Sunday, when I was a medical intern   I graduated in December 2019 as the first female cardiac
        at the busiest cardiothoracic (heart and chest) surgery   surgery resident from Aga Khan University Hospital (AKUH)
        service in Karachi, the largest city in Pakistan. I was called   in Karachi, and then joined AKUH as a Senior Resident. The
        to the OR. Because I had worked so hard as a student   job at this very busy cardiothoracic surgery service involves
        and intern, I was given the opportunity to perform a   six days of operations and academic activities. A supervisor
        “sternotomy” (chest opening). When I did, I saw the human   watches while I perform surgery. I also assist with coronary
        heart and the lungs for the first time. Simply put, it was love   artery surgeries for adults, and with replacing patients’
        at first sight. In that moment, I knew without any doubt   heart valves.
        that this was what I wanted to do for the rest of my life.
                                                               Even though my routine is very busy, I take time out to
        While I was still an intern, I started reading about cardiac   sketch, draw, and paint whenever I can. It gives me peace.
        surgeries. Whenever I had time, I drew different views of the   It’s my “happy place” after a long day’s work. Art has helped
        heart. I was fascinated by the heart’s rhythm and efficiency.   me grow in so many ways: It has taught me patience, made
        Even today, while I’m waiting for the patient to be prepared   me focus, and made me passionate. All these qualities have
        for surgery, I usually sketch. This helps me “see” the steps of   helped me grow in my career, too. Now my canvas is the
        the operation, and concentrate on what I plan to do for the   human heart, and stitches are my paints.
        patient. It’s much like the steps of a dance.]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[When Science Meets Art





 Dr. Hina Inam tells ChildArt Guest Editor, Dr. Katia Howlett,

 about her Artistic Journey to Medicine

 “ Every child is an artist.




 ”
 The problem is to remain an artist

 once they grow up.


                      —Pablo Picasso



 This was a favorite quote of mine when I was
 growing up. As a young child, I often sat on the stairs with
 my sketchbook, drawing my thoughts. This passion stayed
 with me, and eventually it became a part of my profession.
 Strange as it may sound, surgery and the arts are closely
 connected. Just as a painter thinks about and executes
 a painting, a surgeon is an artist creating masterpieces   Hina Inam
 in the operating room (OR). I simply shifted from having
 paintbrushes in my hand to a scalpel.
 Along my career path, the International Child Art
 Foundation (ICAF) has played a big role. I was once a shy
 little girl, but going to the United States representing my
 country at the World Children’s Festival and meeting all
 those incredibly talented kids, gave me confidence. Art
 became my speech; it became my passion. When I felt
 happy, I’d draw. When I felt sad, I’d find comfort in art. It also   Hina at the 1999 World Children’s Festival
 plays an important role in who I am today.  on the National Mall in Washington, DC
 It all began on a long Sunday, when I was a medical intern   I graduated in December 2019 as the first female cardiac
 at the busiest cardiothoracic (heart and chest) surgery   surgery resident from Aga Khan University Hospital (AKUH)
 service in Karachi, the largest city in Pakistan. I was called   in Karachi, and then joined AKUH as a Senior Resident. The
 to the OR. Because I had worked so hard as a student   job at this very busy cardiothoracic surgery service involves
 and intern, I was given the opportunity to perform a   six days of operations and academic activities. A supervisor
 “sternotomy” (chest opening). When I did, I saw the human   watches while I perform surgery. I also assist with coronary
 heart and the lungs for the first time. Simply put, it was love   artery surgeries for adults, and with replacing patients’
 at first sight. In that moment, I knew without any doubt   heart valves.
 that this was what I wanted to do for the rest of my life.
 Even though my routine is very busy, I take time out to
 While I was still an intern, I started reading about cardiac   sketch, draw, and paint whenever I can. It gives me peace.
 surgeries. Whenever I had time, I drew different views of the   It’s my “happy place” after a long day’s work. Art has helped
 heart. I was fascinated by the heart’s rhythm and efficiency.   me grow in so many ways: It has taught me patience, made
 Even today, while I’m waiting for the patient to be prepared   me focus, and made me passionate. All these qualities have
 for surgery, I usually sketch. This helps me “see” the steps of   helped me grow in my career, too. Now my canvas is the
 the operation, and concentrate on what I plan to do for the   human heart, and stitches are my paints.
 patient. It’s much like the steps of a dance.]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[When Art Meets Science





        Dr. Viviana Astudillo-Clavijo talks with ChildArt’s

        Managing Editor, Amy Enke




        One spring day in 1999, nine-year-old Viviana
        Astudillo-Clavijo’s mother received an important
        phone call. Viviana had just won an ICAF art competition.
        She was invited to represent her country, Canada, at
        the World Children’s Festival (WCF) in Washington, D.C.
        Her whole family was excited for her, and they traveled
        together to the event. While there, Viviana visited the White
        House and made new friends from all over the world.

        Before the trip, a local politician heard about Viviana and
        brought her pins with a picture of the Canadian flag on
        them, to give to other children. Many of the children at
        WCF brought items like this from their own countries and
        had fun trading them with each other. Now, twenty years
        later, Viviana still has the pins she collected at the festival,
        displaying them in a frame. She also stays in touch with
        some friends she met there—including one who lives
        almost 9,000 miles away in Africa.
        Viviana’s interest in art began early. As a child, she loved to
        draw. Some of her earliest artistic memories are of drawing
        on paper napkins at restaurants while her family waited
        for the food to arrive. The love of art came quite naturally
        to her, but the skill of art required work. She was frustrated
        by wanting her art to be better, but she learned early on
        to just keep working. Her mother would bring her how-to                                                                         Viviana’s winning art was a painting entitled, “My World in the Year 2000.” It depicts a line of children walking
        books from the library, and finally, at age fourteen, she                                                                              hand in hand, in pursuit of peace, sharing, and joy—the words she painted onto the canvas.
        took her first real art class at a local studio. To kids today              Art by Viviana Astudillo-Clavijo
        she says, “Continue exploring, embrace challenges, and use
        mistakes as fuel for your next project.”               Today, Viviana uses her artistic skills in a different way. While   concepts in science.” Much of her research                     Viviana credits ICAF with helping to foster
                                                               earning a Ph.D. in Evolutionary Biology from the University     is based on specimens of fish, and sketches,                       her creativity.  “ICAF gave me confidence to
                                                               of Toronto, she blended art with science and used that          diagrams, slides, and images are some of her                       continue making art. It validated something
                                                               combination to teach others. Her scientific specialty is        most useful research tools.                                        that I thought was just fun as a more serious
                                                               ichthyology (pronounced ik-thee-OL-a-jee)—the study of          Many museums conduct research, and                                 part of my life.” She found inspiration at
                                                               fishes; her art specialties are murals, paintings, and pencil   today, Viviana helps students learn how                            the WCF in being surrounded by other
                                                               and ink drawings.                                               to use specimens in the natural history                            people with similar interests. ICAF aims to
                                                               Several times, she wondered whether to pursue art or            section of Canada’s Royal Ontario Museum.                          help develop empathy and creativity in the
                                                               science as a profession. Ultimately, she has found many         She presents her research at the museum,                           world’s future leaders, and Viviana’s story is
                                                               opportunities to enhance her own study of biology with          answers questions for museum visitors, and                         filled with both of those qualities. Through
                                                               art, and to share and teach science through art. Viviana        lectures for groups of university students.                        her work as an artist, a scientist, and a
                                                               says, “Art led me to where I am today. I definitely want it to   She has also contributed her artworks to                          teacher, she has contributed to the mission
                                                               remain part of my profession. Art is not officially recognized   teaching exhibits, including a series of                          of peace, sharing, and joy that she imagined
                                                               as part of my degree program or my profession, but I find it    layered puzzles that show the anatomy of                           with her first winning painting.
                                                               to be a useful tool for both teaching and learning complex      different animals.
             Viviana at ICAF’s World Children’s Festival in 1999.]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[When Art Meets Science





 Dr. Viviana Astudillo-Clavijo talks with ChildArt’s

 Managing Editor, Amy Enke




 One spring day in 1999, nine-year-old Viviana
 Astudillo-Clavijo’s mother received an important
 phone call. Viviana had just won an ICAF art competition.
 She was invited to represent her country, Canada, at
 the World Children’s Festival (WCF) in Washington, D.C.
 Her whole family was excited for her, and they traveled
 together to the event. While there, Viviana visited the White
 House and made new friends from all over the world.

 Before the trip, a local politician heard about Viviana and
 brought her pins with a picture of the Canadian flag on
 them, to give to other children. Many of the children at
 WCF brought items like this from their own countries and
 had fun trading them with each other. Now, twenty years
 later, Viviana still has the pins she collected at the festival,
 displaying them in a frame. She also stays in touch with
 some friends she met there—including one who lives
 almost 9,000 miles away in Africa.
 Viviana’s interest in art began early. As a child, she loved to
 draw. Some of her earliest artistic memories are of drawing
 on paper napkins at restaurants while her family waited
 for the food to arrive. The love of art came quite naturally
 to her, but the skill of art required work. She was frustrated
 by wanting her art to be better, but she learned early on
 to just keep working. Her mother would bring her how-to   Viviana’s winning art was a painting entitled, “My World in the Year 2000.” It depicts a line of children walking
 books from the library, and finally, at age fourteen, she   hand in hand, in pursuit of peace, sharing, and joy—the words she painted onto the canvas.
 took her first real art class at a local studio. To kids today   Art by Viviana Astudillo-Clavijo
 she says, “Continue exploring, embrace challenges, and use
 mistakes as fuel for your next project.”  Today, Viviana uses her artistic skills in a different way. While   concepts in science.” Much of her research   Viviana credits ICAF with helping to foster
 earning a Ph.D. in Evolutionary Biology from the University   is based on specimens of fish, and sketches,   her creativity.  “ICAF gave me confidence to
 of Toronto, she blended art with science and used that   diagrams, slides, and images are some of her   continue making art. It validated something
 combination to teach others. Her scientific specialty is   most useful research tools.  that I thought was just fun as a more serious
 ichthyology (pronounced ik-thee-OL-a-jee)—the study of   Many museums conduct research, and   part of my life.” She found inspiration at
 fishes; her art specialties are murals, paintings, and pencil   today, Viviana helps students learn how   the WCF in being surrounded by other
 and ink drawings.  to use specimens in the natural history                people with similar interests. ICAF aims to
 Several times, she wondered whether to pursue art or   section of Canada’s Royal Ontario Museum.   help develop empathy and creativity in the
 science as a profession. Ultimately, she has found many   She presents her research at the museum,   world’s future leaders, and Viviana’s story is
 opportunities to enhance her own study of biology with   answers questions for museum visitors, and   filled with both of those qualities. Through
 art, and to share and teach science through art. Viviana   lectures for groups of university students.   her work as an artist, a scientist, and a
 says, “Art led me to where I am today. I definitely want it to   She has also contributed her artworks to   teacher, she has contributed to the mission
 remain part of my profession. Art is not officially recognized   teaching exhibits, including a series of   of peace, sharing, and joy that she imagined
 as part of my degree program or my profession, but I find it   layered puzzles that show the anatomy of   with her first winning painting.
 to be a useful tool for both teaching and learning complex   different animals.
 Viviana at ICAF’s World Children’s Festival in 1999.]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[Art by Vicky V.                                                                                                                                                        A lie so beautiful it becomes truth.
                                                                                                                                                                                               Art is a lie,





                                                                                                                                                                                              Art is deception,

                                                                                                                                                                              Deception so powerful it becomes reality.

                                                                                                                                                                                   Reality is the brain’s playground,

                                                                                                                                                                            Through which we are invited to roam freely.

                                                                                                                                                                                Weighing in at a modest three pounds,

                                                                                                                                                                           Our brain can’t even seem to understand itself,

                                                                                                                                                                         So how then does it help us understand our world?

                                                                                                                                                                                     Captive to electrical impulses,
                      Neuroscience = Art                                                                                                                                     Our experiences form our view of the world.



                                                                                                                                                                                       Our brain colors our reality,

                                                                                                                                                                           A reality painted by the lenses of our choosing.

                                                                                                                                                                                     Captive to nerves and neurons,

                                                                                                                                                                         Our brain manipulates our past and draws on our
                                                                                                                                                                                                    future.


                                                Art by                                                                                                                                        Deception is art,
                                                Max J.
                                                                                                                                                                                     An art the brain has mastered.

                                                                                                                                                                                           Although art is a lie,

                                                                                                                                                                                           It is the brain’s truth.

                                                                                                                                                                                        Although art is deception,

                                                                                                                                                                                          It is the brain’s reality.

                                                                                                                                                                                             The brain is a lie,

                                                                                                                                                                                      A lie so beautiful that it is art.


                                                                                                                                                                                               —Michael Kofi Esson, Research Assistant
                                                                                                                                                                                                     University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee



                                                                                                                                                        Art by Savannah C.
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       31]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Art by Vicky V.                                            A lie so beautiful it becomes truth.
                                                                        Art is a lie,





                                                                       Art is deception,

                                                       Deception so powerful it becomes reality.

                                                             Reality is the brain’s playground,

                                                     Through which we are invited to roam freely.

                                                         Weighing in at a modest three pounds,

                                                    Our brain can’t even seem to understand itself,

                                                  So how then does it help us understand our world?

                                                              Captive to electrical impulses,
 Neuroscience = Art                                   Our experiences form our view of the world.



                                                                Our brain colors our reality,

                                                    A reality painted by the lenses of our choosing.

                                                              Captive to nerves and neurons,

                                                  Our brain manipulates our past and draws on our
                                                                             future.


 Art by                                                                Deception is art,
 Max J.
                                                              An art the brain has mastered.

                                                                     Although art is a lie,

                                                                    It is the brain’s truth.

                                                                 Although art is deception,

                                                                   It is the brain’s reality.

                                                                      The brain is a lie,

                                                               A lie so beautiful that it is art.


                                                                        —Michael Kofi Esson, Research Assistant
                                                                              University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee



                                 Art by Savannah C.
                                                                                                                31]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[How Neuroscience Helps Answer


        the Question: What Is Beauty?






        If someone asked you what’s beautiful, you might       Thus, neuroaesthetics is the study of how the brain
        tell them about a flower, or about a person you’re close   experiences beauty. Scientists that research the brain,
        with, a painting you like, or even a building in your city. If   neuroscientists, take advantage of developments in
        that person then asked you, “Why is that beautiful?,” you’d   technology to investigate how people perceive beauty.
        probably find that harder to answer. We all experience   In one study, researchers used magnetic resonance imaging
        beauty differently, and we’re drawn to different types of   (MRI) to look at a person’s brain activity when they listened
        things. But why?                                       to music. The researchers found that the more a person

        The questions of what beauty is and why we all experience   liked a song, the more activity there was in a particular
        it differently were discussed as far back as ancient Greece.   pathway in their brain (called the mesolimbic striatum).3
        The philosopher Plato asked, “What is beauty?” in Hippias   Neuroscientists have also looked at how professional
        Major, which he wrote in 390 B.C.1 Since then, many people   artists experience things differently than novices. In one
        have tried to understand beauty better. In 1757, the   experiment, researchers found that established artists were
        Scottish philosopher David Hume said that maybe some   not better at making sense of some kinds of basic visual
        people, like artists and art critics, were better at perceiving   information than novices; in other words, something else
        beauty because others have been biased by experiences   is responsible for the more experienced artists’ ability to
        which taint their view of beauty.2 These debates and   create their artworks.4 In another, art students perceived
        questions are still with us today. Whenever you disagree   things mostly the way non-art students did, but changes
        with a movie review, enjoy reading a novel or short story,   in the art students’ brains were related to their increased
        debate a friend about how good a singer is, or admire a   creativity and artistic skills.
        painting, you are making a small judgment about what is   Neuroscientists have increased our understanding of what
        beautiful and why.                                     beauty is and how we experience it, but a lot of questions
        As technology developed over the years, scientists became   remain. In the future, scientists may be able to understand
        able to understand more about what people find beautiful   how to create songs or paintings that are even more
        and why. This scientific field is called “neuroaesthetics.”   beautiful than the ones we have now; they might know
        “Neuro” means relating to nerves or the brain; aesthetics   why humans are drawn to beauty in nature, like mountains
        (pronounced es-THEH-tiks) is the philosophy of beauty.   and flowers; they might even know how to use art more
                                                               effectively as therapy to help sick people get better. In
                                                               the meantime, when you find yourself liking a particular
                                                               song or finding one painting prettier than another, you
                                                               can appreciate the beauty of both the art and the amazing
                                                               brain that, together, are creating the experience.
                                                                                                                                            Electrical lines and streetlights depicted as firing neutrons illuminate an American neighborhood in
                                                                                                                                                                   a moment of silence on Blackout Tuesday.
                                          By Calen Smith
                                                                                                                                    “
                                          Research Assistant                                                                               Imagine what your mind looks like when you sympathize with the
                                          University of Utah
                                                                                                                                          pain of others. It is fascinating that we, as humans, are created for


                                                                                                                                           solidarity regardless of culture. Through this work of art, I hope to
        1  Plato. (1986). Plato’s Hippias major. Bryn Mawr, Pa.: Thomas Library, Bryn Mawr College.                                     community. We are all capable of feeling empathy. We can experience
        2  Hume, D. (1757). Of the standards of taste. Essays Moral, Political, and Literary (pp. 226-249). Liberty Classics: https://philpapers.org/rec/HUMOTS.
        3  Salimpoor, V., den Bosch, I., Kovacevic, N., McIntosh, A., Dagher, A., Zatorre, R. (2013). Interactions Between the Nucleus Accumbens and Auditory   bring consolation to everyone that has been negatively affected by
         Cortices Predict Music Reward Value. Science. 340 (6129), pp 216-219. DOI: 10.1126/science.1231059.                                      ongoing racial injustice amid the COVID-19 pandemic.
        4  Perdreau, F., & Cavanagh, P. (2013). Is artists’ perception more veridical? Frontiers in Neuroscience. 7(6). https://doi.org/10.3389/fnins.2013.00006                                                    ”
        5  Schlegel, A., Alexander, P., Fogelson, S., Li, X., Lu, Z., Kohler, P...... Meng, M. (2015). The artist emerges: Visual art learning alters neural structure and                           —Laili Xie, Research Assistant
         function. NeuroImage. 105. 440- 51. DOI: 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2014.11.014                                                                                                              University of California, San Diego]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[How Neuroscience Helps Answer


 the Question: What Is Beauty?






 If someone asked you what’s beautiful, you might   Thus, neuroaesthetics is the study of how the brain
 tell them about a flower, or about a person you’re close   experiences beauty. Scientists that research the brain,
 with, a painting you like, or even a building in your city. If   neuroscientists, take advantage of developments in
 that person then asked you, “Why is that beautiful?,” you’d   technology to investigate how people perceive beauty.
 probably find that harder to answer. We all experience   In one study, researchers used magnetic resonance imaging
 beauty differently, and we’re drawn to different types of   (MRI) to look at a person’s brain activity when they listened
 things. But why?   to music. The researchers found that the more a person

 The questions of what beauty is and why we all experience   liked a song, the more activity there was in a particular
 it differently were discussed as far back as ancient Greece.   pathway in their brain (called the mesolimbic striatum).3
 The philosopher Plato asked, “What is beauty?” in Hippias   Neuroscientists have also looked at how professional
 Major, which he wrote in 390 B.C.1 Since then, many people   artists experience things differently than novices. In one
 have tried to understand beauty better. In 1757, the   experiment, researchers found that established artists were
 Scottish philosopher David Hume said that maybe some   not better at making sense of some kinds of basic visual
 people, like artists and art critics, were better at perceiving   information than novices; in other words, something else
 beauty because others have been biased by experiences   is responsible for the more experienced artists’ ability to
 which taint their view of beauty.2 These debates and   create their artworks.4 In another, art students perceived
 questions are still with us today. Whenever you disagree   things mostly the way non-art students did, but changes
 with a movie review, enjoy reading a novel or short story,   in the art students’ brains were related to their increased
 debate a friend about how good a singer is, or admire a   creativity and artistic skills.
 painting, you are making a small judgment about what is   Neuroscientists have increased our understanding of what
 beautiful and why.   beauty is and how we experience it, but a lot of questions
 As technology developed over the years, scientists became   remain. In the future, scientists may be able to understand
 able to understand more about what people find beautiful   how to create songs or paintings that are even more
 and why. This scientific field is called “neuroaesthetics.”   beautiful than the ones we have now; they might know
 “Neuro” means relating to nerves or the brain; aesthetics   why humans are drawn to beauty in nature, like mountains
 (pronounced es-THEH-tiks) is the philosophy of beauty.   and flowers; they might even know how to use art more
 effectively as therapy to help sick people get better. In
 the meantime, when you find yourself liking a particular
 song or finding one painting prettier than another, you
 can appreciate the beauty of both the art and the amazing
 brain that, together, are creating the experience.
                     Electrical lines and streetlights depicted as firing neutrons illuminate an American neighborhood in
                                            a moment of silence on Blackout Tuesday.
 By Calen Smith
              “
 Research Assistant  Imagine what your mind looks like when you sympathize with the
 University of Utah
                   pain of others. It is fascinating that we, as humans, are created for


                    solidarity regardless of culture. Through this work of art, I hope to
 1  Plato. (1986). Plato’s Hippias major. Bryn Mawr, Pa.: Thomas Library, Bryn Mawr College.  community. We are all capable of feeling empathy. We can experience
 2  Hume, D. (1757). Of the standards of taste. Essays Moral, Political, and Literary (pp. 226-249). Liberty Classics: https://philpapers.org/rec/HUMOTS.
 3  Salimpoor, V., den Bosch, I., Kovacevic, N., McIntosh, A., Dagher, A., Zatorre, R. (2013). Interactions Between the Nucleus Accumbens and Auditory   bring consolation to everyone that has been negatively affected by
 Cortices Predict Music Reward Value. Science. 340 (6129), pp 216-219. DOI: 10.1126/science.1231059.  ongoing racial injustice amid the COVID-19 pandemic.
 4  Perdreau, F., & Cavanagh, P. (2013). Is artists’ perception more veridical? Frontiers in Neuroscience. 7(6). https://doi.org/10.3389/fnins.2013.00006   ”
 5  Schlegel, A., Alexander, P., Fogelson, S., Li, X., Lu, Z., Kohler, P...... Meng, M. (2015). The artist emerges: Visual art learning alters neural structure and   —Laili Xie, Research Assistant
 function. NeuroImage. 105. 440- 51. DOI: 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2014.11.014   University of California, San Diego]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[My Light                                                                                                       The ABCD Data Treasure Chest



            When someone dies                                                                                                  The Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development             importantly, the public.

            are they really gone?                                                                                              (ABCD) Study is following more than 11,800             Scientists are already analyzing the first two years of ABCD
                                                                                                                               children and their families in 21 communities          Study data. For example, two researchers at the University
          The apples in the garden                                                                                             across the United States. (“Cognitive development”     of Colorado, Boulder (one of the ABCD research sites)
                                                                                                                               means development of a person’s ability to think, learn,
         miss your callused touch,                                                                                             understand, and remember information.) Beginning when   have shown that children of mothers who had reported
                                                                                                                                                                                      using marijuana when they were pregnant had more sleep
                                                                                                                               the children were ages nine and ten, the study will follow   disorders.1 This observation will now be studied more
          and the Earth, it seems,                                                                                             them for ten years, collecting a treasure trove of information   deeply to see if being exposed to marijuana while they’re
             can’t weep enough.                                                                                                as the children navigate their teenage years and become   in the mother’s womb directly affects children’s sleep. (The
                                                                                                                               young adults. It will collect information about their physical   ABCD Study will help answer many other questions about
                 Forever feels                                                                                                 and mental health, activities, and academic progress;   possible long-term effects of being exposed to drugs in the
                                                                                                                               their environments; and the social and cultural forces that
                  more real                                                                                                                                                           womb.)
                                                                                                                               could either make them stronger or increase the risks
                                                                                                                               they face. And that’s just the beginning: The study is using   A research team at the National University of Singapore
             than the rain does.                                                                                               technologies such as advanced brain imaging methods    (not affiliated with ABCD) studied children who consumed
                 You’re gone                                                                                                   and wearable sensors to explore brain development, sleep   different amounts of caffeine and how well they learned,
                                                                                                                               patterns, and more.                                    thought, and remembered information. The researchers
                but the story                                                                                                                                                         found that children who consumed greater amounts of
                                                                                                                               In many ways, the ABCD Study reflects a new era of science.   caffeine scored lower on vocabulary tests, had a harder time
                    lives on                                                                                                   First, as one of only a few “big data” studies of its kind, it is   remembering information, and processed new information
                                                                                                                               collecting massive amounts of information from thousands   more slowly, and more. This might mean that consuming
                   in a bed                                                                         Art by Jake O.             of participants: genetic data, brain images from magnetic   more drinks containing caffeine (such as energy drinks and
                  of neurons                                                                                                   resonance imaging (MRI), and much more. It will all add   many soft drinks) affects kids’ cognitive abilities as they
                                                                                                                               up to many trillions of bytes of information! How is this   grow up; or it could mean that children whose cognitive
                you once said,                                                                                                 possible? Scientists can now ask—and get answers for—  abilities are affected by other things are more likely to drink
                                                                                                                               bigger questions than ever before, thanks to advances
             electrical impulses                                                                                               in computing, artificial intelligence (also called machine   these beverages. Finding out more about connections like
                                                                                                                                                                                      this can help families to support their children’s cognitive
                                                                                                                               learning), and data storage.                           development in the most effective ways.
             with enough power
                    to light                                                                                                   A second groundbreaking aspect of ABCD is that it uses   ABCD data are released to the wider research community
                                                                                                                               an “open science” model. This means that any researcher
                                                                                                                                                                                      once a year. In Fall/Winter 2020, the third batch of ABCD
                                                                                                                               anywhere in the world can apply for access to almost all of   data—ABCD Data Release 3.0—will be made available on
               entire universes.                                                                                               the information collected, and analyze that data on their   the ABCD website. This information will help us learn how
            I wish you were here                                                                                               own. The ABCD Study data could help answer many more   children’s involvement in arts activities like music, dance,
                                                                                                                               questions than the approximately 185 scientists who are   and visual arts may be related to how well they do in school
              but you are there                                                                                                directly involved in the study could explore. Researchers   (see “Music’s Harmony on the Developing Brain: Data from
            where stars like you                                                                                               can also review the answers that other researchers publish,   the ABCD Study” by Tim Brown and John Iversen on page
                                                                                                                               using the same data—helping to correct any mistakes and   16). These data—like all the data the study is collecting—
             are meant to burn                                                                                                 keep scientific progress moving more quickly. This will   could unlock new discoveries that improve the lives of
                                                                                                                               help everybody in the scientific community—and, most
           like diamonds studded                                                                                                                                                      children, adolescents, and adults.
                                                                                                                                                  To learn more about how to obtain data from the ABCD Study, visit nda.nih.gov/abcd.
                  in the sky,
                 your bright                                                                                                               Terry L. Jernigan, Ph.D.                                Sandra A. Brown, Ph.D.
                                                                                                                                           ABCD Study Principal Investigator                       ABCD Study Principal Investigator
                   presence                                                                                                                University of California, San Diego                     University of California, San Diego
                                                                                                                                           Professor of Cognitive Science, Psychiatry,
              forever my light.                                                                                                             and Radiology                                          Vice Chancellor for Research and

                                                                                                                                           Director of Center of Human Development                  Distinguished Professor
                     By Phillip Nguyen                                                     Art by Austin O.
                    Research Assistant                                                                                         1  https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2352721820301352?via%3Dihub
                University of Vermont                                                                                          2  https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00213-020-05596-8#Ack1]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[My Light  The ABCD Data Treasure Chest



 When someone dies   The Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development   importantly, the public.

 are they really gone?  (ABCD) Study is following more than 11,800   Scientists are already analyzing the first two years of ABCD
        children and their families in 21 communities          Study data. For example, two researchers at the University
 The apples in the garden   across the United States. (“Cognitive development”   of Colorado, Boulder (one of the ABCD research sites)
        means development of a person’s ability to think, learn,
 miss your callused touch,  understand, and remember information.) Beginning when   have shown that children of mothers who had reported
                                                               using marijuana when they were pregnant had more sleep
        the children were ages nine and ten, the study will follow   disorders.1 This observation will now be studied more
 and the Earth, it seems,   them for ten years, collecting a treasure trove of information   deeply to see if being exposed to marijuana while they’re
 can’t weep enough.  as the children navigate their teenage years and become   in the mother’s womb directly affects children’s sleep. (The
        young adults. It will collect information about their physical   ABCD Study will help answer many other questions about
 Forever feels   and mental health, activities, and academic progress;   possible long-term effects of being exposed to drugs in the
        their environments; and the social and cultural forces that
 more real                                                     womb.)
        could either make them stronger or increase the risks
        they face. And that’s just the beginning: The study is using   A research team at the National University of Singapore
 than the rain does.   technologies such as advanced brain imaging methods   (not affiliated with ABCD) studied children who consumed
 You’re gone  and wearable sensors to explore brain development, sleep   different amounts of caffeine and how well they learned,
        patterns, and more.                                    thought, and remembered information. The researchers
 but the story                                                 found that children who consumed greater amounts of
        In many ways, the ABCD Study reflects a new era of science.   caffeine scored lower on vocabulary tests, had a harder time
 lives on  First, as one of only a few “big data” studies of its kind, it is   remembering information, and processed new information
        collecting massive amounts of information from thousands   more slowly, and more. This might mean that consuming
 in a bed   Art by Jake O.  of participants: genetic data, brain images from magnetic   more drinks containing caffeine (such as energy drinks and
 of neurons  resonance imaging (MRI), and much more. It will all add   many soft drinks) affects kids’ cognitive abilities as they
        up to many trillions of bytes of information! How is this   grow up; or it could mean that children whose cognitive
 you once said,   possible? Scientists can now ask—and get answers for—  abilities are affected by other things are more likely to drink
        bigger questions than ever before, thanks to advances
 electrical impulses  in computing, artificial intelligence (also called machine   these beverages. Finding out more about connections like
                                                               this can help families to support their children’s cognitive
        learning), and data storage.                           development in the most effective ways.
 with enough power
 to light  A second groundbreaking aspect of ABCD is that it uses   ABCD data are released to the wider research community
        an “open science” model. This means that any researcher
                                                               once a year. In Fall/Winter 2020, the third batch of ABCD
        anywhere in the world can apply for access to almost all of   data—ABCD Data Release 3.0—will be made available on
 entire universes.   the information collected, and analyze that data on their   the ABCD website. This information will help us learn how
 I wish you were here  own. The ABCD Study data could help answer many more   children’s involvement in arts activities like music, dance,
        questions than the approximately 185 scientists who are   and visual arts may be related to how well they do in school
 but you are there   directly involved in the study could explore. Researchers   (see “Music’s Harmony on the Developing Brain: Data from
 where stars like you  can also review the answers that other researchers publish,   the ABCD Study” by Tim Brown and John Iversen on page
        using the same data—helping to correct any mistakes and   16). These data—like all the data the study is collecting—
 are meant to burn   keep scientific progress moving more quickly. This will   could unlock new discoveries that improve the lives of
        help everybody in the scientific community—and, most
 like diamonds studded                                         children, adolescents, and adults.
                           To learn more about how to obtain data from the ABCD Study, visit nda.nih.gov/abcd.
 in the sky,
 your bright        Terry L. Jernigan, Ph.D.                                Sandra A. Brown, Ph.D.
                    ABCD Study Principal Investigator                       ABCD Study Principal Investigator
 presence           University of California, San Diego                     University of California, San Diego
                    Professor of Cognitive Science, Psychiatry,
 forever my light.   and Radiology                                          Vice Chancellor for Research and

                    Director of Center of Human Development                   Distinguished Professor
 By Phillip Nguyen   Art by Austin O.
 Research Assistant   1  https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2352721820301352?via%3Dihub
 University of Vermont   2  https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00213-020-05596-8#Ack1]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[Art by Defne Y.                                           conscious experience. He called neurons “mysterious    practicing or playing music during adolescence have an
                                                                                                                                Science and Art Come Together  continued from page 5


                                                                                                                                                                                      effect on a person’s grades? Do arts like drawing or drama
                                                                                                                               butterflies of the soul.”
                                                                                                                                                                                      have effects on well-being?
                                                                                                                               We also now know that neurons, like butterflies, are
                                                                                                                               constantly changing. They’re always forming new
                                                                                                                               connections with one another, changing those connections   By working with kids from childhood to young adulthood,
                                                                                                                                                                                      the ABCD researchers will be able to see more precisely
                                                                                                                               based on our experiences, and also—especially when we’re   than ever how all of these young people’s activities and
                                                                                                                               children—allowing unused connections to wither away.   experiences during their second decade of life affect both
                                                                                                                               This constant changeability of the brain, called “plasticity,”   the way their brains mature, and other aspects of their
                                                                                                                               explains how we’re “wired” by our experiences. Every   physical and mental health.
                                                                                                                               experience changes the brain a little. And in the first couple   This issue of ChildArt is devoted to the ABCD Study, with
                                                                                                                               decades of life, experiences have extraordinary power to   articles by some of the scientists involved in the study, and
                                                                                                                               shape who we are and who we’ll be for the rest of our lives.   art by many of the children who are participating in it. I
                                            Art by Emma C.                                                                     From birth, and even from before birth, brain development   hope you find the brilliance and creativity of all of these
        Art by Paulina G.                                                                                                      is shaped by interaction with the environment. This    people as inspiring as I do. For more information about the
                                                                                                                               includes our physical environment—the food we eat and   ABCD Study, visit abcdstudy.org.
                                                                                                                               the air we breathe—and our cultural environment, such as
                                                                                                Art by Lillian D.              our family, school, media, and the arts.

                                                                                                                               The ABCD Study

                                                                                                                               My Institute, the National Institute on Drug Abuse, is now
                                                                                                                               leading the biggest-ever study of childhood experiences
                                                                                                                               and their effects on how the brain develops. The
                                                                                                                               Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development  Study (ABCD
                                                                                                                                                                 SM
                                                                                                                               Study®) is using advanced brain imaging and many other
                                                                                                                               research tools to study the changing brains of adolescents.
                                                                                                                               This study follows them through middle school and high
                                                                                                                               school, and into their first years of adulthood. It tracks many
                                                                                                                               of their experiences during that time: not only school and
                                                                                                                               physical activities like sports and sleep, but also creative

                                                          Art by Esther N.                                                     activities like music lessons or other kinds of art activities.
                                                                                                                               Research already suggests that getting training in the
                                                                                                                               arts, or practicing an art, strengthens parts of a person’s
                                                                                                                               brain. These parts include the prefrontal cortex, which
                                                                                                                               is necessary for judgment and critical thinking, and the
                                                                                                                               hippocampus, which is important for memory. The ABCD
                                                                                                                               Study will help us answer many questions, such as: Does
                                                                                                                                                                                                                      Art by Taylor H.
                                                                                                                                Movement and Dance  continued from page 15

                                                                                                                               versions of themselves performing the dance.           Researchers can learn a lot, too. Studying learning
                                                                                                                               Experiencing STEM “making” this way gives young people   at the intersections of STEM and the arts allows us
                                                     Art by Heather C.                                                         opportunities to look at scientific facts and events in many   to better understand educational experiences as a
                                                                                                                               different ways at the same time. They can also learn how   social determinant of health, specifically for youth in
                                                                                                                               to represent science in creative ways, and how to work   underrepresented communities. It can also help us to
                                                                                                                               with other students to develop and build on their ideas as   understand how making art can help young people
                                                                                                                               part of the creative process. The students are intrigued by   learn STEM subjects, feel good about themselves, and
                                                                                                                               uncertainty through hypothesizing, testing, iteration and   handle challenges better. Dance-making is creating more
                                                                                                                               revision, and modeling.                                than dance: It’s helping young people to live happier,
                                                                                                                                                                                      healthier lives.
                                                                                              Art by Alexandria J.
        Art by Austin O.                                  Art by Annele K.]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[Art by Defne Y.  conscious experience. He called neurons “mysterious   practicing or playing music during adolescence have an
         Science and Art Come Together  continued from page 5


                                                               effect on a person’s grades? Do arts like drawing or drama
        butterflies of the soul.”
                                                               have effects on well-being?
        We also now know that neurons, like butterflies, are
        constantly changing. They’re always forming new
        connections with one another, changing those connections   By working with kids from childhood to young adulthood,
                                                               the ABCD researchers will be able to see more precisely
        based on our experiences, and also—especially when we’re   than ever how all of these young people’s activities and
        children—allowing unused connections to wither away.   experiences during their second decade of life affect both
        This constant changeability of the brain, called “plasticity,”   the way their brains mature, and other aspects of their
        explains how we’re “wired” by our experiences. Every   physical and mental health.
        experience changes the brain a little. And in the first couple   This issue of ChildArt is devoted to the ABCD Study, with
        decades of life, experiences have extraordinary power to   articles by some of the scientists involved in the study, and
        shape who we are and who we’ll be for the rest of our lives.   art by many of the children who are participating in it. I
 Art by Emma C.  From birth, and even from before birth, brain development   hope you find the brilliance and creativity of all of these
 Art by Paulina G.  is shaped by interaction with the environment. This   people as inspiring as I do. For more information about the
        includes our physical environment—the food we eat and   ABCD Study, visit abcdstudy.org.
        the air we breathe—and our cultural environment, such as
 Art by Lillian D.  our family, school, media, and the arts.

        The ABCD Study

        My Institute, the National Institute on Drug Abuse, is now
        leading the biggest-ever study of childhood experiences
        and their effects on how the brain develops. The
        Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development  Study (ABCD
                                           SM
        Study®) is using advanced brain imaging and many other
        research tools to study the changing brains of adolescents.
        This study follows them through middle school and high
        school, and into their first years of adulthood. It tracks many
        of their experiences during that time: not only school and
        physical activities like sports and sleep, but also creative

 Art by Esther N.  activities like music lessons or other kinds of art activities.
        Research already suggests that getting training in the
        arts, or practicing an art, strengthens parts of a person’s
        brain. These parts include the prefrontal cortex, which
        is necessary for judgment and critical thinking, and the
        hippocampus, which is important for memory. The ABCD
        Study will help us answer many questions, such as: Does
                                                                                               Art by Taylor H.
         Movement and Dance  continued from page 15

        versions of themselves performing the dance.           Researchers can learn a lot, too. Studying learning
        Experiencing STEM “making” this way gives young people   at the intersections of STEM and the arts allows us
 Art by Heather C.  opportunities to look at scientific facts and events in many   to better understand educational experiences as a
        different ways at the same time. They can also learn how   social determinant of health, specifically for youth in
        to represent science in creative ways, and how to work   underrepresented communities. It can also help us to
        with other students to develop and build on their ideas as   understand how making art can help young people
        part of the creative process. The students are intrigued by   learn STEM subjects, feel good about themselves, and
        uncertainty through hypothesizing, testing, iteration and   handle challenges better. Dance-making is creating more
        revision, and modeling.                                than dance: It’s helping young people to live happier,
                                                               healthier lives.
 Art by Alexandria J.
 Art by Austin O.  Art by Annele K.]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[Resources                                                                                                              VOLUME 20, ISSUE 2, NUMBER 60                                                     OCTOBER – DECEMBER 2020




        NIDA                                                  NIDA for Teens
                                                              https://teens.drugabuse.gov/
        Mapping the Brain
                                                              Designed for teens and those who influence them, parents, guardians,
        https://teens.drugabuse.gov/teachers/lessonplans/mapping-brain   teachers, and other educators, the science-based information and          A View Through the ABCD Lens
        Developed in partnership with Scholastic, students learn about several   resources inspire learning and encourage critical thinking so teens can
        common types of brain-imaging technology used by neuroscientists   make informed decisions about their health.
        and doctors.                                                                                                             PUBLISHER AND EDITOR               in healthcare settings. Dr. Howlett received   SPECIAL THANKS
                                                              NEA                                                                Ashfaq Ishaq, Ph.D.                a Ph.D. in public health from the University   Frederick Marks, AIA, LEED AP BD+C, Six Sigma
                                                                                                                                 Ashfaq is the founder and chair of the
                                                                                                                                                                    of California, San Diego and San Diego State
                                                                                                                                                                                                      Green Belt
        The Awesomely Evolved Human Brain
                                                              The Arts in Early Childhood: Social and Emotional Benefits of      International Child Art Foundation (ICAF),   University, Master of Public Policy from   Fred is a Visiting Scholar and Research
        https://teens.drugabuse.gov/teachers/lessonplans/awesomely-  Arts Participation (a literature review by Melissa Menzer for the   established in 1997. He is an experienced   Pepperdine University, and Master of Business   Collaborator in the Regulatory Biology
        evolved-human-brain                                                                                                      entrepreneur, educator, manager, researcher,   Administration from the Johns Hopkins   Laboratory at the Salk Institute for Biological
                                                              National Endowment for the Arts):                                  and civil-sector leader. He holds a Ph.D. in   University.           Studies and was the impetus behind ICAF’s
        Developed in partnership with Scholastic, students learn about the                                                       economics from the George Washington                                 collaboration with the NIH. We are indebted
        brain’s ability to make predictions and solve ambiguities and how   https://www.arts.gov/sites/default/files/arts-in-early-childhood-  University, where he later served as adjunct   CONTRIBUTING EDITOR AND DESIGNER  to him for his guidance throughout the
        drugs might compromise these capabilities.            dec2015-rev.pdf                                                    associate professor of economics. Ashfaq   Eric M. Wargo, Ph.D.      development of this special issue of ChildArt.
                                                                                                                                 is spearheading a children’s revolution that   Assistant Guest Editor  Elizabeth Hoffman, Ph.D.
                                                                                                                                                                    Eric has a Ph.D. in anthropology from Emory
        “Wiring” Your Brain                                   Arts Section of Early Childhood Quarterly issue (co-edited by      treats children as creators (not merely pupils   University and works as a science writer and   Elizabeth is a Scientific Program Manager for
                                                              Melissa Menzer for the Arts Endowment):                            or consumers), takes their imagination as
        https://teens.drugabuse.gov/teachers/lessonplans/wiring-your-brain                                                       seedbed for invention and innovation, and   editor for NIDA’s Office of Science Policy and   the Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development
                                                              https://www.sciencedirect.com/journal/early-childhood-research-                                       Communications at NIH.            (ABCD) Study in NIDA’s Division of Extramural
        Developed in partnership with Scholastic, students learn that the   quarterly/vol/45/suppl/C                             respects their art as the most honest and                            Research at NIH. Dr. Hoffman holds a Ph.D. in
        choices they make today can help to shape and “wire” how their brains                                                    purest form of human creative expression. For   Oslo                 cognitive neuropsychology from the George
        will operate as adults.                                                                                                  the past two decades, he has been fostering   Creative Director      Washington University. Her contributions to
                                                              “New Evidence of the Benefits of Arts Education” (authored by      children’s creativity and empathy, since   Oslo of oslographics.com is a Graphic Artist   the content and providing an expert sounding
                                                              Brian Kisida and Daniel H. Bowen for the Brookings Institution,    creativity and empathy are key attributes of   and Designer in the D.C. Metro area. Since
        Sowing the Seeds of Neuroscience – Neuroscience 101                                                                                                         graduating from Virginia Tech in 1986 with a   board served to improve each part of the issue.
                                                              based on research supported with a National Endowment for          successful learners and leaders and are also
        https://teens.drugabuse.gov/teachers/lessonplans/sowing-seeds-  the Arts grant):                                         preconditions for sustainable prosperity and   B.A. in art, Oslo has been involved in graphic   The IQ Solutions Content and Creative Team
        neuroscience-neuroscience-101                                                                                            peace.                             arts in some form or another, always bringing   The IQ Solutions Team provided technical
                                                              https://www.brookings.edu/blog/brown-center-                                                          what others see in their head to life.   expertise, copy editing, and creative guidance.
        Part of the Sowing the Seeds of Neuroscience Series, students learn the   chalkboard/2019/02/12/new-evidence-of-the-benefits-of-arts-  GUEST EDITOR                                           Their contributions within a truncated period
        basic anatomy and physiology of the nervous system.   education/                                                         Katia Delrahim Howlett, Ph.D., M.P.P., M.B.A.                        of time were instrumental to the success of
                                                                                                                                 Katia is the Deputy Director of the Division of                      this issue–a true joy to work with.
                                                                                                                                 Extramural Research at the National Institute
        Transforming Science for Critical Thinkers            “Mind and Music Live with Renée Fleming” webinar series (with      on Drug Abuse (NIDA), National Institutes of                         ABCD Study Families, Researchers, and Staff
        https://teens.drugabuse.gov/teachers/lessonplans/transforming-  archived presentations):                                 Health (NIH). Prior to joining NIDA in 2015,                         Thanks to recent technological advances, we
                                                                                                                                                                                                      can now explore, in unprecedented detail,
        science-critical-thinkers                             https://www.kennedy-center.org/whats-on/festivals-series/sound-    Dr. Howlett managed the development                                  the biological and environmental factors
                                                                                                                                 of evidence-based national educational
        Students have the opportunity to expand their critical thinking skills   health/music-and-the-mind/                      trainings, materials, resources, and campaigns                       that influence youth development. However,
        through this series of lessons.                                                                                          for researchers, healthcare professionals,                           our research would not be possible without
                                                              National Endowment for the Arts Research Labs                      children, adolescents, and families to promote                       the dedication of the families, researchers,
        Stressed Out?                                         Across the country, NEA Research Labs are studying the benefits of   the prevention of substance use disorders   NEXT ISSUE:            and staff that graciously donate their time
                                                                                                                                                                                                      and energy to advance our understanding of
                                                                                                                                                                          ChildArt (Jan-Mar 2021)
        https://teens.drugabuse.gov/teachers/lessonplans/stressed-out   the arts for cognition, learning, or social and emotional well-being in   and the implementation of evidence-based   Global Creative Leaders  neuroscience and development.
                                                                                                                                 practices in the treatment of these illnesses
                                                              children and adolescents. Ongoing research projects include:
        Developed in partnership with Scholastic, students learn about how
        the body’s stress response system works and the health consequences   •  University of California, San Diego, in partnership with the
        of ongoing stress.                                        San Diego Children’s Choir: Early Academic Readiness and       •  George Mason University Arts Research Center, in collaboration   Other
                                                                  Learning Intervention (EARLI) studies will test the influence of   with Virginia Repertory Theatre and other partners: Study
        Cool Science Careers                                      various school-day musical interventions on early childhood      investigating the role of arts engagement, across all art forms, on   Arts Education Partnership
                                                                  development.                                                     children’s social and emotional development in educational, out-
        https://teens.drugabuse.gov/teachers/lessonplans/cool-science-    https://chd.ucsd.edu/research/NEA/index.html             of-school, and other settings.                    https://www.aep-arts.org/
        careers                                                                                                                                                                      A national network of more than 100 organizations dedicated to
                                                                •  Drexel University (in Philadelphia), in partnership with Tracy’s     https://masonarc.gmu.edu/
        Students explore careers in science through a series of interactive   Kids, Medstar Georgetown Hospital, Children’s National Hospital,   •  Vanderbilt University Medical Center is partnering with the   advancing arts education supported by the National Endowment for
        exercises.                                                New York Presbyterian, and Methodist Hospital in San Antonio:    Nashville Symphony, Nashville Opera, and Borderless Arts   the Arts and the U.S. Department of Education and administered by
                                                                  Multi-site study of the role of art therapy in fostering psychosocial   Tennessee: Study to examine if and how music may impact   Education Commission of the States.
        Make a Mad, Mad, Mad Neuron                               well-being among pediatric, adolescent, and young adult cancer   social-emotional development and well-being across diverse
                                                                  patients, families, and healthcare providers.                    populations, including children with developmental disabilities   ArtsEdSearch
        https://teens.drugabuse.gov/teachers/lessonplans/make-mad-mad-
        mad-neuron                                                https://drexel.edu/cnhp/research/faculty/KaimalGirija/arcs_lab/   such as autism spectrum disorders and their families.   https://www.artsedsearch.org/
        An interactive game that gives teens the opportunity to explore how   •  University of Arkansas, in partnership with The Woodruff Arts     https://www.vumc.org/music-cognition-lab/social-emotional-   An clearinghouse of research on the outcomes of arts education.
                                                                                                                                   development-and-community-building-through-music
        the brain works by building their own monster neural circuit.  Center in Atlanta, Ga., and the Crystal Bridges Museum of
                                                                  American Art (in Bentonville, Ark.): Study to look at the potential        o  Lab has developed an at-home “toolkit” to support parent-   International Arts + Mind Lab
                                                                  non-cognitive and emotional benefits of arts-related field trips for        and-child music interactions: http://serenademusicclass.
                                                                  elementary, middle school, and high school students.                  org/home-toolkit/                            https://artsandmindlab.org
                                                                  https://nea-research-lab.uark.edu/                                                                                 Research-to-practice initiative from the Brain Science Institute
                                                                                                                                                                                     at Johns Hopkins University.]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[Resources  VOLUME 20, ISSUE 2, NUMBER 60                                                 OCTOBER – DECEMBER 2020




 NIDA  NIDA for Teens
 https://teens.drugabuse.gov/
 Mapping the Brain
 Designed for teens and those who influence them, parents, guardians,
 https://teens.drugabuse.gov/teachers/lessonplans/mapping-brain   teachers, and other educators, the science-based information and   A View Through the ABCD Lens
 Developed in partnership with Scholastic, students learn about several   resources inspire learning and encourage critical thinking so teens can
 common types of brain-imaging technology used by neuroscientists   make informed decisions about their health.
 and doctors.   PUBLISHER AND EDITOR         in healthcare settings. Dr. Howlett received   SPECIAL THANKS
 NEA      Ashfaq Ishaq, Ph.D.                a Ph.D. in public health from the University   Frederick Marks, AIA, LEED AP BD+C, Six Sigma
          Ashfaq is the founder and chair of the
                                             of California, San Diego and San Diego State
                                                                                Green Belt
 The Awesomely Evolved Human Brain
 The Arts in Early Childhood: Social and Emotional Benefits of   International Child Art Foundation (ICAF),   University, Master of Public Policy from   Fred is a Visiting Scholar and Research
 https://teens.drugabuse.gov/teachers/lessonplans/awesomely-  Arts Participation (a literature review by Melissa Menzer for the   established in 1997. He is an experienced   Pepperdine University, and Master of Business   Collaborator in the Regulatory Biology
 evolved-human-brain   entrepreneur, educator, manager, researcher,   Administration from the Johns Hopkins   Laboratory at the Salk Institute for Biological
 National Endowment for the Arts):   and civil-sector leader. He holds a Ph.D. in   University.   Studies and was the impetus behind ICAF’s
 Developed in partnership with Scholastic, students learn about the   economics from the George Washington   collaboration with the NIH. We are indebted
 brain’s ability to make predictions and solve ambiguities and how   https://www.arts.gov/sites/default/files/arts-in-early-childhood-  University, where he later served as adjunct   CONTRIBUTING EDITOR AND DESIGNER  to him for his guidance throughout the
 drugs might compromise these capabilities.  dec2015-rev.pdf  associate professor of economics. Ashfaq   Eric M. Wargo, Ph.D.   development of this special issue of ChildArt.
          is spearheading a children’s revolution that   Assistant Guest Editor  Elizabeth Hoffman, Ph.D.
                                             Eric has a Ph.D. in anthropology from Emory
 “Wiring” Your Brain   Arts Section of Early Childhood Quarterly issue (co-edited by   treats children as creators (not merely pupils   University and works as a science writer and   Elizabeth is a Scientific Program Manager for
 Melissa Menzer for the Arts Endowment):   or consumers), takes their imagination as
 https://teens.drugabuse.gov/teachers/lessonplans/wiring-your-brain   seedbed for invention and innovation, and   editor for NIDA’s Office of Science Policy and   the Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development
 https://www.sciencedirect.com/journal/early-childhood-research-  Communications at NIH.   (ABCD) Study in NIDA’s Division of Extramural
 Developed in partnership with Scholastic, students learn that the   quarterly/vol/45/suppl/C  respects their art as the most honest and   Research at NIH. Dr. Hoffman holds a Ph.D. in
 choices they make today can help to shape and “wire” how their brains   purest form of human creative expression. For   Oslo  cognitive neuropsychology from the George
 will operate as adults.   the past two decades, he has been fostering   Creative Director   Washington University. Her contributions to
 “New Evidence of the Benefits of Arts Education” (authored by   children’s creativity and empathy, since   Oslo of oslographics.com is a Graphic Artist   the content and providing an expert sounding
 Brian Kisida and Daniel H. Bowen for the Brookings Institution,   creativity and empathy are key attributes of   and Designer in the D.C. Metro area. Since
 Sowing the Seeds of Neuroscience – Neuroscience 101   graduating from Virginia Tech in 1986 with a   board served to improve each part of the issue.
 based on research supported with a National Endowment for   successful learners and leaders and are also
 https://teens.drugabuse.gov/teachers/lessonplans/sowing-seeds-  the Arts grant):  preconditions for sustainable prosperity and   B.A. in art, Oslo has been involved in graphic   The IQ Solutions Content and Creative Team
 neuroscience-neuroscience-101   peace.      arts in some form or another, always bringing   The IQ Solutions Team provided technical
 https://www.brookings.edu/blog/brown-center-  what others see in their head to life.   expertise, copy editing, and creative guidance.
 Part of the Sowing the Seeds of Neuroscience Series, students learn the   chalkboard/2019/02/12/new-evidence-of-the-benefits-of-arts-  GUEST EDITOR  Their contributions within a truncated period
 basic anatomy and physiology of the nervous system.   education/  Katia Delrahim Howlett, Ph.D., M.P.P., M.B.A.  of time were instrumental to the success of
          Katia is the Deputy Director of the Division of                       this issue–a true joy to work with.
          Extramural Research at the National Institute
 Transforming Science for Critical Thinkers   “Mind and Music Live with Renée Fleming” webinar series (with   on Drug Abuse (NIDA), National Institutes of   ABCD Study Families, Researchers, and Staff
 https://teens.drugabuse.gov/teachers/lessonplans/transforming-  archived presentations):   Health (NIH). Prior to joining NIDA in 2015,   Thanks to recent technological advances, we
                                                                                can now explore, in unprecedented detail,
 science-critical-thinkers   https://www.kennedy-center.org/whats-on/festivals-series/sound-  Dr. Howlett managed the development   the biological and environmental factors
          of evidence-based national educational
 Students have the opportunity to expand their critical thinking skills   health/music-and-the-mind/  trainings, materials, resources, and campaigns   that influence youth development. However,
 through this series of lessons.   for researchers, healthcare professionals,   our research would not be possible without
 National Endowment for the Arts Research Labs  children, adolescents, and families to promote   the dedication of the families, researchers,
 Stressed Out?   Across the country, NEA Research Labs are studying the benefits of   the prevention of substance use disorders   NEXT ISSUE:  and staff that graciously donate their time
                                                                                and energy to advance our understanding of
                                                   ChildArt (Jan-Mar 2021)
 https://teens.drugabuse.gov/teachers/lessonplans/stressed-out   the arts for cognition, learning, or social and emotional well-being in   and the implementation of evidence-based   Global Creative Leaders  neuroscience and development.
          practices in the treatment of these illnesses
 children and adolescents. Ongoing research projects include:
 Developed in partnership with Scholastic, students learn about how
 the body’s stress response system works and the health consequences   •  University of California, San Diego, in partnership with the
 of ongoing stress.   San Diego Children’s Choir: Early Academic Readiness and   •  George Mason University Arts Research Center, in collaboration   Other
 Learning Intervention (EARLI) studies will test the influence of   with Virginia Repertory Theatre and other partners: Study
 Cool Science Careers   various school-day musical interventions on early childhood   investigating the role of arts engagement, across all art forms, on   Arts Education Partnership
 development.   children’s social and emotional development in educational, out-
 https://teens.drugabuse.gov/teachers/lessonplans/cool-science-    https://chd.ucsd.edu/research/NEA/index.html  of-school, and other settings.   https://www.aep-arts.org/
 careers                                                      A national network of more than 100 organizations dedicated to
 •  Drexel University (in Philadelphia), in partnership with Tracy’s     https://masonarc.gmu.edu/
 Students explore careers in science through a series of interactive   Kids, Medstar Georgetown Hospital, Children’s National Hospital,   •  Vanderbilt University Medical Center is partnering with the   advancing arts education supported by the National Endowment for
 exercises.   New York Presbyterian, and Methodist Hospital in San Antonio:   Nashville Symphony, Nashville Opera, and Borderless Arts   the Arts and the U.S. Department of Education and administered by
 Multi-site study of the role of art therapy in fostering psychosocial   Tennessee: Study to examine if and how music may impact   Education Commission of the States.
 Make a Mad, Mad, Mad Neuron   well-being among pediatric, adolescent, and young adult cancer   social-emotional development and well-being across diverse
 patients, families, and healthcare providers.   populations, including children with developmental disabilities   ArtsEdSearch
 https://teens.drugabuse.gov/teachers/lessonplans/make-mad-mad-
 mad-neuron     https://drexel.edu/cnhp/research/faculty/KaimalGirija/arcs_lab/   such as autism spectrum disorders and their families.   https://www.artsedsearch.org/
 An interactive game that gives teens the opportunity to explore how   •  University of Arkansas, in partnership with The Woodruff Arts     https://www.vumc.org/music-cognition-lab/social-emotional-   An clearinghouse of research on the outcomes of arts education.
            development-and-community-building-through-music
 the brain works by building their own monster neural circuit.  Center in Atlanta, Ga., and the Crystal Bridges Museum of
 American Art (in Bentonville, Ark.): Study to look at the potential        o  Lab has developed an at-home “toolkit” to support parent-   International Arts + Mind Lab
 non-cognitive and emotional benefits of arts-related field trips for        and-child music interactions: http://serenademusicclass.
 elementary, middle school, and high school students.   org/home-toolkit/  https://artsandmindlab.org
   https://nea-research-lab.uark.edu/                         Research-to-practice initiative from the Brain Science Institute
                                                              at Johns Hopkins University.]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[Celebrate
                                                                  Creativity,



       Support the                                                Diversity,




                   Children!                                      and Unity

                                                                  right across from the

                                                                  U.S. Capitol in our

                                                                  nation’s capital!





















        Friday, July 30
                              th
                  to
         2021
      Sunday, August 1           st







    WorldChildrensFestival.org






                                                        Participate in the free 6th Arts Olympiad. ICAF.org
                                                        Support the 2021 celebration of “Creativity, Diversity, and Unity.”
                                                        WorldChildrensFestival.org
                                                        For more information and to subscribe to ChildArt magazine, visit
                                                        ICAF.org/ChildArt

                                                        Post comments or visit us at facebook.com/ICAF.org
                    Correspondence
                    Address:
                                           Incorporated in 1997 in the District of Columbia as a 501(c)(3) nonprofit, the International
                    ICAF                   Child Art Foundation serves American children as their national arts organization to foster
                    P. O. Box 58133        their creativity and develop mutual empathy between them and with their peers
                    Washington, DC 20037   worldwide through the universal language of art.]]></page></pages></Search>