<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="48"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[APRIL-JUNE  2018
















        Dimensions of



        ARCHITECTURE]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[APRIL-JUNE 2018  VOL. 18, ISSUE 2, NUMBER 54




           Guest editor’s corner


           Creativity is at its most Seussian period during
           childhood.  For some, this time of exploration,
           imagination and whimsy continues into the
           teenage years and later into adulthood.  Of          Published since 1997, ChildArt is a commercial-free arts learning,
           all the arts where one may use their ability to      self-discovery, and global education periodical expressly written
           transcend traditional ideas, rules, patterns,        for 10 to 14 year-olds, but useful as a teaching tool for  educators
           relationships and create meaningful new              and inspirational for creative individuals of all ages. Subscribe to
           ideas, forms, methods, interpretations -             ChildArt online at www.icaf.org.
           architecture is the most complex to execute.            When a child’s creativity is ignored, it could be lost forever.
           It requires an understanding of economics,           Tax-deductible donations support children’s creative and
           history, engineering science, construction,          empathic development. You can donate online at www.icaf.org
           human behavior, visual perception in addition        or make your check to ICAF and mail it to: ICAF, P. O. Box 58133,
           to drawing, color theory and composition.            Washington, DC 20037.
           This issue of ChildArt Magazine is devoted to           All rights reserved. Reproduction of the whole or any part of
           covering the multi-dimensional aspects of this       the contents without written permission is prohibited. ChildArt
           profession, from its training to its application.    (ISSN 1096-9020). Copyright 2018 International Child Art
           It is also intended to articulate and illustrate the   Foundation (ICAF), a 501(c)(3) nonprofit.
           power of building design to affect our senses,
           our memories and our well-being at any age.

           The authors who have written the articles you
           are about to read are a distinguished group
           of people whose accomplishments are briefly
           noted in the Credits section of this issue.  They
           are still kids at heart and it was their intention
           to pass on their experience so that you would
           learn to appreciate the importance of having
           a built environment that is compatible with          The American Institute of Architects (AIA) was founded in New
           nature, aesthetically beautiful, and functional.     York City in 1857 by a group of 13 architects to “promote the
           Architecture comes in all shapes and sizes, and      scientific and practical perfection of its members” and “elevate
           you will be exposed to projects of all scales        the standing of the profession.”  Headquartered in Washington,
           from a single room to an urban center.  You will     DC, AIA offers education, government advocacy, community
           also become aware of the value of saving and         development, and public outreach.  It has more than 90,000
           preserving our heritage, and the importance          licensed and associated professionals as members.
           of making good architecture available to
           everyone.                                            Included among AIA’s many programs is the K-12 Initiatives.
                                                                Based on the belief that architecture and design education
           It is a privilege for me to serve as guest           empowers children with the learning habits and critical thinking
           editor of this special edition of ChildArt in        skills needed to thrive over a lifetime, this program works to
           my capacity as a member of The American              develop strategic partnerships, share instructional resources, and
           Institute of Architects.  Special thanks needs       engage architects and educators to help young students gain an
           to go to the International Child Art Foundation      early appreciation of architecture.
           (ICAF) who concluded that there would be
           valuable lessons for its magazine readers if the
           subject of architecture was presented.







           Frederick Marks
           Founding Member & President-elect
           Academy of Neuroscience for Architecture
           ANFA                                               Cover: Mykolas Vasiliunas, Age 9  (detail)]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[APRIL-JUNE 2018  DIMENSIONS OF ARCHITECTURE  1




          Dimensions of







          ARCHITECTURE
















          02                03                04                08               10                14
          Intro             Mankind Invents   Architectural     Why Buildings    Drawing as        Creativity
          Tom Vonier        Architecture      Education         Remain Standing   Thought          + Place
                            Ewa Struzynska    Tom Fisher        Henry Petroski   Steven Holl       Donald Rattner














          16                18                22                26               28                30


          Preserve          Unifying a        Supporting        My Life as an    The Rooms of a    Your Ideal Town
          Conserve          Museum            Environmental     Architect        House             James Logan Abell
          Restore           Ian Bader         Sustainability    Billy Ming Sing Lee  Angela Brooks
          Ashley Wilson                       Mary Ann Lazarus













          34                36                38                40               43                44

          Themed            Citizen Architect   Architecture    Sacred Spaces    Learning          Credits
          Architecture      Emily McGlohn     Without           Fred Marks       Resources
          Michael Lingerfelt                  Architects
                                              Michael Crosbie]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[2  CHILDART  ICAF.org




           Helping youths learn about



           ARCHITECTURE

















           INTRO:

           An educated citizenry is our profession’s best friend . . .






           THOMAS VONIER







              he International Union of Architects   and villages in France differ from those in   We want everybody to love it as much as
           T (UIA) is the only global organization   Mexico or the United States, just as a town   we do!
           representing the world’s architects, who   in Idaho differs from one in Connecticut.    Appreciation for architecture very
           now number some 3.2 million in all.   These differences give places their special   probably begins early in life.  Our
           When the UIA’s founders established the   qualities and unique characters.  environments affect us as infants, and
           organization in 1948, they outlined three   Would Paris still be Paris without its   that which surrounds us probably shapes
           basic missions: to unify professionals   unmistakable grands boulevards and the   our very ability to perceive—to see, to
           around the world, to improve international   Eiffel Tower? Would New York City still   hear, to sense, and to interpret.  We know
           policies affecting human settlements,   be the Big Apple without its remarkable   that infants and young children receive
           and to elevate the global stature of   skyscrapers? Would Istanbul be a great   great stimulation from colors, sounds,
           architecture.                       and memorable place without its gracious   shapes, textures, spatial volumes, lights
              At the time of the UIA’s founding,   minarets and amazing souks?  Would   and movements—from the full range of
           the world was recovering from the   Washington DC be as great a national   sensations and stimuli that we experience
           devastation of World War II, particularly   capital without its monuments and   as adults, and from the very things that
           in Europe.  The founders saw promise in   edifices? Would Bilbao be as widely   constitute architecture.
           the ideals of international cooperation,   known without its striking museum?   The UIA recognizes excellence
           and sought wide support for building new   Buildings and their relationship to an   in efforts to teach children about
           communities and better, more modern   urban environment make places what they   architecture through the international
           urban environments.                 are.  Many architects believe that people   Golden Cube Award, and by holding
              People everywhere take pride in their   who may never become architects should   conferences among people from all
           buildings and communities, especially   learn about buildings and cities; that the   over the world who work on childhood
           when they are distinguishing        public should want to preserve great   education.  Japan, the United States,
           or historic.  Architecture—like music, food,   monuments and well-designed buildings;   Germany, France and many other
           language, clothing and customs—can   and that all people should support better   countries have won awards.  We are
           be a distinctive element of national and   urban design.  There is a simple reason   working to ensure that many more people
           ethnic culture. Architecture can be part   why architects support programs that   benefit from exposure to architecture
           of national and local identity.  Buildings   teach young people about architecture:   at a young age.]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[APRIL-JUNE 2018  DIMENSIONS OF ARCHITECTURE  3




          Mankind “invents” architecture






          EWA STRUZYNSKA



              othing is more hostile and      hurricanes and fires to remind us of how   populations in most cities will double.
          N uncomfortable to human beings,    the loss of any shelter –natural or built -   The architect’s work is becoming
          or more lacking of protection, than the   can leave us unprepared and open   much more complicated. He has to deal
          infinite emptiness of space.  Think of   to harm.                      not only with construction and beauty but
          yourself standing in an open field unable   Between the vastness of space and the   with social, political, economic, religious
          to see any signs of human settlement in   vulnerable human body is architecture,   and ecological factors.
          all directions.                     a complex set of systems that must    Temperament, experience, culture,
             Based on how we have been able to   adapt to the site provided by the natural   the ability to listen, and to transcend
          exist over thousands of years, our gaze   environment and the multiple needs of a   technique—these characteristics are
          instinctively identifies natural places   fragile creature (like yourself).  what determines talent for producing the
          of shelter as a means for physical and   Architecture is made by architects.  “good” architecture that is meaningful
          psychological survival.  We remain naked   Architects master several disciplines,   and purposeful for individuals and
          and susceptible, otherwise.  We need   particularly two: first, construction,   for society.
          shelter against rain, snow, hail, wind,   in the broadest sense, encompassing   We can say that buildings give
          cold, sandstorms, heat, wild animals   techniques and data; and second, the   humans security and protection, but it
          and pure danger—some of it from other   plastic art that includes the creation of   is architecture that has the capability to
          humans.  Today’s modern comfort has   forms and their combination to create   provide us with a healthy, improved and
          made us lose sight of how vulnerable,   harmonious relations.          appropriate quality of life.
          homeless, and unprotected we actually   Today, most humans live in cities.
          are. It often takes natural disasters like   Tomorrow, that means in 2050, the



                                                                                      UIA WP Architecture and Children Program]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[4  CHILDART  ICAF.org




           Architectural



          EDUCATION










           THOMAS FISHER



               ave you ever wanted to walk around
          H during class, talk with whomever you
           want there, and make drawings, models,
           and computer images as your academic
           work? And have you always enjoyed
           doing puzzles, imagining the future,
           and working with others on projects?
           If so, then you might like architecture
           school. You may think that you don’t
           draw well enough, can’t make models                    There are
           carefully enough, or won’t learn the math              123
           fast enough to succeed in architecture                 accredited schools of architecture in
           school, but those skills, while helpful, are           the USA alone, as documented by the
           not essential to becoming an architect.                Association of Collegiate Schools of
           The one ability that you do need is what               Architecture (ACSA).
           the Harvard educator Howard Gardner
           calls “visual-spatial intelligence,” the               Visit one at a time when a public lecture
           ability to see two- and three-dimensional              is being conducted.
           relationships and patterns.
             You probably already know whether
           or not you have this intelligence. If
           reading maps, remembering images,
           or imagining spaces comes easy to you,
           then you probably have it, even if no one
           ever told you so. Other than in art class,
           the standard curriculum in most schools
           pays little attention to visual-spatial
           ability, but in architecture school this
           form of intelligence matters most. With
           it, students learn to see relationships and
           connections among things that others
           can’t visualize and to envision what
           doesn’t yet exist in ways that others can’t
           imagine. Architecture school teaches you
           how to become a practical futurist and a
           spatial visionary.
             Architecture school also teaches
           you how to play again. Because of the
           ability of the human brain to combine
           information, ideas, and images in new
           ways, everyone has the capacity to be
           creative, something we all did well as kids]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[APRIL-JUNE 2018 DIMENSIONS OF ARCHITECTURE  5





          on the playground. But once we enter   design studio, the best answer is often the   vision and then work out the details;
          elementary school, teachers start to grade   most creative one.        in all cases, though, they proceed in
                                                Architecture students work hard at this
          us according to our giving the correct   play; it can take a lot of time to find the   an iterative way, exploring a new idea,
 EDUCATION  over time, makes most of us think we   best solutions to the open-ended prob-  idea in a new way, which in turn leads to
                                                                                 which often leads to seeing an earlier
          rather than the creative answer, which
                                              lems and complex situations that we face
          lack creativity. It isn’t true! In architecture
                                                                                 yet another idea. Through that creative
                                              when designing buildings. Architecture
          school, with its studio-based education,
                                                                                 process, students learn how to imagine
          students regain their confidence in their
          own creativity, learning not only how to   students also have a lot of freedom in how   possibilities and make them real and how
                                                                                 to use visual-spatial intelligence to meet
                                              and when they work on their projects.
          design buildings and communities, but   Some students start with the pieces of a   people’s shelter needs.Architectural
          also how to make new connections and   project and work toward a solution, while   education demands a lot of work, but few
          see new relationships among things. In   others begin with a big idea or overall   fields are as much fun.
                                                                                Environmental Design Studio, University of Manitoba]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[6  CHILDART  ICAF.org


























































































         Louis Kahn, 1951, Temple of Apollo, No. 4]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[DIMENSIONS OF ARCHITECTURE  7







                                                                                            "You say to a
                                                                                            brick,

                                                                                            'What do you

                                                                                            want, brick?'

                                                                                            And brick says
                                                                                            to you,

                                                                                            'I like an
                                                                                            arch.'

                                                                                            And you say

                                                                                            to a brick,

                                                                                            'Look, I want
                                                                                            one, too, but
                                                                                            arches are

                                                                                            expensive and
                                                                                            I can use a —

                                                                                            lintel.'

                                                                                            And then you
                                                                                            say:

                                                                                            'What do you
                                                                                            think of that,

                                                                                            brick?'

                                                                                            Brick says:

                                                                                            'I like an
                                                                                            arch."





                                                                                            Louis Kahn

                                                                                            Architect, FAIA
                                                                                            AIA Gold Medal, 1971

                                                                                            1901-1974]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[8  CHILDART  ICAF.org



           Why Buildings Remain



           S TANDING










           HENRY PETROSKI














              uildings stand up because engineers once tried to
          B knock them down. As strange as this may sound, the
           surest way to guarantee that any structure—building,
           bridge, tower, dam—does not collapse is to try to
           make it do so, but not necessarily in real life. It would
           be silly and expensive to build an actual skyscraper,
           say, without having a good idea that it would stand
           up to whatever might be thrown at it.
             All manmade structures come under attack
           by forces of nature. These forces, which include
           gravity, earthquakes, hurricanes, and tsunamis,
           are not things that engineers can make up or
           easily duplicate, but they can make models of
           them—virtual models that do not even require
           real wind or water.
             Engineers know whether a building will
           stand up because they attack models of it
           on paper, on the computer screen, or even
           in a laboratory before construction ever
           begins. The laboratory models are small
           versions of the real thing, but they are not
           just toys.
             Every child is familiar with models.
           From an early age, boys and girls
           playing with real and virtual building
           blocks and other materials construct
           real and imaginary houses, castles,
           towers. We call these things toys, but
           they teach us a great deal about how
           to imagine, create, and assemble
           parts into a whole.]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[APRIL-JUNE 2018  DIMENSIONS OF ARCHITECTURE  9

















          Our parents and grandparents may
          remember doing this by connecting with
          small nuts and bolts small steel parts that   tumbling down                  forces that attack them, perhaps
          came in Erector or Meccano construction   when someone walks               by interlocking wooden blocks more
          sets. Younger generations did the same   by, making the floor shake      carefully or by pressing Legos together
          with wooden parts that came in sets   like in an earthquake.            more tightly.
          called Lincoln Logs and Tinker Toys.   Sometimes, engineers build         Like children playing with toys, adult
          Today, children use plastic blocks   models on large mechanical tables called   engineers learn from failures what does
          known as Legos.                     shake tables so they can deliberately   not work. And by knowing what has
             As anyone who has played with these   move them to imitate an earthquake.   not worked in the past they know better
          toys knows, there are limits to how large   Other times, they put their models in   how to succeed in the future. This is the
          we can make things. Sometimes we run   wind tunnels, to study the effects o   way buildings have been improved and
          out of parts; sometimes we use the parts    heavy winds on a bridge, tower, or   perfected since the days of the Pyramids.
          too boldly and our construction collapses   neighboring buildings.     In ancient times this was done largely by
          before we can finish it.              When collapses occur, children and   trial and error.
             While real engineers are not playing   engineers alike learn from the failure what   Today, buildings stand up because
          when they design a structure, their   to watch out for the next time they build.   modern engineers try to knock down
          models can collapse by being too heavy,   They learn to use larger and stronger   models of them. The process is known as
          or too unbalanced, or just too vulnerable.   beams and columns. They also learn how   design, and it represents a careful thinking
          A tall stack of wooden blocks can come   to reinforce their structures against the   ahead about what can go  wrong.








































                                                                                                 Illustrations: Forrest Wilson]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[10  CHILDART  ICAF.org



           Drawing as



           THOUGHT










           STEVEN HOLL



                y 2 year old daughter comes to   an idea—without the thoughts of   to define a concept. Many of these
           M me at dawn saying, “Drawing?     plans or sections.                  watercolors lead to dead-ends; ideas that
           Drawing?” She sees me making my       The immediacy of a child’s       don’t show promise—but I know this well
           morning watercolor and wants to get up   drawing brings us back to the begin-   and just keep drawing each day to search
           on a chair with me and make drawings   ning of thinking. The hand, the eye, the   for the crucial idea which will drive design.
           together. We draw sailboats, birds,   brain are all deeply connected when the   The little 5” x 7” format is the right size
           airplanes, things she knows the words   child makes marks on paper—but the   of the human hand; also it fits on a folding
           for. Her drawing of the moon, however,   surprise—the imaginative creation of a   airplane tray and an image snaps quickly
           is not what we would recognize; rather,   “moon-rabbit”—that is a product of the   on an iPhone.
           it is a long arabesque. She claims, “it’s   mind. This deep intuitive invention is the   The watercolor concept sketch made
           the moon; it’s a moon-rabbit.” The   same for me as an old architect glancing   in a Rhinebeck lake hut can be immediately
           interaction of the hand and brain engages   back at 40 years of practice. 250 designs   photographed and sent simultaneously
           the human imagination in an immediate   and 70 realized constructions, each one   to New York, Beijing and Moscow. In
           neurologically connected way that cannot   of my architectural projects began as a   minutes, three teams of architects can
           be replicated in a digital process.   drawing—usually a watercolor in a 5” x 7”   have the central concept for a 200,000
             I believe drawing, especially    watercolor tablet (more than 30,000   square meters project. There is a digital
           for architects, is a form of thought.   exist in my archive).          supercharged aspect that follows—
           Today supercharged digital rendering   The drawings are thoughts in    however, there is no compromise on
           techniques can depict a building in its   themselves; bringing together light,   allowing the time needed to arrive at a
           proposed site in every detail—without   space, color, and a few words searching   concept via Drawing as Thought.































                                                                                     Hangzhou Music Museum | Hangzhou, China]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[The drawings are thoughts in
                  themselves; bringing together
                        light, space, color,
                         and a few words
                           searching to
                        define a concept.

                           Steven Holl












                                                                                                   Kiasma Museum |  Helsinki, Finland]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[12  CHILDART  ICAF.org







































                                                                                   Linked Hybrid | Beijing, China]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[DIMENSIONS OF ARCHITECTURE  13




































































                                                                                          Hunters Point Library, Queens | New York













                           Chapel of St. Ignatius | Seattle, Washington
                                                                                        Get yourself a sketchbook
                                                                                           and discover your
                                                                                             inner talent.]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[14  CHILDART  ICAF.org


           CREATIVITY







           +



           PLACE                                                                              DONALD RATTNER












               o you know where you spend      things that architects and interior   levels. I suspect you’re wondering what
           D around 90% of your time every day?   designers do to enlarge our sense of   stress has to do with creativity. The
           I do—it’s indoors! Okay, if you’re a kid   space are straightforward: we design   answer is, a lot. Stress changes how you
           who plays outside a lot, or you live in a   rooms with tall ceilings, ten feet or   think. Sometimes for the better, like when
           tropical or desert climate, maybe it’s bit   higher; we open up the walls with doors   you find yourself suddenly in danger. In
           less. Either way, that’s a lot of time in one   and windows; we orient buildings toward   those situations, stress prompts you to
           particular type of setting.         light and views, and we face furniture into   be alert, clear-minded, and focused on
              Given the statistic, how important   a room rather than onto a wall whenever   finding the quickest path to escaping
           would you guess the quality and     possible. Through experimentation,   your predicament.
           character of interior environments are   scientists have discovered that each of   Creative thinking, however, is quite
           to how you think, feel, and act? That’s   these strategies can improve our ability   the opposite. Coming up with fresh
           right—very! And that’s not merely a   to solve creative problems, whether it’s   insights flourishes when your mind
           hunch. Researchers, architects, interior   composing a painting or inventing a   is allowed to wander, and to explore
           designers, and specialists from many   new app.                        multiple answers to a problem, not just
           different fields have been studying the   Less expected techniques have also   the first solution that springs to mind. The
           impact that our surroundings have on   popped up. One is to decorate the walls   lower your stress levels, then, the abler
           people for several decades now, using   of a room in a cool color, such as blue,   you are to function creatively.
           the same rigorous methods of testing   because cool colors make things appear   There are several proven techniques
           and observation to collect their data and   to move away from the viewer (check out   for shaping your environment to reduce
           draw their conclusions that scientists use   the Mona Lisa to see the effect in action).   stress. Probably the best known is to
           in other disciplines.               Another is to hang artwork showing   populate it with the elements of nature,
              Some of what they’ve discovered   far-away places, like travel posters   like plants, animal life, and natural
           might surprise you. For example, did   advertising foreign countries. According   materials. (Scientists believe we’ve been
           you know that including certain features   to the research, just thinking about the   hardwired since caveman days to relax
           in the space where you pursue your   distance between where you are and   when we see hints of a food source at
           creative interests could make you better   the picture on the poster is enough to   hand.) Another is to choose furniture
           at them? If you’re someone who enjoys   prompt a feeling of spaciousness.  that’s round or curved in shape and
           making, teaching, or learning about art,   So why do these techniques improve   detail. Why? Because round things won’t
           that has to be exciting and welcome   creativity? Some scientists believe the   hurt us, while straight edges might (think
           news.                               reason is that your “mental space”—that   spoon versus knife.) Here’s a third: keep
              So what are these features? Scientists   is, the space in your imagination where   the lights down low. We get stressed out
           have uncovered a great many of them,   you cook up new thoughts—expands   when we feel like we’re under a spotlight.
           but I believe they can be organized   and contracts in harmony with your   Think about your creative space the
           into a few main groups. One category   impression of physical space. The more   next time you’re in it. Does it make you
           consists of qualities that make us feel   open you feel the space around you is,   feel happy and relaxed? Does it feel
           that the space around us is expanding, a   the more open you’ll be to exploring new   sufficiently open? If not, consider some
           second of qualities that make us feel less   ways of doing things.     changes along the lines of what I’ve
           stressed.                             Now let’s consider the second    suggested here. After all, place matters—
              Let’s take the first group first. Some   category I mentioned: lowering stress   to you and your creativity.]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[APRIL-JUNE 2018  DIMENSIONS OF ARCHITECTURE  15




                                              Pick a spot.      Play music. It can   Show your     Write on the walls.
                                              Designate a       get your creative   stuff. To yourself   Draw big, think
                              MORE            creative space    juices flowing.  and others        big. Whiteboard
                              CREATIVE        and stick with it.                 for reflection    or chalkboard
                                              Your brain will   Let in the light.   and feedback.   paint turn walls
                              SPACE TIPS      get trained to    Mind and body    Consider pinup    into idea spaces.
                                              shift into creative   thrive on daily   boards, easels, or
                                              mode whenever     doses of         digital projection
                                              you’re in it.     natural light.   methods.]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[16  CHILDART  ICAF.org



           Preserve Conserve Restore







           ASHLEY WILSON










               re there places you visit that bring   internment camps, often should be saved   unloved and no longer used buildings
           A back a flood of memories?  Perhaps   so we don’t forget when others acted   out there could be renovated into new
           it’s your first home, a playground, a park,   indecently.  Good and bad places can   places with new functions. Architecture is
           a school, or a sports arena.  Now imagine   inspire us to achieve more.  a fluid process- once a building exists, it
           yourself returning to visit that arena, park   Just by habit, most of us recycle   can continue to change forever to match
           or home in twenty years.  How would you   bottles, turn off the water when we are   new needs.  Also, dwindling natural land
           feel if these places were gone?     brushing our teeth and use energy saving   should be protected and preserved rather
              Presumably bad, because these    LED bulbs, but we don’t apply that same   than developed.  Renovating existing
           places are the backdrop to your life.  If   approach to the big stuff.  Demolishing   buildings to new and better uses helps
           they remain standing, every time you   buildings is incredibly wasteful. Erecting   to solve many of these problems.  It’s
           see them they will spark memories   buildings that aren’t meant to last and   better for the land, better for protection
           and transport you back in time.  Why?   can’t be recycled is wasteful too.  The   against natural disaster, and better for the
           Because memory is triggered by place.    building sector is one of the biggest   economy. Reusing buildings is creative,
           It’s like the way memory is triggered by   polluters because it takes a lot of energy   and it’s better for our psyches because we
           music; when you hear a song from the   to create concrete, run construction   are saving places that hold memories.
           past, it immediately reminds you of a   vehicles, and produce building    It’s easy to understand the importance
           previous time.  Since architecture evokes   components.  Major construction   of saving iconic historic and natural places
           memories, saving historic places is   contributes to air pollution, drinking   such as the Empire State Building or the
           more than recycling at a big scale, it’s an   water pollution, landfill waste, energy   Grand Canyon.  The beauty, symbolism,
           investment in connecting people to the   use and climate change, so we need to   and sense of well-being they evoke create
           world around them.                  reduce material consumption by reusing   a strong desire to protect them for future
              We want to save the places that make   buildings.  There are billions of unused   generations.  While the typical building
           us feel calm, where we feel at home, or   places that are waiting to be renewed.  doesn’t solicit this type of response, the
           where good things happened.  Even the   That’s good news, because the world   benefits of protecting regular places
           places where bad things happen, such   has a growing population and needs   weaves our heritage into a new modern
           as Nazi concentration camps or Japanese   new homes, schools and places.  All the   tapestry that belongs to all of us.]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[APRIL-JUNE 2018  DIMENSIONS OF ARCHITECTURE  17













































































                                                          Visit the NTHP Web site to see whether there
                                                          is a property in your state that is designated as
                                                          a national treasure.  Investigate whether there
                                                          is a State Historic Preservation Office near you.
                                                          Take a tour and learn how a building provides a
                                                          community with a strong sense of identity!]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[18  CHILDART  I ICAF.org CAF.ORG




           Unifying a


           MUSEUM










           IAN BADER








            would like to tell you about a very   built with thin supporting members. The
          I interesting building project. My archi-  pyramid shape is very strong structurally.
           tecture firm and the man who started   We made it of glass so that it wouldn’t
           it, the famous architect I.M. Pei, were   block views and would invite people to
           asked to design a new entrance and   enter. It would also act as a skylight to the
           central hall for the Louvre Museum in   hall below.
           Paris in 1983. The Louvre is the largest   There was an uproar and outcry when
           museum in the world and is the central   the pyramid design was first unveiled. Peo-
           landmark of all of France. Originally it   ple thought that it would be very ugly, that
           was built, starting in the 16th century,   it was too modern for the historic Louvre
           as a palace for                                    Palace, and that it was
           the kings of                                        impolite to place such
           France. You                                         a distinct object right
           can imagine                                         in the middle of the
           that on such                                        museum’s courtyard.
           a prominent                                           First we present-
           and important                                       ed the idea of the
           site, making                                        pyramid with a scale
           a design that                                       model. Then, because
           would work                                          of the concern that it
           well and satisfy                                    would ruin the Louvre
           everyone was a                                      Museum and be an
           great challenge.                                  embarrassment on the
              The site for the new entrance and   most important site, right in the middle of
           central hall was the historic courtyard of   Paris, we made a full-size mock-up in the
           the museum. Even though this court-  exact place where the pyramid was to be
           yard was such an important place, right   built. This mock-up was temporary, made
           in the middle of the Palace of the Louvre   of rubber ropes, pulled up by a crane.
           and on the central axis of Paris, it had   Once the mock-up was viewed, the mayor
           been neglected, containing a few trees   of Paris and other officials calmed down
           and parking for cars. Our proposal was   and the project went ahead.
           to place a glass Pyramid in the middle of   Today the pyramid is considered to be
           this courtyard.                     very successful. The number of visitors
              The main reason we thought that the   to the museum has more than doubled,
           pyramid was the best shape for the new   making it the most-visited art gallery in
           building was that it was the simplest   the world, with more that 8 million people
           and most efficient form imaginable.   coming every year. It has become a
           Simple, because it has only four surfac-  cultural icon of which the French
           es and efficient, because it could be   people are very proud.

           Sketches /Doodles (above) of Louvre Project; Isometric Drawing (right) of the Louvre Museum, Paris, France]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[APRIL-JUNE 2018  DIMENSIONS OF ARCHITECTURE  19





                                                The fine arts, of which the Louvre
                                              Museum has a considerable collection
                                              that includes paintings by Gericault,
                                              Delacroix, Vermeer, Rembrandt and
                                              Leonardo da Vinci in addition to sculp-
                                              ture by Rodin, is uplifting for people
                                              to view. Clear and transparent, the
                                              Pyramid, with its memorable shape          Visit a museum and ask yourself
                                              and graceful relationship to the historic   how easy it was to find your
                                              Palace of the Louvre, functions as an      way to what you wanted to see.
                                              effective entrance and central gath-       If you get lost or overlook a
                                              ering point for this great museum.  It     collection, think about how you
                                              has become a symbol of the best that       would reorganize the hallways
                                              French culture has to offer.               and the galleries.]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[20  CHILDART  ICAF.org

































                     Ray & Charles Eames                                 Gerrit Reitveld







































                                                                            Robert Venturi




           Did you know that architects design chairs?]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[APRIL-JUNE 2018  DIMENSIONS OF ARCHITECTURE  21

































                      Alvar Aalto                                                 Frank Gehry







































 Robert Venturi  Frank Lloyd Wright                             A chair is a very difficult object.

                                                                A skyscraper is almost easier.


                                                                Ludwig Mies van der Rohe]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[22  CHILDART  ICAF.org



           Supporting Environmental




           SUSTAINABILITY










           MARY ANN LAZARUS









               re you familiar with the term   who design buildings have a great deal of
           A Sustainable Design?  Maybe you    responsibility and impact over the use of
           have heard of it in a year when you   valuable, natural resources and people’s
           attended Earth Day on April 22.     comfort and well-being. That is why the
              Buildings – that is the home you live   profession of architecture is committed to
           in, the school you go to, the office where   making sustainable design a top priority –
           your parents work – are composed of   finding design solutions that limits the use
           A LOT of stuff.  There are the materials   of non-renewable resources, minimizes
           necessary for constructing exterior walls   waste, and creates healthy, productive
           and a roof, and the materials used for   environments for people. Did you know
           interior finishes and making furniture.    that it is even possible for a building to be
           There is equipment for operating    regenerative; to actually give back more
           buildings so that indoor air temperatures   resources than it uses?
           are comfortable and water is available to
           keep you clean and hydrated. Buildings
           also require constant maintenance and
           upgrading.   And all of these functions   This image shows all of the fresh water on the
           demand a lot of energy!            whole earth. The bigger marble is all of the
              But there’s only so much stuff to go   liquid fresh water anywhere while the much
           around on our one planet. If buildings use   smaller one is all of the fresh water in the
                                              ground, lakes, rivers, or swamps. The very tiny
           materials that can’t quickly grow back,   blue dot under that is all of the fresh water just
           like wood from old forests or water from   in the rivers and lakes. That’s all the fresh water
           underground lakes, then those resources   on the planet we have to use, so we need to be
                                              very careful to not waste any.
           may run out. When energy generation is
           dependent on fossil fuels, the air may get
           polluted and this will contribute to global
           warming of both the atmosphere and of
           the oceans.
              With the right intentions, buildings
           also can be wonderful, healthy
           places to live, work and play in, while
           being material and energy efficient.
           But sometimes the indoors can be
           uncomfortable – like too hot or cold,
           smelly, or not without enough light or
           even with too much light - so people have
           a harder time staying healthy or getting
           work done.  This means that architects]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[APRIL-JUNE 2018  DIMENSIONS OF ARCHITECTURE  23

































                U.S. ENERGY CONSUMPTION BY SECTOR                  U.S. ELECTRICITY CONSUMPTION BY SECTOR

                                    Building operations                                            Building operations
                                         41.7%                                                          74.9%
                                                                                                      (28.6 QBtu)
          Industry                                                    Industry
           24.4%                                                      24.9%
                                                                      (9.5 QBtu)


                                                Building
                                             Construction and
                                               Materials             Transportation
                                                 5.9%                   <1%
                           Transportation                              (.1 QBtu)
                              28.1%

                                             Data Source: U.S. Energy Information Administration, 2012






                                                   U.S. BUILDING IMPACTS









                       12%               39%                65%             71%
                       WATER USE         CO 2               WASTE           ELECTRICITY
                                         EMISSIONS          OUTPUT          CONSUMPTION










                                                 Data Source: U. S. Green Building Council]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[24  CHILDART  ICAF.ORG




















































           CASE STUDY:   Discovery Elementary School

           Arlington Public Schools, Arlington VA
           Architect: VMDO from Charlottesville, VA

           One great example of how sustainable   Virginia.  Completed in 2016, the facility   that converts sunlight to energy and
           design can have a very positive impact   is two stories and has approximately   reduces the need for electricity.  All
           on a building’s design is to look at the   97,500 square feet of space.  Its roof   of the classrooms have big, operable
           Discovery Elementary School in Arlington,   is covered with solar collection panels   windows with views to nature that allow
                                                                                  plenty of natural light and fresh air to
                                                                                  enter from the outside to keep students
                                                                                  and teachers alert and motivated for
                                                                                  active learning.  Together with their
                                                                                  other decisions made by the architect,
                                                                                  the school accomplishes something
                                                                                  special – it’s a net-zero building.  This
                                                                                  means the school uses no more energy
                                                                                  in one year than it can produce on the
                                                                                  site where it is located.  The building
                                                                                  is also constructed with recycled
                                                                                  materials; materials that are healthy and
                                                                                  were found nearby in order to limit the
                                                                                  amount of fuel used to get
                                                                                  them there.]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[APRIL-JUNE 2018  DIMENSIONS OF ARCHITECTURE  25















                                      SKETCH EXERCISE :

                                      How do we design spaces so that they can be healthy and
                                      not use more resources than we have to?

                                       Architects look for design ideas from a lot of different
                                      sources and then turn those into building solutions.

                                      One of the best places to look for sustainable design ideas
                                      is how nature works. Because, after all, nature must work
                                      within the limits set by its surroundings.



                                      HERE’S A SUSTAINABLE DESIGN CHALLENGE FOR YOU TO DO:


                                       1      Pick from one of the following types of homes:
                                                  •   A house in the country
                                                  •   An apartment building in the city
                                                  •   A home in the suburbs


                                              Pick a location for your home – what city, town or village? This could be anywhere
                                       2      in the world!


                                       3      Describe how many people live in the home:
                                              Number of adults:
                                              Number and ages of children:
                                              Other family members like pets:



                                       4      Quickly list 10 things that the home must allow everyone to do like (sleep, eat,
                                              bathe, play, other ideas).


                                             Now sketch some ideas for your house. Try designing a home that meets any of the
                                       5     following requirements. Pick one or more:

                                               •  How could your home open up during the day to let in the sun and
                                                 close down again at night to keep in the heat?  What would the walls look like? How
                                                 would the rooms be laid out?
                                               •  How could your home use materials that are only available nearby? What would
                                                 those materials be? What shape would it take using the materials that you’ve picked?
                                                 Try to think about using as few materials as possible. How might the rooms be laid
                                                 out? Draw what the outside would look like.

                                               •  How could your home only use energy that’s generated from local renewable
                                                 resources, like the sun or wind?  What shape and direction would your house be?
                                                 Could parts change during the day to get the most sun or wind? Draw what the
                                                 house might look like to capture the most nearby energy sources.]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[26  CHILDART  ICAF.org




           My Life as an




           ARCHITECT










           BILLY MING SING LEE















            was born in 1932 and brought up in a   what I saw in my travels from the dorm   of I. M. Pei and Edward Larrabee Barnes
          I privileged Shanghai family – a spacious   to the classroom.  This sharpened my   both located in New York City.  Each of
           Spanish Mansion, with a Beaux Art   awareness of all the things around me   their design work was super-elegant
           Garden.  A block away was the private   from neo-classical buildings to birds and   and refined. The most valuable lessons
           residence of Mr. Tsuyee Pei, father of   squirrels.  Yale’s Architecture Program   I learned from these two masters was
           famous architect I.M. Pei.                                             that Words and Manners are extremely
              Fragile and with hearing impairment,                                important in promoting ideas, and that
           I was a slow-learner, very naïve, but                                  one must have a big vision for it is the
           good at drawing and mathematics. My                                    design implementation that defines
           favorite elder cousin suggested that I                                 one’s reputation.
           may one day become an architect. I took                                   I went on to form my own NYC office
           everything she said to heart, although                                 Copelin & Lee (later called Copelin, Lee
           during those primary years, I had no                                   & Chen ) earning a “Promising Young
           idea what architecture meant. I did hear,                              Architects” recognition at the same
           however, that one Uncle was famous                                     time that architects Charles Gwathmey
           for his Sun Yat San Memorial Design in                                 and Richard Meier got theirs (both of
           Nanking, and another Uncle designed an                                 whom became world renown).  When
           apartment building where the doors to                                  our partnership dissolved in 1974, my
           the bathrooms swung into the                                           wife and I moved to California.  I began
           occupiers’ knees!                                                      to lecture at UC-Berkeley, Stanford U,
              Following in my father’s footsteps,                                 Cal Poly SanLuis Obispo, and several
           I was sent to the US for my education.                                 universities in China.  Before retiring as
           First to the prep-school Phillips Academy                              an architect, I worked with two young
           at Andover, Massachusetts in 1947.  I                                  architects on a private residence in St.
           learned from Mr. Diz Bensley’s art-                                    Helena, Napa Valley.  It was chosen by
           appreciation course that architecture   was one of the best in the world at that   the Museum of Modern Art San Francisco
           is not just ‘creative expressions’ but a   time because of its teachers like Louis   for their annual Winery Tours.
           ‘service to society.’  Then I went to Yale   Kahn, Mies van der Rohe, and Paul   When I first came to the US, I had
           College in New Haven, Connecticut.  Rudolph, whose trend setting building   a habit of not challenging ‘traditions’
              At Yale I attended the lectures of one   designs of that era still influence   and being obedient and conforming
           of the greatest US architectural historians   us today.                based on my Confucius and Buddhist
           of the 20th century, Prof. Vincent Scully.    When I entered the profession of   upbringing.   I remained reserved and
           I was asked to write essays describing   architecture, I first worked for the offices   quiet for quite a long time.]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[APRIL-JUNE 2018  DIMENSIONS OF ARCHITECTURE  27





















































                                            Guanyin Bodhisattva (left); Billy Lee, pictured at far right, with family and friends (above) at the Wornick Estate;
                                                                            Billy, second from left, with schoolmates at Andover  (below)









                                                                                 But it has led me now to be interested
                                                                                 in how architectural design influences
                                                                                 FRIENDSHIP & RELATIONSHIP and
                                                                                 induces COMPASSION.   I want young
                                                                                 designers to get involved with what
                                                                                 I call ‘caring architecture’ – be it an
                                                                                 empathetic hospital for the sick, a
                                                                                 temporary home for the refugees, a less
                                                                                 stressful work place, a friendly school,
                                                                                 a humanistic prison, a comforting
                                                                                 home, and a place for contemplation
                                                                                 or worship.]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[28  CHILDART  ICAF.org



           The Rooms





           of a




           HOUSE










           ANGELA BROOKS









             ouis XIV, the 17thc King, lived in a   together is a social event and being open   We think about how one material or
          L chateau north of Paris with 700 rooms,   to a living room or a place to study helps   building feature can do more than
           but the painter Vincent van Gogh two   a family spend time together.  Families   one thing.
           centuries later made due with only one   come in all different shapes and sizes:  a   In my house, a bookshelf is a
           room near the southern coast of France.    single parent with children, a single adult   wall between spaces and includes a
           Architects believe that the environment   taking care of a parent, a blended family,   hidden door of books (the handle in
           where a person lives impacts living.  Did   a single person, two parents with children   the bookshelf).  A panel of newsprint
           you know that being inside a building   and a grandparent or three college-aged   (printing paper) can be sanded to feel
           can make you sick or it can make you   sisters living together.  The individual   like velvet, doors can be flush (no frame)
           feel better?  That having a connection   spaces of a house need to accommodate   so they disappear, and you see just one
           to natural light and a breeze improves   how people of all cultures and ethnicity   undulating smooth wall: a beautiful and
           your health and wellbeing.  Being able   live.  Louis XIV would entertain up to   soundproof backdrop to the kitchen and
           to see a garden or a tree (a room with a   5,000 nobles at a dinner.  Van Gogh had   living room. The stairs are steel plates
           view!) brings you closer to it.  These are   but a few friends at his home in Arles.  with hole patterns in them, which filter
           important principles that architects think   In the state California, with its mild   light and allow airflow to the second story.
           about when they design homes.  A house   climate, one can open the entire wall of the   All of these materials in our house are
           can sit on a large lot by itself, or a house   house to the rear garden; this blurs the line   ‘double-duty’; they are both beautiful
           can be a small studio apartment in a very   between inside and outside and makes   and functional.
           tall building; for us the design principles   you feel like the garden is a part of the   The Rooms of a House can tell the
           are exactly the same.               house.  My own residence has been called   story of who you are.  Just think of Louis
              An architect starts planning the rooms   ‘the house without walls’ because when   XIV and van Gogh!
           of a house by thinking about space.  you look at it, you actually can’t see a wall.
              Spaces that are larger and more open   Sliding glass doors disappear into a pocket
           encourage socializing and spaces that   so that the rear garden becomes a part of
           are reduced in size to be more efficient (a   the living room.  Stairs are thin steel plates
           loft sleeping space, for instance) suggest   and sit between clerestory glass and you
           to the inhabitant that they spend less   can see through them to the sky beyond.
           time there; sleeping is a solitary act and   A shade screen, which also provides
           by assigning less space for this purpose   privacy for the bedroom, is a floating plane
           there can be more area in the house for   and not a wall of the house.  These things
           shared activities.  In planning the rooms of   allow those inside the house to feel like
           the house, architects try to illuminate and   they are a part of the outside, promoting
           nurture family functions: cooking a meal   better mental and physical health.]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[ASK               Is there a lot of   Can you open a   Are the ceilings   Can you see all the
                            YOURSELF          natural light so   few windows and   and windows     way through the
                            THESE             that you notice   feel the breeze   high so that the   house from the
                            QUESTIONS         the sun moving    coming through   sunlight is pulled   front door to the
                            WHEN              throughout        the space?       into the room and   back garden?
                            YOU ARE           the day?                           you feel lighter?
                            IN YOUR                                                                The answer for us
                            HOUSE:                                                                 is always YES.]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[30  CHILDART  ICAF.org



           Your Ideal




           TOWN










           JAMES LOGAN ABELL

























                hy do humans congregate in cities?    Generally, cities in the USA and   villages held public meetings in the town
           W How long have humans been         around the world evolved with military   square to discuss improvements and the
           doing this?  If you could design a model   roads and trade routes radiating like a   future of their town, sometimes called the
           city, what elements would you include in   spiderweb, called radial cities.  Egyptian   New England Town Meeting. These kinds
           your new city?                      ruins show us the first early city plans   of city planning meetings with citizen
              Humans have always been highly   organized in rectangular urban blocks,   involvement continue on today.
           “social animals”, similar to chimpanzees   and by the 5th century BC, the Greek   Often cities have grown and changed
           and elephants. Unlike other mammals,   philosopher, Hippodamus, was creating   in ways that no longer make them friendly,
           however, humans have survived over   grid plans for towns.             efficient, or helpful to the people living
           time "in the jungle" by adapting and   In northern New Mexico, the Anasazi   there.   City governments have urban
           shaping their physical environment,   people built cities high on cliff terraces   designers and architects who address these
           working cooperatively, and living in   or within walled areas for protection.    concerns and spend their time planning
           groups of ever increasing numbers.    Many city plans dating back to the Middle   urban improvement s. Providing new roads,
           Archaeologists have discovered ancient   Ages were organized around a castle   new water lines, new power lines, and
           ruins that reveal many aspects of past   or a cathedral in Europe.  In Asia, urban   all the needed city services for a growing
           human settlements.  They include    planning often focused on the palace of   town can sometimes overwhelm municipal
           houses, private yards, pens for keeping   the emperor with city growth surrounding   workers, so often the city government will
           chickens or goats, shared ceremonial fire   and spiraling outward.     hire an independent urban design company
           pits for community gathering, and road   Some of the best American city plans   to address urban problems.  These people
           systems.  The agricultural farms that have   respond to natural features such as   are architects, city planners, landscape
           been found from that era, thousands of   harbors, beaches, rivers, hillsides, and   architects, and sometimes include
           years ago, indicate that our ancestors   mountains. The 1734 James Oglethorpe   transportation engineers, and downtown
           had become village builders and were   Plan for Savannah, GA was a grid of   improvement specialists.
           no longer nomadic. In a much less   city blocks, but introduced “squares”   For the last 50 years, the American
           complex way, these early settlements   of green parks every few city blocks to   Institute of Architects has offered a “city
           foreshadowed the modern urban cities   offer rest and relaxation within the city.    improvement” program to help towns all
           that we know today.                 When the USA was a new country, many   across the USA be healthier, more walkable,]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[APRIL-JUNE 2018  DIMENSIONS OF ARCHITECTURE  31











































     Illustration : John Desmond, FAIA    Springfield, Illinois



          and more enjoyable places to live.  Called
          “R/UDAT”, it is the Regional /Urban
          Design Assistance Team.   Team members
          are selected for their special expertise
          to address that town’s specific issues.
          Often the needs addressed are park
          planning and natural resource protection,
          redeveloping downtowns into more
          walkable and livable places, improving            Use “Google Earth” or “Mapquest” to look at city plans in your region.
          transportation, encouraging urban art and          Can you find examples of radial cities?  How do these compare with
          sculpture, and providing housing for the            grid cities?  Can you find examples that respond to ocean fronts,
          elderly. The visiting team serves with no         rivers, or mountains?   Print some of these examples and display them
          pay so their ideas are often brutally honest.                     on the wall for comparison.
          Most importantly, a “R/UDAT” gets the
          citizens, business owners, and elected            Have several classmates make a list of their favorite places to go in your
          officials talking and planning what kind of a      town. Have them also include places their parents go to frequently.
          future for their children and grandchildren          Be sure to include schools, churches, offices, supermarkets, but
          they would like to have in their town. This is      also public places like playgrounds, parks, and “hang-out” places.
          much like the New England town meeting.           Display these lists on the wall and compare.  What places are the most
             You are the future of cities in the             mentioned?  What city places are the favorites? Finally, make a list of
          decisions you will make over the next              needed improvements you would like to see.  Maybe a skateboard
          decades:  where to live, how far to travel         park, or a water park, or describe your own ideal “hangout place”.
          for work, play, and exercise, and how
          the resources of your town and region
          will be used to the highest and most               Attend a city council meeting or a planning and zoning commission
          efficient use!  Start designing your ideal                 meeting in your town where city improvement
          future city now!                                                   ideas are being discussed.]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[32  CHILDART  ICAF.org
       Emilija Stefanovska, Age 10]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[DIMENSIONS OF ARCHITECTURE  33































                                                                                       Make no

                                                                                       little plans;

                                                                                       they have no

                                                                                       magic to stir

                                                                                       men's blood

                                                                                       and probably

                                                                                       themselves

                                                                                       will not be

                                                                                       realized. Make

                                                                                       big plans; aim

                                                                                       high in hope

                                                                                       and work.






                                                                                       Daniel H Burnham
                                                                                       Architect, FAIA

                                                                                       Urban planner
                                                                                       1846-1912]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[34  CHILDART  ICAF.org



           Themed




           ARCHITECTURE










           MICHAEL LINGERFELT
























                here do the fields of Math,    joy and excitement that you “get” in   opportunity for him to take another
           W Science and Technology merge      making that first mark.            road.  His career started with the
           with Theater, Art and Literature?   How   Imagineers are the creative force   illustration of a mouse and ended
           can you walk among the dinosaurs,   behind the iconic Walt Disney Company   with having the second largest
           engage with a wizardly world, visit a   attractions and experiences enjoyed   entertainment business in the world.
           foreign land or universe?  Become an   by millions of “guests” each year.  They   During your career, you will be
           Entertainment Architect.            combine classic, rich storytelling with   faced with many decisions, forks in the
              In Robert Frost’s classic poem "The   the latest technology to breathe life into   road and challenges.  As an architect,
           Road Not Taken" the reader is challenged   attractions, resorts and cruise ships.    you will be afforded the opportunity to
           to look at the choices we all face as   While everyone knows the heritage,   make a difference through your work.
           opportunities.  We are free to choose   innovation and resourcefulness of   Use innovation and refuse to take the
           either road but do not really know what   Imagineers, most do not know the lengths   easy way out and don’t say, “It can’t
           lies ahead nor the experiences we will   taken to assure “guests” have the best   be done.” Walt Disney crystallized this
           pass up in life because of that choice.    experience possible.        when he said, “Once we step onto the
              In my case, most enter the field of   Using the principles learned at   final path that ascends steeply towards
           architecture because we want to make   Imagineering, I have been able to learn   reality, there is no turning back. We are
           a difference and leave our mark on this   about Prehistoric Earth as well as Outer   encouraged onward by our belief in
           planet, but true architecture is much   Space, be immersed in other cultures   the dream, and each other. If it can be
           more than sheltering humanity from the   while visiting foreign lands and be a   imagined, it can be believed. If it can
           elements but should cause the human   part of technological breakthroughs.    be believed, it can be achieved! ”
           spirit to be uplifted and soar.     Today, I am designing projects that   Use every experience in your path
              How a person approaches a blank   address the physical challenges of   to learn a new skill, try something
           sheet of paper is one of the principles   humanity; to provide protection from   innovative or learn from your mistakes.
           that guide Disney Imagineers, knowing   natural disasters while reducing the   Never underestimate the power of
           that one’s attitude will go a long way   environmental demands of an ever-  going above the expectation or putting
           in determining the outcome.  It is the   increasing population.        in the extra effort.  Architecture has the
           difference between the fear that you   Walt was never satisfied with the status   power to enrich or in many instances
           “have” to make the first mark and the   quo and that trait became an on-going   even save lives.]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[APRIL-JUNE 2018  DIMENSIONS OF ARCHITECTURE  35













































































         Visit a theme park.  Marvel
          at how it is different from
         the architecture you find in
          your hometown.  Debate
            among your friends
            whether this type of
         ‘enhanced reality’ should
          be more commonplace.]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[36  CHILDART  ICAF.org



           Citizen



           ARCHITECT










           EMILY MCGLOHN

























               ow would you describe yourperfect   must be strong, fit into the landscape,   version of the design is more detailed.
           H house? Colorful? Tall? Enormous?   and accepted by the people who will   When the project is complete, a grand
           Warm, dry, and noble: This is how   use them. Energy efficiency and material   opening celebrates the students’ work
           Rural Studio, an off-campus design-  durability are also important criteria   and the community’s new building. The
           build program of Auburn University’s   to consider.                    building keys are given to the new owner;
           College of Architecture, Design &     Buildings that use less energy and stay   this is the best day of the project.
           Construction describes the perfect   useful for a long time are less expensive to   Many organizations believe good
           house. Unfortunately, not everyone has   operate and use fewer natural resources.   architecture is for everyone. MASS
           a house that fits this description. Many   One way to use less energy in buildings   Design Group, in Boston, Massachusetts,
           people in our area live in houses that are   is to design for the regional climate.   works all over the globe advocating for
           cold in the winter and leak when it rains.   In the southern United States, it is hot   “architecture that promotes justice and
           Since 1992, we have worked in rural   and humid in the summer. Rural Studio   human dignity.” Onion Flats Architecture,
           West Alabama to solve these problems.   buildings address this uncomfortable   a firm in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania,
           Auburn architecture students, from all   condition through natural ventilation. In   works to design affordable, beautiful, and
           over the country, move to Hale County,   the winter, the buildings use the sun as a   efficient homes in an urban place.
           Alabama to learn about good design   “free” source of heating. Our buildings   Rural Studio believes that “everyone,
           and how to construct buildings. They use   work with the climate. As a result, they   both rich and poor, deserves the benefit
           their skills to build warm, dry, and noble   use less energy, cost less to operate, and   of good design.” This philosophy will
           houses for families, parks for children,   the occupants are more comfortable.  be realized when students graduate
           and community centers for the public.  Rural Studio buildings are beautiful   into professional architects and practice
              At Rural Studio, students learn   too. Students participate in an interactive   these ideas. It will take more than Rural
           about architecture with their hands. The   design process. They work together to   Studio to solve this problem. Firms like
           students design and build their projects.   propose ideas for their project and make   MASS Design Group and Onion Flats
           Students work with their professors   drawings and models to represent their   Architecture are developing new ideas
           and other professionals like engineers,   ideas. In presentations to their professors,   in their global and urban communities.
           landscape architects, and community   they receive feedback on how to improve   Working together is the best way to
           activists to refine their designs. Important   their ideas. This process repeats until a   achieve this goal and Auburn students
           to the success of a project, buildings   final design is ready for construction; each   are proud to do their part.]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[Lion's Park Playscape, Greensboro, Al








                      Everyone, both rich and
                     poor, deserves the benefit
                          of good design.

                            Rural Studio





                                                                                                 Safe House Museum, Greensboro, Al






















    Pattern Book Home, Greensboro, Al]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[38  CHILDART  ICAF.org



           Architecture Without




           ARCHITECTS











           MICHAEL  J. CROSBIE















                hat is architecture? A good    folks who are not professional architects,   Architecture without architects can
           W definition is that it is the art and   but instead builders (sometimes even non-  be found all over the world, but there
           science of creating buildings. When   builders) who follow common building   are many aspects of these vernacular
           a building is designed by an architect   customs refined over time.     buildings that make them alike. They’re
           there are many questions that must be   In the US, we often find examples of   usually built with materials found close by
           answered: How will it stand up, how will   architecture without architects in rural   (such as brick in the Southern part of the
           it be heated or cooled, will the spaces   places away from cities, where people   US, where clay soil is plentiful, affordable,
           inside be suitable for what their functions   design and construct buildings simply   and the bricks are made locally). In
           are, what will it look like, will it be a “good   by following what their neighbors do.   places where building materials aren’t
           neighbor” to nearby buildings and the   Old barns and churches are excellent   easily found, you can build vernacular
           greater community? Architects bring the   examples of this. Farmers designed and   architecture just by cutting down nearby
           science and art of building together to find   built their own barns based on other   trees (log cabins are great examples of
           answers to these questions, among many   barns they had seen, and often the new   architecture without architects). Such
           more. What they create is architecture.   barns were built with the help of local   buildings often use recycled materials
              But, it turns out that architecture (even   people in “barn-raisings.” Many churches   (a new barn might be made from the
           great architecture) can be designed and   were constructed between the 1700s   materials of an old barn that fell down or
           built by people who are not architects. It’s   and early-1900s by carpenter-builders   was damaged by fire). Another aspect
           called “architecture without architects,” a   who traveled around a region creating   of architecture without architects is
           phrase coined by architect and historian   vernacular architecture. Along with their   that it is often energy efficient. Walls
           Bernard Rudofsky for a 1964 museum   tools, they carried “pattern books” with   and roofs are built with enough natural
           exhibit and book on the topic. The best   examples of church buildings in different   materials to keep out the cold, and the
           architecture without architects is often   styles. A congregation that wanted a new   building is positioned or oriented so
           pretty old, built before architects became   church would pick one they liked from the   that it collects the warmth of the sun. In
           a distinct profession in the mid-1800s. For   pattern book and the carpenter-builders   hot climates, vernacular architecture is
           example, in ancient, traditional societies   would get to work. Carpenter-builders also   designed so that prevailing breezes are
           such as Greece, people followed the   designed and constructed houses in styles   captured to cool the building without
           “vernacular” way of making architecture   that are (and continue to be) popular with   air-conditioning.
           to create whole cities that are finely   most people. In the late-1800s in certain   Simple but beautiful works of
           tuned to function and beauty. Vernacular   parts of the country there was a fashion for   architecture without architects can teach
           is a fancy word for what is “common”   covering vernacular buildings with ornate   architects (and all of us) some of the best
           or shared by people in a certain place.   wood or stone details (today we call them   ways to design new buildings that are
           Lots of architecture without architects is   “Victorians,” after Queen Victoria, who   resourceful, comfortable, and fit in well
           vernacular: it is designed and built by   was monarch of Great Britain at the time).   with the surrounding community.]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[APRIL-JUNE 2018  DIMENSIONS OF ARCHITECTURE  39













































































                                                                                      Take a walk through your
                                                                                    neighborhood where there are
                                                                                    residences, retail stores, banks
                                                                                   and schools, and guess whether
                                                                                    an architect was responsible for
                                                                                           their design.]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[40  CHILDART  ICAF.org



           Sacred




           SPACES










           FRED MARKS









                hat makes something sacred?  Can   Christians may have followed four or   and writing, and the walls & windows
           W its physical properties have an   more routes traveling some 500 miles   of sacred buildings would offer an
           impact on the answer?  It seems that our   from France to reach the Cathedral of   opportunity for artisans to tell stories
           Neolithic-Stone Age ancestors considered   Santiago de Compostela in Galicia,   about mankind and its many faiths &
           the entire planet sacred.  While the word   or northwest Spain.  For thousands of   beliefs using iconography (images and
           sacred can relate to religion or spirituality,   years, Muslims have annually made a   symbols) and calligraphy (decorative
           it can also refer to what you hold precious   pilgrimage, known as Hajj, to the holy   lettering).  Architecture was also a
           or cherish, such as a battlefield where   city of Mecca, in Saudi Arabia; today,   means to express God’s cosmic order
           sacrifices were made or the privacy of   pilgrims number over two million   through mathematical proportions.   In
           your own bedroom.                   people from dozens of countries.    expressing harmony, built spaces would
              A single building or monument can   Before reaching their destination, eager   provide an escape from the everyday
           be sacred in itself or can be a home to a   travelers often could see the buildings   chaos and unpredictability of the
           sacred activity.  The indigenous peoples   from great distances, because the   surrounding secular world.
           of Central and South America built   architecture had soaring elements such
           pyramids to align with the movements of   as spires or minarets or the benefit of no   The Sanctuary
           stars in the universe.  In Europe, towering   visual obstructions.     Entering a cave that displays symbolic
           cathedrals were constructed beginning                                  paintings from 30,000 years ago can be
           in the Middle Ages to house the relics   The Arrival                   just as extraordinary as walking down
           of Jesus and his apostles.  In contrast,   Not all sacred buildings need to be   the nave of a medieval cathedral with a
           a vast complex of temples was erected   entered.  They may serve as a stage   ceiling that is 150 feet (10 stories) high.
           in the 11th, 12th and 13th centuries in   setting for an outdoor event or house   Once inside a sacred space, your whole
           the Southeast Asian country Myanmar,   a deity that may be seen through   consciousness is transformed.  There
           honoring the four incarnations      exterior columns supporting a roof.  A   is a metaphor at work – a mystery.  The
           of the Buddha.                      building designed in the early 1960s by   spatial characteristics of the interior help
                                               the American architect Louis Kahn for   to activate your emotions.  As does the
           The Journey                         scientist Jonas Salk often receives 40,000   art, from light-infused stained glass to
           The influential French novelist Gustave   visitors each year. These ‘pilgrims’ never   dimly-lit marble mosaic flooring.
           Flaubert once said that “pleasure   enter the functional working spaces   There is a small chapel in Houston,
           is found first in anticipation, later in   of this southern California institution   Texas designed by the American
           memory.”  Before the car, the train,   used by biologists and neuroscientists.    architect Philip Johnson that is devoted
           and the bicycle, people walked long   There is a sense of enclosure without   entirely to the works of mid-20th century
           distances to visit sacred sites.  It was   confinement as one looks west to the   ‘color field’ painter Mark Rothko.  In this
           a welcomed journey and one where    Pacific Ocean and to the sky above.  space, one experiences a transparency,
           architecture played a big part.  They   Compulsory public education, such   a Zen simplicity and timelessness.  The
           would go up hills and mountains to see   as attending a school, did not take place   paintings that are on exhibit in one room
           a temple to the gods – Athena/Apollo/  until approximately the 19th century.    are religious without being associated
           Zeus – such as the Parthenon in Athens   Therefore, most citizens in earlier   with religion.  This is a power that is
           or those on the Greek island of Delphi.     centuries had difficulty with reading   shared by all sacred spaces.]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[APRIL-JUNE 2018  DIMENSIONS OF ARCHITECTURE  41



















































          Takstang Monastery in Paro, Bhutan                       St-Etienne Cathedral, Toulouse, France









                                                                           Once inside a sacred

                                                                                  space, your
                                                                           whole consciousness

                                                                                is transformed.
















          The Badshahi Mosque in Lahore, Pakistan]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[42  CHILDART  ICAF.org]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[APRIL-JUNE 2018 DIMENSIONS OF ARCHITECTURE  43




          Learning resources



          BOOKS                               BLOGS                              Charles and Ray Eames:
                                                                                 The Architect And The Painter
          Architecture SHAPES                 www.lifeofanarchitect.com          PBS American Masters, 2011, in English
          by Michael J. Crosbie & Steve Rosenthal, 1993
                                              www.youngarchitect.com             (Profile of the American Architect)
          Cathedral, by David Macaulay, 1999  www.visualizingarchitecture.com    Louis Sullivan:
          City: A Story of Roman Planning and   www.studyarchitecture.com        The Struggle for American Architecture
          Construction, by David Macaulay, 1974                                  by Mark Richard Smith, 2010, in English
                                              www.archispeakpodcast.com
          What It Feels Like To Be A Building                                    (Profile)
          by Forrest Wilson, 1969             www.dezeen.com                     Citizen Architect: Samuel Mockbee and the
          Maya Lin: Artist-Architect of Light and Lines   www.house-design-architects.  Spirit of the Rural Studio
          by Jeanne Walker Harvey, 2017       architectureforlondon.co.uk        by Sam Wainwright Douglas, 2010
          The Phantom Tollbooth               www.contemporist.com               (Profile of the American Architect)
          Norton Juster, 1961                 www.archidose.blogspot.co.uk       Infinite Space: The Architecture of John Lautner,
          Who Built That? Modern Houses       www.aaschool.ac.uk                 by Murray Grigor, 2008, in English
          by Didier Cornille, 2014                                               (Profile of the American Architect)
                                              www.architectureblog.tumblr.com
          Iggy Peck Architect                                                    Loos Ornamental
          by Andrea Beaty & David Roberts, 2007                                  by Heinz Emigholz, 2008, in English
                                                                                 (Profile of Austrian Architect Adolf Loos)
          13 Buildings Children Should Know   movies  (Characters As or
          by Annette Roeder & Jane Michael, 2009  Aspiring to Be Architects)     Schindlers Hauser
                                                                                 by Heinz Emigholz, 2007, in English
          Dreaming Up: A Celebration of Building   Columbus                      (Profile of Austrian-American Architect
          by Christy Hale, 1996               with Parker Posey and Haley Lu Richard, 2017  Oskar Schindler)
          Look at That Building!              Sleepless in Seattle               Regular or Super: Views on Mies van der Rohe
          by Scot Ritchie, 2011               with Tom Hanks, 1993               by Patrick Demers, 2005, in English
          See Inside Famous Buildings         One Fine Day                       (Profile of the German-American Architect)
          by Rob Lloyd Jones, 2008            with Michelle Pfeiffer, 1996       My Architect: A Son’s Journey
                                              The Towering Inferno               by Nathaniel Kahn, 2003, in English
                                              with Paul Newman, 1974             (Profile of the American Architect Louis Kahn)
          ARCHITECTURAL MAGAZINES
                                              12 Angry Men                       Frank Lloyd Wright
          ARCHITECT (Journal of AIA)          with Henry Fonda, 1957             by Ken Burns & Lynn Novick, 1998
          Architectural Record                The Fountainhead                   PBS,  American Masters,in English
          Dwell                               with Gary Cooper, 1949             (Profile of the American Architect)
                                                                                 Philip Johnson: Diary of an Eccentric Architect
          Metropolis                                                             by Barbara Wolf, 1997, in English
          Architectural Digest                                                   (Profile of the American Architect)
                                              DOCUMENTARIES
                                                                                 Antonio Gaudi
                                              Urban Poetry
          GRAPHIC NOVELS                      by Joe Gilbert, 2015. in English   by Hiroshi Teshigahara, 1985, in English
                                                                                 (Profile of the Spanish Architect)
                                              (The Barbican Estate in London)
          Hand-Drying in America: And Other Stories                              REM
          by Ben Katchor, 2013                Eero Saarinen:                     by Tomas Koolhaas, 2016, in English
          Julius Knipl, Real Estate Photographer:   The Architect Who Saw The Future   (Profile of the Dutch Architect Rem Koolhaas)
                                              by Peter Rosen, 2016, in English
          The Beauty Supply                                                      Big Time
          by Ben Katchor, 2000                (Profile)                          by Kaspar Atrup Schroder, 2017, in English
                                              Rotterdam 2040
                                              by Gyz La Riviere, 2014, in English   (Profile of the Danish Architect Bjarke Ingels)
          WEB SITES                           (City’s Future)                    How Much Does Your Building Weigh,
          The American Institute of Architects   The Land Of Many Palaces        Mr. Foster?
                                                                                 by Deyan Sudjic, 2010, in English
           www.aia.org                        by Song Ting, 2016, in English     (Profile of the English Architect)
                                              (Pressuring Farmers to Relocate to the City)
          Union of International Architects                                      Sketches of Frank Gehry
           www.uia-architectes.org            The Human Scalein                  by Sydney Pollack, 2005, in English
                                              by Andreas Dalsgaard, 2012, in English/Danish
          Association of Collegiate Schools of Architecture   (Accommodating Population Growth)  (Profile of the American Architect)
          www.acsa-arch.org                                                      First Person Singular: I.M. Pei
                                              Frei Otto: Spanning The Future
          Academy of Neuroscience for Architecture   by Simon K. Chiu, 2015,in English   by Peter Rosen, 1997, in English
          www.anfarch.org                     (Profile of Architect/Engineer)    (Profile of the Chinese-American Architect)
          American Society of Landscape Architects   Ordos 100                   Powers of Ten, by Charles & Ray Eames, 1977
          www.asla.org                        by Ai Weiwei, 2012, in English     (Depicts Relative Scale of the Universe)
          National Trust for Historic Preservation   (Architecture by Herzog & de Meuron; Planning   Why Man Creates
          www.savingplaces.org                by Weiwei)                         by Saul Bass, 1968, in English
                                                                                 (The Nature of Creativity)



    Madis Aaso, Age 10, Estonia]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[44  CHILDART  ICAF.org




           Credits



           PUBLISHER AND EDITOR                                 THOMAS FISHER, ASSOC. AIA
                                                                Thomas Fisher is a Professor, Director of the Minnesota Design
           ASHFAQ ISHAQ, PH.D.                                  Center and Dayton Hudson Chair in Urban Design.  He is a
           Ashfaq Ishaq is the founder and chair of the International Child   graduate of Cornell University in architecture and previously the
           Art Foundation (ICAF) established in 1997. He is an experienced   Editor Director of Progressive Architecture magazine.  Mr. Fisher has
           entrepreneur, educator, manager, researcher, and civil-sector   written 9 books, over 50 book chapters or introductions, and over
           leader. He holds a Ph.D. in economics from the George Washington   400 articles in professional journals.
           University, where he later served as adjunct associate professor
           of economics. Ashfaq is spearheading a children’s revolution that   STEVEN HOLL, FAIA
           treats children as creators (not merely pupils or consumers), takes   Steven Holl is the founder of Steven Holl Architects based in New
           their imagination as seedbed for invention and innovation, and   York City.  He is recognized as one of the world’s leading architects,
           respects their art as the most honest and purest form of human   having received many prestigious awards including the 1998 Alvar
           creative expression.                                 Aalto Medal, the 2012 AIA Gold Medal and the 2014 Praemium
                                                                Imperiale.  Mr. Holl is an adjunct teacher at Columbia University and
           GUEST EDITOR                                         lectures on a global basis.

           FREDERICK MARKS, AIA, SIX SIGMA GREEN BELT           MARY ANN LAZARUS, FAIA
           Frederick Marks is a Visiting Scholar at the Salk Institute for   Mary Ann Lazarus is a Principal at MALeco, LLC and a Adjunct
           Biological Studies in La Jolla, CA.  He is a specialist in healthcare   Faculty at Washington University in St. Louis, MO.  She is a former
           and laboratory facility design and a current advisor on research to   National AIA Resident Fellow for its Sustainability & Health Initiative,
           the national AIA, the National Institute of Building Sciences (NIBS),   a Program Committee Chair for Greenbuild and the founder of
           and the International WELL Building Institute.       the Sustainable Design Initiative at HOK, the largest US-based
                                                                architectural-engineering firm.
           CONTRIBUTING  WRITERS
                                                                BILLY MING SING LEE
           JAMES LOGAN ABELL, FAIA*                             Billy Ming Sing Lee is retired from the architectural profession but
           James Logan Abell is an architect and a licensed landscape   continues to be active as a teacher.  He most recently was the
           architect  He has been associated with the R/UDAT program for   Treasurer and Membership Director for the US-China People’s
           over three decades. Mr. Abell is a recipient of the prestigious AIA   Friendship Association, South Bay Chapter, California.
           Kemper Medal for his work in urban design, and the AIA Thomas
           Jefferson Award for Public Architecture for a lifetime achievement in   MICHAEL LINGERFELT, FAIA
           the design of civic buildings.                       Michael Lingerfelt, FAIA, is a former Director of Project Architecture
                                                                & Engineering for Walt Disney Imagineering.  Over his career, he
           IAN BADER, FAIA                                      has designed/managed $3.6 billion of construction that includes
           Ian Bader is a Principal of Pei Cobb Freed & Partners in New York   hospitality facilities, schools and healthcare buildings.  Mr. Lingerfelt
           City and was educated at the University of the Witwatersrand,   is currently working on a ‘signature’ restaurant at the EPCOT Japan
           Johannesburg.  His design commissions include symphony halls,   Pavilion when he is not traveling to Texas, Florida, Alabama, Puerto
           academic buildings, and courthouses.  In 2017, Mr. Bader’s firm   Rico, Saint Barthelemy and Haiti to help in disaster relief.
           won the AIA 25 Year Award for the Grand Louvre-Phase I.
                                                                EMILY MCGLOHN, AIA
           ANGELA BROOKS, FAIA                                  Emily McGlohn  is a Visiting Assistant Professor at Auburn University
           Angela Brooks is Managing Principal of the firm Brooks + Scarpa   Rural Studio and a Designer at Duet Design Studio in Alabama.  She
           based in Los Angeles and a recipient of the AIA 2010 National Firm   received her Bachelor degree at Auburn U and Masters degree at
           Award and the 2014 Smithsonian Cooper-Hewitt Design Award.  University of Oregon; both in Architecture.  Ms. McGlohn is a Board
                                                                member & Secretary of The Society of Building Science Educators
           MICHAEL J. CROSBIE, FAIA, PHD                        and a published author in various professional journals.
           Michael J. Crosbie, FAIA, PhD, is an architect, writer, and professor
           of architecture at the University of Hartford in Connecticut.  He has   HENRY PETROSKI, PE
           served as an editor for the AIA Journal, Progressive Architecture,   Henry Petroski is a professor of civil engineering and of history at
           ArchitectureWeek.com, and Faith & Form.              Duke University. He is the author of many books on engineering
                                                                and design, including To Engineer Is Human: The Role of Failure in
                                                                Successful Design and The Road Taken: The History and Future of
                                                                America’s Infrastructure.]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[APRIL-JUNE 2018  DIMENSIONS OF ARCHITECTURE  45




                                                                      Image Credits



          DONALD RATTNER, RA                                           Page 3, Introduction
          Donald Rattner is a Founding Principal of Donald M Rattner, AIA,   UIA WP Architecture and  Children Program
          Creativity Architect based in New York City.  He is a graduate of   Page 5, Architectural Education
          Columbia U and Princeton U, and author of the book “The Creativity   Justin Ladia, Faculty of Architecture, University of Manitoba
          Catalog, Parallel of the Classical Orders of Architecture.”  Mr.   Pages 6-7, Louis Kahn Sketch
          Rattner serves as a Board of Director for the International   Sue Ann Kahn/Art Resource, NY
          Child Art Foundation (ICAF).
                                                                       Pages 8-9, Why Buildings Remain Standing
          STEVE ROSENTHAL                                              "What It Feels like To Be a Building," Landmark Reprint Series,
          Steve Rosenthal is an architectural photographer trained as an   1989
          architect, and the co-author, with his wife and Michael Crosbie, of   Pages 10-13, Drawing as Thought
          five children’s books about architecture.                    Chapel of St. Ignatius and Kiasma Museum: Paul Warchol;
                                                                       Hunters Point Library and Linked Hybrid: Steven Holl Architects
          EWA STRUZYNSKA
          Ewa Struzynska is an architect and  Director UIA WP Architecture &   Page 15, Creativity + Place
          Children, in Paris, France.  Uniting 124 countries and territories, UIA   IdeaPaint
          seeks to educate children so - as adults, citizens, clients, politicians -   Pages 16-17, Preserve Conserve Restore
          they will be equipped to take an active part in shaping the world to   Victorian Farmhouse: Adam Franco; Studio Interior: Khushru Irani
          everyone’s benefit.                                          Design Studio
                                                                       Pages 18-19, Unifying a Museum
          THOMAS VONIER, FAIA, RIBA                                    All images: Pei Cobb & Freed & Partners
          Thomas Vonier is President/Secretary General of the International
          Union of Architects in Paris, a founding President of AIA Continental   Pages 20-21, Chairs
          Europe and the past President of The American Institute of Architects   Eames 'Lounge' chair: Herman Miller Co.; Gerrit Reitveld chair: V
          (AIA) in Washington, DC.  He is a former European correspondent   & A Images, London/Art Resource, NY; Venturi 'Sheraton' chair:
          for Progressive Architecture magazine.                       online_chips; Aalto 'Armchair 42': Hive Modern; Gehry 'Wiggle'
                                                                       chair: Houzz.com; Wright 'Johnson Wax' chair: Design Within
          ASHLEY WILSON, AIA, ASID                                     Reach; Mies 'Barcelona' chair: Knoll Co.
          Ashley Wilson is the Graham Gund Architect for the Historic Sites   Pages 22-25, Supporting Environmental Sustainability
          at the National Trust for Historic Preservation (NTHP).  She provides   Earth image: US Geological Survey; Sunflowers: Bruce Fritz;
          broad oversight to the conservation and preservation of the   Charts: top two adapted from Architecture 2030; bottom one
          architecture and landscapes of the Trust’s twenty-seven historic sites   adapted from U.S Green Building Council, School Interior Photos:
          in the United States.                                        Alan Karchmer/OTTO; School Aerial View: Digital Imaging and
                                                                       Design, Inc.; Bird Nest: Jean Louis Tosque, Pixabay
          DESIGNER                                                     Pages 26-27, My Life as an Architect
                                                                       Bodhisattva: Walters Museum, Baltimore; Other images: Billy Lee
          KAREN DEANS
          Karen Deans is a grahic designer, illustrator and author     Pages 28-29, The Rooms of a House
          of children's books.                                         Van Gogh's "Room at Arles": The Art Institute of Chicago/Art
          www.karendeans.com                                           Resource, NY; Brooks + Scarpa and photographer Marvin Rand
                                                                       Page 35, Themed Architecture
                                                                       All images: Michael Lingerfeldt
                                                                       Page 37, Citizen Architect
                                                                       All images, (except bottom right): Tim Hursley; Workers putting up
                                                                       stud wall: Rural Studio
                                                                       Page 39, Architecture Without Architects
                                                                       All images: Steve Rosenthal Photography
                                                                        Page 41, Sacred Spaces
                                                                       Monastery: Keren Su, China Span photography, c/o Sterling
                                                                       Publishing ; Cathedral: Steve Rosenthal Photography; Mosque:
                                                                       Ed Kashi, CreativeLive Photography c/o Sterling Publishing
          *FAIA stands for Fellow of American  Institute of Architects]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[ICAF.org


































































           P. O. Box 58133
           Washington DC 20037]]></page></pages></Search>