<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="36"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[April-June 2017                                   The Magazine of the International Child Art Foundation






























































                                                                   The Road To The


                                                             F        UTURE









                                                                   CREATIVE PATHWAYS]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[Editor's Corner





          This special issue on futures thinking                     APRIL-JUNE 2017
          celebrates the 20th anniversary of the                     Vol 17, Issue 2, Number 50
          founding of ICAF - the International Child
          Art Foundation.  We are most grateful to                   Editor and Publisher: Ashfaq Ishaq,
                                                                     Ph.D.
          Professor Sohail Inayatullah (based in Tai-
          pei and Sydney) for his guidance and to                    Guest Editor: Sudhir Desai
          our Guest Editor Mr. Sudhir Desai (based                   Contributing Editor:  Martina Woe-
          in Bangalore) for bringing this issue to                   bcken
          life. Thanks also to the contributors for
          sharing their knowledge and wisdom with                    Creative Director:  Karen Deans
          our young readers.                                         Editorial Assitant: Monica Meneses

          ICAF can also means “I Create A Fu-                        Contributors: Sudhir Desai, Heidi
          ture.” Children are creators and ICAF                      Gustafson, Sohail Inayatullah, Anne
          transforms them into global citizens of the                Boysen, Ivana Milojevic,
          future. Today’s rising parochialism and                    Sandjar Kozubaev, Martina Woebcken,
          nativism imperils ICAF’s very existence. To                Dr. Lisa Hasler Waters, Dr. Peter Bishop,
          The past two decades as many as 5 mil-                     Dr. Thérèse Dugan, Marianne Solomon,
                                                                     Stefan Frischauf, Dr. Ashfaq Ishaq.
          lion 8- to 12-year-olds children have pro-
          duced original art under ICAF programs,                    Photo Credits: Provided by the
          but this is not enough because total world                 contributors, or  by Pixabay.com
          population in this age group is about
          660 million. ICAF must grow, but this is
          not possible without your help. So please
          donate today at www.icaf.org/support/.
          Together we can paint a brighter future
          for all.                                                   All rights reserved. Reproduction of the whole or
                                                                     any part of the contents without written permission is
                                                                     prohibited. ChildArt (ISSN 1096-9020). Copyright
                                                                     2017 International Child Art Foundation. Printed in
                                                                     the United States of America.
                                                                     ChildArt quarterly magazine, published since 1998,
          Ashfaq Ishaq, Ph.D.                                        is a commercial-free arts learning, self-discovery,
                                                                     and global education periodical expressly written for
          Editor                                                     8-12 year-olds, but useful as a teaching tool fo early
                                                                     educators and inspirational for creative individuals of
                                                                     all ages. Subscribe to ChildArt online at www.icaf.org.
                                                                     When a child's creativity is ignored, it could be lost
                                                                     forever. Tax-deductible donations support children's
                                                                     creative and empathic devlopment. You can donate
                                                                     online at www.icaf.org, or make your check to ICAF
                                                                     and mail to: ICAF, P.O. Box 58133, Washington, DC
                                                                     20037.
                                                                             Cover art by Emilija Stefanovska (10), Macedonia.]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[The Road To The Future: Creative Pathways




                                 Ride Into Tomorrows                               Sudhir Desai   4

                                 DIY Futures Lab                                  Heidi Gustafson   6

                                 Using the Future to Change the
                                 Story of Today                                  Sohail Inayatullah   8

                                 Imagining the Future of Work                        Anne Boysen  10

                                 Healing Traumatic Pasts
                                 Through Emancipatory
                                 Futures Narratives                                Ivana Milojevic  13
                                                                                               ´
                                 Three Basic Skills to Think Like a Futurist    Sandjar Kozubaev  16
                                 Dr. Mihai Nadin:
                                 Scholar, Engineer, Creative Thinker            Martina Woebcken  19

                                 Mapping the Futures With Video              Dr. Lisa Hasler Waters  21

                                 Fun is Good                                       Dr. Peter Bishop  24

                                 Chips and Tips:
                                 A Conversation With Dr. Dugan of Intel           Dr. Ashfaq Ishaq  26

                                 Creating Your Future                            Mariane Solomon  28

                                 Afghan Kids: Their Future and Ours               Stefan Frischauf  31

                                 Children Imagining the Future
                                 Art from the ICAF Collection                                    34





                                                                                  Art by Viviana Norambuena Torres (11), Chile.]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Ride into Tomorrows

                   A letter from our guest editor, Sudhir Desai:






















               n the 20th of July 1969, when Neil Arm-       As human societies became more complex, and
               strong landed on the moon, I was a 14 year   plans and projects had longer gestation periods,
        O old in Bhopal, India. I remember that date     some inter-generational, it became critical to know
        so clearly, because I had etched it on the headboard   beforehand if something in the future might disrupt
        of my bed. Even though Yuri Gagarin and others
                                                         the prevailing and preferred present-day order of
        had been into space before, landing on the moon
                                                         things.
        changed the entire picture of what was possible
        in future with humans in space. My imagination       There have always been people who claimed
        ‘skyrocketed’ and I resolved to join NASA. Little   knowledge of the future, and were admired or
        could I have foreseen the progress we have made   worshipped because they could not only foretell but
        since, and the exciting work that is now happening   could change the future. Even today, those who can
        all around the world.                            foresee and shape the future, have immense influ-
            Just as we are familiar with the phrase ‘long,   ence and hence power.
        long ago’, from the stories of our childhood, the    In the past we called them prophets, shamans,
        idea of a ‘long time from now’ has intrigued human
                                                         diviners or astrologers, and some methods they
        minds from the beginning of civilization.
                                                         used such as tarot cards or palmistry were based on
            Our earliest hunter-gatherer ancestors had to   systems of knowledge that were not scientific.
        wonder whether there would be food and shelter in
                                                             Today, we increasingly rely on science and
        ensuing months, though their time horizons were
                                                         technology to better understand our world and fore-
        limited. When humans settled down and became
                                                         cast with some confidence what might happen. The
        farmers, it became even more critical to know about
                                                         power of a forecast often depends on underlying
        natural events, such as rainfall or storms that might
     ChildArt | April-June 2017 ChildArt | April-June 2017  uncertainties changed, beyond natural elements, but   what the future might bring is rising with time and
                                                         conditions not changing much, but the only thing
        impact crops.  Later, during the Industrial Age the
                                                         constant now is change itself. But our need to know
        the anxieties about the future and its wonder didn’t
                                                         the experts are now called futurists.
        subside or vanish.





   4  4                                                              Art by Kuang Myat Zaw (12), Myanmar.]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[n this special issue of ChildArt, The Road to the Future,   r. Sohail Inayatullah (pages 8-9) informs you how
           Creative Pathways, we invite you to begin your journey into   futures thinking can help you deliberate about the
        I your own individual and our collective futures. You learn  D future of your city or town. Anne Boysen (pages
        about futures thinking, why it is important, useful, and most   10-12) describes some historical trends that will influence the
        deserving of your personal involvement. You will meet several   work you will do and how you will do it. Dr. Ivana Milojevic
        leading futurists and experts from around the world to guide   (pages 13-15) shows the importance of stories in shaping and
 A letter from our guest editor, Sudhir Desai:
        your thinking and help you plan a future.             envisioning better tomorrows. Stefan Frischauf (pages 31-33)
                                                              brings into your consciousness the future faced by children
            If you become fascinated, you might ask: How do I
                                                              living on the fringe, like those in war-torn Afghanistan. To
        become a futurist?  I too asked this question, though much
                                                              understand why professionals become interested in and practice
        later in my life when I was working in a technology company
                                                              futures, we interviewed Dr. Mihai Nadin (pages 19-20) and Dr.
        in Houston, Texas. Yes, I never joined NASA but I did get to
                                                              Therese Dugan (pages 26-27), one working in a university and
        work with NASA but in a different capacity.
                                                              the other in Silicon Valley.
            Late 1990’s onwards change had become rapid with the
                                                                 The futures field has matured to where we now have
        transformational impact of the Internet. As strategists, we were
                                                              formal educational programs. Dr. Peter Bishop, who has been
        struggling to understand the implications of the digital tech-
                                                              teaching Futures Studies for decades, has now made it his
        nologies and our own excitement with these developments. I
                                                                                                  mission to teach
        became exposed
                                                                                                  futures in schools
        to “scenario
                                                                                                  too (pages
        planning”—a
                                                                                                  24-25). Sandjar
        key method used
                                                                                                  Kozubaev (pages
        by futurists. I
                                                                                                  16-18) provides
        wanted to learn
                                                                                                  three things you
        more and joined
                                                                                                  can practice right
        the Master’s
                                                                                                  away to create
        Program at the
                                                                                                  better futures in
        University of
                                                                                                  more imaginative
        Houston (Clear
                                                                                                  ways. Dr. Lisa
        Lake) with Dr.
                                                                                                  Waters (pages
        Peter Bishop
                                                                                                  21-23) intro-
        (see page 24-25).
                                                                                                  duces us to Vlad,
        Later I worked
                                                                                                  a student just
        on the “Impact of Future Technology” with IBM and met
                                                              like yourselves, who is using videos and YouTube for mapping
        several world-renowned futurists, some of whom you will meet
                                                              futures. You too can find the expression for your own pas-
        here in this magazine. Though today I do not predict the future,
                                                              sions and interests. You might then want to participate in the
        my mindset and ways of thinking have irreversibly changed,
                                                              Scenario Writing competition that Marianne Solomon (pages
        making me “future sensitive”—thinking about and incorporat-
                                                              28-30) describes. This involves creative writing also, which is
        ing knowledge about the future into all that I do. This is our
                                                              critical to developing compelling scenarios of the future.
        objective for you with this issue: Make you future sensitive.
                                                                 These articles and exercises will get you started on this ex-
            This issue of ChildArt provides ideas on how you can get
                                                              citing journey. Many other resources available for free today can
        started on that journey. You will find that thinking systemati-
                                                              help you continue your creative explorations further. Here is a
        cally about tomorrows matters not only for the future you will
                                                              link to a web site where you will find talks with many leading
        create for yourself— for it actually is also important for all of us
                                                              futurists - www.singularityweblog.com/category/podcasts/
        and for the generations to come. This requires a different kind
        of creative thinking—what we call futures thinking. With the
        help of some of the experts featured here, you can give it a try.   Enjoy the ride into tomorrows!
                                                                                                                     ICAF.ORG ICAF.ORG
        Sudhir Desai is a strategic designer and futurist. He is currently Head of Strategy and Foresight at the Srishti Institute of Art,
        Design andTechnology in Bangalore,  India. He is also CEO of Living Enterprise, astrategic design consulting company.
                                                                                                                    5  5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[DIY Futures Lab



        How To Make Your Own Divination Kit

        By Heidi Gustafson

        What is divination?
        Divination is the art and practice of discovering hidden knowledge. Some people say it means ‘predicting
        the future,’ but that is not completely true. In ancient times, divination was used for many things, in many
        ways. Most simply, divination was a practice used to explore the unknown in unexpected, new, ways.
        Why do we use divination?
        Humans are scared of the unknown. It’s human nature to worry about tomorrow, to worry about what we
        do not know yet. Why? We are actually just pretty afraid of change. Because change is unstoppable!
        Change is always happening. We can’t control everything that happens, let alone understand it.

        So, how do we become less scared of change?
        We make tools to help us feel better about change, tomorrow, and the future. Some of these are called
        divination tools. You’ve probably heard of the popular ones: tarot cards, fortune cookies, crystal balls. But
        there are thousands of other kinds of divination tools!


                                                                            Plant
                                                                Mineral
                             Example Chart                    piece of metal  Leaf, wood,  Animal      Personal     Ancester
                                                                                       Feather,
                                                                                                Small object,
                                                                 Stone,
                                                                                                           Item from
                                                                                                            family or
                                                                                      bone, fur,
                                                               jewel, shell,
                                                                                                 old tooth,
                                                                            flower,
                                                                            seed
                                                                                                game piece,
                                                                                                           tribe, photo,
                                                                                        claw
                                                                                                          jewelry, note
                                                                                                  hair tie
                                                Name of           Red       Rose     Chicken     Chess      String
                                                Object           Stone      Petal      Bone       Piece    Necklace
                                               Description 1
                                                                 Hard      Crinkly    Bumpy      Tough       Like
                                               Feels                                                         Hair
                                               Description 2      Red       Pink      Weird      Knight     Noodle
                                               Looks like        Heart      Chair       Log
                                               Description 3               Smells       It's     Helps     Reminds
                                                                Smooth                                      Me Of
                                               Favorite Part               Sweet       Gross     Me Win
                                                                                                           Grandma






     ChildArt | April-June 2017 ChildArt | April-June 2017  Heidi Gustafson is an interdisci-


        plinary artist, translator and re-
        searcher. She's the founder of Early
        Futures, a research studio studying
        the intersections of primordial mat-
        ter and human consciousness. See

        earlyfutures.com.
   6  6   more of work on her studio website:]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[DIY Futures Lab  DIY (Do It Yourself!) DIVINATION KIT



 How To Make Your Own Divination Kit                          You are going to use your descriptions
        What You Need:
      - a bag, jar or any container (even your hand!)         of the objects to help you get you started. You are go-
      - 5 small found items (see below)                       ing to imagine each of those objects and descriptions
      - a pen or pencil or chalk or string                    tell you something about your future. Let’s have fun with
      - something to draw on (paper bag, the ground)          it! See how many ideas you can come up with. For
                                                              example: let’s say you had a pink rose petal land in the
        INSTRUCTIONS:                                         ‘super important.’ What could that mean about impor-
                                                              tant parts of possible futures?
        STEP 1
        Find five objects that come from one of               Perhaps it means one future wants to be soft and pink.
        each of the categories.                               Or maybe it means your future needs a better smell?
        Describe the objects in 3 different ways              Or maybe it means you will plant flowers soon, or that
        (see example chart to the left).                      someone is getting married. Or maybe it means you
                                                              could make something out of rose petals? Or that you
        STEP 2                                                need to wear more things that are crinkly and pink!
        Draw three large circles. You can                     Keep going until you can’t think of anything else. It’s
        draw them on the ground (with                         okay if you can only think of a couple things.
        chalk, string, paint), or on paper
        (with pen, pencil or marker).                         Now go through the next circles. The second circle is
                                                              “kind-of important.”  You don’t need to think about this
              Label the circles:                              object that much yet. Do the same excerise you did
              innermost circle = super important              with the important circle, but this time think about it
              middle circle = kind-of important               more like “I don’t need to worry that much about it.”
              outer circle = not important
              everything outside the circle =                 For example: let’s say you had a red stone that landed
              pay more attention to me!                       there. What could this mean you don’t need to worry
                                                              too much about? Perhaps you can stop worrying about
        STEP 3                                                everything being so hard; maybe things will get easier!
        Put the objects in
        a bag, cup, or your                                   The outer circle is “not important.” That means, do not
        own hand.                                             think about these things at all.
        STEP 4                                                Anything that lands outside the three circles means,
        Ask a question about the future, or                   “You aren’t paying enough attention to me!” If any ob-
        something you are curious about that                  jects land there, you should try to keep them for a few
        you do not know yet.                                  days close to you. Carry them around in your pocket,
                                                              or keep them near your bed. You can think “how can
        STEP 5                                                I pay more attention to you?” For example: let’s say
        Throw the objects onto the                            it is a feather. You could try to pay more attention to
        circle area.The objects will fall                     anything that has to do with feathers: birds, flying,
        in different circles or outside                       wings. Try to go back to the place you got that object
        the circles.                                          from (did you find it on a trail? in your backyard? did
        STEP 6                                                someone give it to you?).  Whatever you can do, think
        Now for the tricky part: Divination                   about this object as much as possible to help it come
        (ie. making the future!) Start from                   back into your circles of importance!
        the middlemost circle. Did any objects
        land there? Whatever lands in this                    You can play this future game with your friends too.
        circle is what we will call “super im-                Have them ask you a question, and you can throw your
        portant!” You need to think about this                objects into the circle for them. You can come up with
        object (or objects!) a lot.                           ideas and talk about all the different futures they might
                                                              have.  The most important aspect of all divination is
                                                              creating a sense of mystery,
                                                               make believe, and
                                                               creative imagination.                                 ICAF.ORG ICAF.ORG


                                                                                                                    7  7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[From Prediction to Transformation:

        Using the Future


        to Change the Story of Today



        Imagine the Unthinkable. Dream the Impossible.



        By Sohail Inayatullah




























        Figure 1                                              Figure 2
                  e think about futures in many contexts and the   first is predictive. In this, we seek to make precise and we hope
                  future of cities is often on our minds these days.   accurate predictions of what will come. How many computers
        WFigure 1, for example,  shows the future of a city   will there be in 2030? What percent of cars on the road will be
        in Australia. It is a prediction. We can interpret it differently   driverless? Will humans reach Mars by 2050?
        - is this a wonderful clean future with very little traffic?  We
                                                                 Governments, corporations, nongovernmental organiza-
        can also question it, asking where are the humans? Where is
                                                              tions, social movements, and individuals all seek to predict.
        nature? We can also take a different view of the future of the
                                                              They want to know what will happen. This is partly so they can
        same city. Figure 2 is drawn by an 11 year old. In her future,
                                                              make better decisions, but often it is to reduce anxiety,  and to
        the city is more pedestrian focused. There are even skywalks.
                                                              make the world a better place.
        But most significantly, she is in that future. The future is about
        future generations - tomorrow's children. But when we explore   A second aspect of Futures Thinking is interpretive. We
        different perspectives, the future is opened up and we can ask:   are less concerned here about predicting and more focused on
        what type of city do we wish to live in?              meaning, on gaining insight from predictions of the future. We
                                                              understand that people actually understand the future differ-
     ChildArt | April-June 2017 ChildArt | April-June 2017  ble. Linking the impossible with reality are the words of Nelson   usual. Others see the future as full of difficulty, as a world of
          There is certainly a fun aspect of Futures Thinking. Science
                                                              ently. Some see the future as more of the same, business-as-
        fiction, imagining the unthinkable and dreaming the impossi-
                                                              danger and pain. Still others see the future as transformative,
        Mandela, who said: "It always seems impossible until its done."
                                                              where everything can and will change. The impossible will be-
            But there is also a rigorous aspect of Futures Thinking. This  come possible. And finally, others wish for the future to be past,
                                                              when times were simpler, and when the world was easier to
        is important as it disciplines the field, structuring how we think.
                                                              believing them to be either linear or cyclical.
   8  8   In Futures Studies, there are four important approaches. The   understand. Interpretations also differ by cultures and nations]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[third approach is critical. In this perspective, it is not   s in all innovative work, there can be resistance. People
        A prediction or individual or social interpretation that is  Amay not wish to help do the dishes. The contribution
        important, but what is not being said - the hidden assump-  of Futures Thinking is we search for the narrative or the
        tions behind what we research, what we focus on. For exam-  metaphor behind their views. For example, the metaphor
        ple, one may imagine the future as business-as-usual because  could be: it is not fair, I always have to do the dishes? Thus,
        one is in a position of economic privilege. Another person or  the real issue, then becomes how to create a fairer society.  In
        organization may be in difficulty and thus see the future as   the move from the current to the desired future, we need to
        dystopian. Where one stands can determine what one sees.   find the story that is blocking. We then search for a better
        In this approach, the role of the futurist is to question all   metaphor that can create a better strategy and way forward.
        assumptions as to energy use (coal or solar), or the type of   One could then create a new story of “taking turns” - every-
        marriages (human - robot?) that we will have in the future.   one gets a go, both to wash dishes and to rest. Or one could
        The questioning challenges what we consider as normal.   find an exchange metaphor - i.e. you rub my back and I’ll
                                                              rub yours, i.e. you do the dishes and I’ll do the garbage. Or
            The final approach to the future is action learning. In
                                                              one can use time to create more wealth and just purchase a
        this approach we move from vision and ideas to strategies.
                                                              robot.
           Prediction                          Control the future - what will happen?


           Interpretation                      What do you mean? We see the future differently
                                               based on where we stand.


           Critical                            What are the assumptions behind what we believe?


           Action Learning                     How we create the future we wish for.



        If we wish for a greener, walkable city, with deep democracy,   Ok, it keeps on coming back to the robot. Maybe the
        engagement, what do we do next? How do we create this   future is really about new technologies. Even if ultimately
        future? Do we petition city government? Do we start a   it is,  it is the meanings we give to new technologies that
        neighborhood green committee? Do we have social media   will be critical - are they our servants, friends, pets, will we
        campaigns? The future in this last approach is used to   co-evolve with them? This depends on how we see them -
        change today. The future makes a way to make a difference.   what our story of ourselves and technologies is, and can be
                                                              different.
            This completes the cycle: from prediction to interpreta-
        tion to critique to action.  An example of this approach that   Futures Thinking thus is about going deeper, asking
        is easy to understand is as follows: a  researcher asked young   questions, and finding solutions to today’s problems, and
        children to predict the future. They drew images of robots   creating opportunities to create different tomorrows.
        in the kitchen. If one only focused on prediction, then the
        conclusion could be that the automation is everything!
        While this may indeed be the case, he went a step further,
        and asked: what do you mean by robots in the kitchen?
        They responded: I want to spend more time with mommy
        and daddy. The question was then not about new technolo-
        gies, but about creating community - about the future of the
        family.

            A  third level critical analysis would be focused on
        asking challenging questions. Well, besides robots, how else
        can we spend more time with the parents? At this stage,
        scenarios can be developed. (1) Well, if we all chipped in,
        then the dishes would be done sooner and then we could all   Dr. Sohail Inayatullah is
        have family time. (2) Well, let’s pay one of the kids to do the   Unesco Chair in Futures Studies.
        dishes. They get an allowance and parents are less tired. (3)   Tamkang University, Taiwan;
        Well, we could take turns cleaning the kitchen. (4) Ok, let’s   University of the Sunshine Coast,
        just buy a robot. Finally, we decide what needs to be done.   Australia; Melbourne Business
        What is the best plan of action forward?                                                                     ICAF.ORG ICAF.ORG
                                                              School, Australia, and USIM, Ma-
                                                              laysia. Director, metafuture.org
                                                                                                                    9  9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Imagining the Future of








                                                                                                                              Jobs
                                                                                                                          Affected

                                                                                                                   Interpreter
                                                                                                                      Interpreter
                                                                                                                   Translator
                                                                                                                      Translator
                                                                                                                   Diagnostician
                                                                                                                  Diagnositician
                                                                                                                   Lawyer
                                                                                                                         Lawyer
                                                                                                                   Customer
                                                                                                                       Customer
        Have you ever heard about a CAPILLAIRE MAKER? Or a LAMPLIGHTER?                                                 Care
                                                                                                                             Care
        The first is a person who makes orange flavored syrup. The second is someone whose
        job was to light, extinguish and refuel street lamps before electricity was invented. Both
        of these were job titles held by people living in the Victorian era, about 100 to 200
        years ago. Today, you would probably not get a job with these titles.




                                                                                            by Anne Boysen
                                                                       th
             s our society became more modernized, so did our   in the 20  century by having products made by work-
        A jobs. A few decades after the Victorian era ended,   ers at an assembly line.  Instead of having one person
        the world once again faced new needs and new job       make a whole product from start to finish, he realized
        titles.                                                that workers could get more done in a shorter amount
                                                               of time if they could concentrate on just one task at a
        Henry Ford was an important influence on industry
                                                               time. This brought the costs down and enabled Ford to
                              th
        and work in the early 20  century. Ford was the founder
                                                               sell cars at lower prices.  Instead of selling only to the
        of the Ford Car Company, but he was also famous for
                                                               wealthy, the Ford Model T was the first car produced
        something else. Ford changed what jobs looked like
                                                               for a mass market.
                                                               Many companies followed Ford’s lead, and started
                                                                making assembly line products for mass consumption.
                                                                 Some products we take for granted today were revo-
                                                                              lutionary in the first part of the 1900s,
                                                                                 such as the washer and telephones.
                                                                                   Not only did the standard of
                                                                                    living drastically improve as a
                                                                                     result, but many people were
                                                                                      needed in production, so
                                                                                       unemployment was low.
     ChildArt | April-June 2017 ChildArt | April-June 2017  The Ford Model T            monotonous for work-
                                                                                       But the ‘Fordistic’ work was


                                                                                        ers who experienced very
                                                                                        little variation in their
                                     was the first car produced
                                                                                        work routines. At the end
                                     for a mass market.
                                                                                        of the 1900s, instead of



  10
  10]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Look at the flower diagram to see which of the different jobs
                            Jobs Affected              could be automated. How do you think this will affect jobs
                              Scientist                in the future?
                              Statistician
                              Customer Care                     happening in many countries in the world.  In other
                              Strategist                         words, since machines could help so many workers
       Jobs                   CEO
   Affected                                                          at the factories get things done, the need to hire
                                                                        more employees became less.
 Interpreter                Cognitive
 Interpreter
 Translator                 Abilities                 Jobs Affected       But it isn’t only robots in factories that could
 Translator
 Diagnostician
 Diagnositician                                             Teacher       take jobs away. Think about jobs where
 Lawyer    Natural                                        Caregiver
  Lawyer
 Customer  Language                     Social/        HR Manager         you have to use both your body and your
 Customer
      Care  Processing      FUTURE      Emotional                         brain, such as driving. The same automotive
       Care                  JOBS                          Therapist      factories that are using robots to put cars
                                        Abilities      Psychologist      together are installing artificially intelligent
                                                                        computers that can make the cars drive all by
                 Sensory          Physical                             themselves! When this happens, many people
             Perception           Abilities                          who drive for a living will be without a job. Even
                                                                 professors and specialists who have gone to school for
    Jobs Affected                       Jobs Affected           many years to learn their expertise are sometimes losing
       Driver                                                   to smart computers. This is because smart computers –
       Manufacturer                      Manufacturer           or artificial intelligence – can read millions of research
       Retailer                                 Dentist         papers in only a few seconds and learn enough to make
       City Planner                            Welder           a decision.
       Water/Electricity                      Plumber
                reader                          Driver          Imagining The Future of Jobs
                                    Physical Therapist
                                                                If humans are losing some of the jobs they fill today,
                                                                does it mean that we will not have jobs in the future?
                                                                Can you think of new types of jobs? Can you think of
        having one factory making a product from A thru Z at
                                                                existing jobs that will be better?
        an assembly line in a factory, a final product could be
        put together by parts that were made in many different
        companies in many parts of the world at the same time.      Will Driving a Car Become
                                                                               a Thing of the Past?
        This was made possible with more globalized produc-
        tion and better information technology.
        Now, a little over a decade and a half into the new
        century we are again facing changes to how we work,
        consume and live. While many workers were needed
        for the ‘Fordistic’ system, the changes we face today
        could put many people out of work. This is because
        computers and robots have become so good at
        doing things we used to need people to do.
        These machines could could now replace
        physical labor.
        For example, between 2000 and 2010
        almost four million manufactur-
        ing jobs disappeared in the U.S.
        alone, while productivity in the
        U.S. almost doubled. The same is
                                                                                                                     ICAF.ORG ICAF.ORG



                                                                                                                    11
                                                                                                                    11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Below are two scenarios with examples of new jobs or jobs that become

          more important when computers and ROBOTS do them for us. Can you
          think of some other ones? Can you draw them?




        Kira checked her morning                              Jose tried his best to appease his mother with his
        alerts and noticed that her real-                     career choice to become a teacher. “But mom, the job
        time market feedback algorithm                        has changed so much since you were a teacher." He
        had created a new consumer                            noticed the grey strands in her hair and the deepening
        demand she had to respond to                          furrows in her forehead. His mother had spent 40 years
        as a transportation experience                        in the profession she had tried to warn her son about.
        designer. After cars no longer                        “It’s so much hard work for so little money. You spend
        needed human drivers, the need                        long evening hours correcting papers by hand, until your
        for car ownership vanished be-                        hand aches from arthritis. You feel you only know your
        cause cars could drive themselves                     students based on their test scores, not by their names
        to pick up people and bring                           or their interests.” He told her the teaching profession
        them to their destination. Trans-                     had changed so much. The routine work was now done
        portation-as-a-Service providers                      by computers – available to teachers and students at
        relied on designers like Kira to differentiate the transport   all times. This freed up time to have personal time with
        experience based on shifting customer needs. She already   students. Teaching and performance testing were no
        had the “Ultimate Business Trip” and “Family Road Trip”   longer designed on the principle that one-size-fits-all.
        designs finished. The designs were now being installed in   Instead the educational system had shifted from con-
        the vehicles, crash tested and ready to be displayed IKEA-  forming student and teachers to predefined standards,
        style with optional test-drives for early adopters. But a new   to developing each person’s unique qualities. After all
        demand had arisen overnight. A group of people were   there is no use in training humans to become biological
        tired of travelling alone and wanted to do more shared   computer algorithms or robots when robots could do the
        rides with other passengers. Not only would this bring   job faster, cheaper and better. Teachers had taken the
        the cost-per-trip down, but it needed Kira to design with   roles of highly esteemed coaches and leaders, and were
        multiple travelers in mind. Could she create a minibus with   compensated much better than his mother had been. But
        diverse café-environment to include in her collection?”  Jose knew he could not convince her of that fact.












                                                Anne Boysen is a professional
                                                futurist specializing in consumer
                                                trends, generational change and
                                                innovation. Drawing on fifteen
                                                years of recording, collecting and
     ChildArt | April-June 2017 ChildArt | April-June 2017  get a better understanding of post-
                                                analyzing relevant trends and data,
                                                Anne tries to help organizations

                                                millennials and what they will
                                                shape and be shaped by. She is the
                                                founder of After the Millennials, a
                                                search-friendly consulting service

                                                around next generation issues and
                                                important future trends.
  12                                            dedicated to building knowledge
  12]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[Healing


           Traumatic

           Pasts Through


           Emancipatory


           Futures


           Narratives




            By Ivana Milojević















                     ur past and our present realities shape the stories of today

                     and yesteryear, and vice versa. So do stories that envision
              better tomorrows. In other words, if we are to create more in-

              clusive and less violent societies, we need to create stories that

              support such change. All this can be, and has been achieved to a
              varying degree, via an accessible, inexpensive yet powerful me-

              dium of storytelling.

              When I was young, we studied historical events in school ex-
              tensively. I was also an avid reader who immensely enjoyed

              books about different time periods and different worlds. At the

              same time, being a sensitive child, I could not understand nor

              stomach all the the horrors described in some of the books I
                                                                                                                     ICAF.ORG ICAF.ORG
              was reading. I’ll tell you about one such horrible narrative…



                                                                                                                    13
                                                                                                                    13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[long, long time ago, many people believed                     e studied the story of ‘the walled-up
        A that it was not possible to build anything,               Wwife’ in school, for its ‘poetic beauty’
        not even a house, let alone significant buildings           and as part of our cultural heritage. I remem-
        such as bridges, castles, wells, monasteries or             ber the story traumatizing me – the human
        citadels, without offering something in return to           cruelty and the imprisonment of a young
        the spirits of the land. The motif of a construc-           mother was too much to bear. What was
        tion whose completion demands a human sacri-                worse, the method of studying the story was
        fice is found in legends and stories across most            to simply memorise it, so there was neither
        of the world, in cultures and societies as diverse          discussion about hidden meanings within it
        as Scandinavian states, Russia, France, Italy,              nor any suggestion how to emotionally pro-
        Greece, Serbia, Bulgaria, Romania, India, Ocea-             cess it.
        nia and Polynesia, China, Japan  and  Sudan.
        Modern builders sometimes come across human                     ast forward many years later. I am a
        or animal skeletons which were built into founda-           Fyoung woman in search of better narra-
        tions centuries ago. and there is some evidence             tives. I no longer accept stories handed to me
        that many of those sacrificed were built into               which portray women as victims of violence.
        foundations alive. Sometimes, a human effigy or a           But I still see violence all around me, not only
        sacred object was placed in the foundation to sub-          in stories but also in ‘real’ life. I especially
        stitute a human victim.                                     bear witness to horrible violence committed

              any buildings in Europe still carry signs of          during the times my society collapsed into
        Mremembrance of those early human victims                   civil war.  To me, ‘the walled-up wife’ story
        by symbolically substituting them with statues              then became a symbol of much that is wrong
        carrying walls and balconies at the ornaments               with our world.
        of the facades. Unfortunate real human victims
        were most commonly slaves, orphans or foreign-                  ast forward, once again, many decades
        ers, but sometimes close members of the family              Flater. With a good friend and colleague of
        were also sacrificed. In the area of the Balkans,           mine, I sat down and wrote a book of stories.
        virtually all societies know of a traditional folk          We chose to rewrite familiar stories, tradi-
        story which tells how a sacrifice of a wife of a            tional and widely known, and replace not only
        master builder or a king took place. Known                  violence present in them, but also gender-
        as ‘the walled-up wife’ legend, the story is                 based and cultural stereotypes.
        entitled in different ways and has many
        versions, but the common theme is as                               ach story we have rewritten liber-
        follows: ‘there were three, nine or twelve                     Eates someone from a prison or some
        masons, or brothers, who decided to                            other form of human cruelty. We freed the
        erect a building, bridge, castle or a cita-                    unnamed young woman from the story I
        del, but whatever they constructed dur-                        described earlier. And we also gave her a
        ing the day collapsed at night; this went                     We wanted to heal the child in us, crying
                                                                      name: Slobodanka, meaning Freedom.
     ChildArt | April-June 2017 ChildArt | April-June 2017  that they needed to make a sacrifice, usu-  younger generations.
        on for weeks or years until they learned
                                                                      out for fairness, justice and peace. More
        ally a first wife who comes to bring a meal
                                                                      importantly, we wanted our dreams for the
        for her husband. After the young woman,
                                                                      future to be reflected in stories we tell to
        also often a new mother, gets built into

        bles down at night.’

  14    the walls, the building no longer crum-
  14]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[Slobodanka
                                              (Freedom)
                                              discussing vari-
                                              ous options and
                                              alternatives to      Slobodanka
                                              violence with        (Freedom)
                                              a very smart       inspecting the
                                              fairy and other   castle that kept
                                              women in her       on crumbling
                                              community.               down.













                                              Slobodanka           Slobodanka
                                              (Freedom) is     (Freedom) using
                                              taken out of the   her education
                                              castle where she   and knowledge to
                                              was built into   properly build the
                                              the walls.               castle.
































        Dr. Ivana Milojević  is a researcher, writer and educator with a trans-disciplinary professional
        background in sociology, gender, peace and futures studies. Since the early 1990s, she has deliv-
        ered speeches and facilitated workshops for governmental institutions, international associations,
                                                                                                                     ICAF.ORG ICAF.ORG
        and non-governmental organizations.



                                                                                                                    15
                                                                                                                    15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Basic Skills


                         to Think


                         Like a


                         Futurist


                         by Sandjar Kozubaev


            Many people ask me what it’s like to be a futurist and
       what skills they would need to become one. The truth is, a
       futurist is not only a profession, but it is also a mindset. It
       is a way you look at the world every day and the way you
       share it with others around you. What many people don’t
       realize is that we are all futurists. As soon as we can speak
       and understand each other, we start imagining what the
       world might be like in the future. As we grow up how-
       ever, this sense of wonder diminishes. It doesn’t disappear
       completely, but there are less and less places and situations
       in which such wondering is encouraged. More often, it is
       discouraged or blocked entirely.

            What I’d like to tell you, is that if you want to think
       like a futurist, or maybe even become a professional futur-
       ist someday, all you need to do is find a way to practice
       these three skills:


       1 What if…?
            This is one of my favorite questions to ask. It helps
       you think about worlds that you can’t even describe.
       What’s great about this question is that you don’t actually
       need to answer it. By asking the question you are already
       beginning to answer it. But it’s harder than you might
       think. Try the following exercise:

             Think of a situation in the world. It could be some-
       thing very simple and close to you, like some event that
       took place in your school. It could also be a news article
       you read online or a story you saw on television. Once you
       chose the situation, ask 10 different “what if” questions
     ChildArt | April-June 2017 ChildArt | April-June 2017  What if adults spent most of their time making art? What
       about it.
            For example, let’s try asking questions about art.


       if nobody made art at all? What if all art was made of only
       one material like clay or paper? What if we used art to



  16   settle all our arguments with each other? These questions
  16]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA["  What if






                                                                                        nobody


                                                                                               made



                                                                                                     art



                                                                                                         at


                                                                                                     all



                                                                                                             ?



                                                                                              -Sandjar Kozubaev







                                                                                                                     ICAF.ORG ICAF.ORG




                                                                                                                    17
                                                                                                                    17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[might sound like silly examples, but they train you to think
        about possibilities that don’t exist today. Most importantly,
        these questions start conversations, which bring us to the next
        skill of a futurist.

        2 Yes and …
              It’s not enough to ask an interesting “What if ”
        question. The next step is to keep up the conver-
        sation which is why we need the “Yes and…”
        exercise. It’s very simple. When someone gives
        you an idea you say “Yes and…” and adds their
        own ideas. Then, someone else does the same
        thing and add their own idea. The main goal
        is to keep adding ideas that inspire other
        ideas until you have tens or even hundreds of
        them. What’s important to know about the
        “Yes and” activity is that it requires generos-
        ity from all the participants. It’s very easy to
        shoot down someone’s idea because you don’t
        think it is good enough, boring, or too fantas-
        tical. But a skilled futurist tries to build on the
        ideas of others and encourages them to do the
        same.

        3 How Might We …?

              Now that we imagined future worlds using “What
        if…?” questions and built on our ideas using “Yes and…”,
        it’s time to imagine possible ways of creating the future we
        want. For that we use “How might we…?” questions. These
        questions turn imaginations into problems that we might
        solve. This is that one final step before we can create real-
        world solutions. Here are some examples for the world of art.
        How might we make art easier to create? How might we cre-
                                                                                        Art by Kuang Myat Zaw (12),
        ate art that speaks in different languages? How might we paint
                                                                                        Myanmar.
        a picture using only words? How might we use mobile phones
        to share artistic experiences? As you probably noticed, these
        questions focus our attention on actions rather than situations.
        Focusing on actions helps us realize what we might do next
        and how we might change the situation from a current one to a
        future, more preferable one.

              The three skills of a futurist I shared above are very easy
        to understand and practice. What is more difficult, is practicing
     ChildArt | April-June 2017 ChildArt | April-June 2017  and citizen. They help us all to work together to create better
        them regularly, and encourage others to do the same. But trust
        me, these skills are very valuable for any future leader, artist


        futures in more imaginative ways.


                    Sandjar Kozubaev is a professional futurist at Sparks Grove, a design agency based
                                       Technology. You can follow Sandjar on Twitter @sandjar.

  18
  18               in Atlanta, Georgia. He is also a PhD student in digital media at Georgia Institute of]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA["Stay a kid forever. Try to stay


                 as open, as
                 geniunely
                  interested in
                  everything,
                   and
                    spontaneous

                    as
                     children."
                      -Dr. Mihai Nadin


                                                                         Scholar





                                                                                 Engineer
        DR.
            MIHAI                                                     Creative




           NADIN                                                                   Thinker











             renowned scholar in fields as diverse as         the flow of creative expression. To facilitate as
        A electrical engineering, computer science,           many choices as possible can be a great stimulus for
        semiotics, and human-computer interaction, Dr.        everyone, whether in education, sports, business or
        Mihai Nadin, since 1985, has devoted his research     self-expression.
        to anticipation, i.e., anticipatory processes that
                                                                  In his much acclaimed 1997 book “The Civili-
        define the living, and how they relate to creativity.
                                                              zation of Illiteracy,” Nadin describes how a society
        He maintains that creative acts are driven by
                                                              of one dominant literacy has progressed towards
        future possibilities. To create something that never
                                                              one of many literacies. The new “languages” are
        existed before cannot be based on reaction. Even a
                                                              more effective because they are more expressive.
        downhill skier or a tennis champion is creative; in
                                                              The languages of rhythm, of color, of texture, of
        returning a very fast serve (and no two serves are
                                                              movement together with those of programming
        ever the same), the player anticipates where the ball
                                                              make possible new forms of creativity. Literature
        is heading.
                                                              and verbal communication will continue to rely on
            Dr. Nadin is interested in the individual and     “natural” language, but new “literacies” will continu-
        society, and how the two can support creative         ously emerge, some through new form of artistic
        processes. Based on his experiences under commu-      expression. The science of sounds and sonification
        nism (but also with consumer society), Dr. Nadin is   (the use of non-speech audio to convey informa-        ICAF.ORG ICAF.ORG
        convinced that heavy regulation or control hinders    tion) is one of them.
                                                                                                                    19
                                                                                                                    19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA["  [Computers are] by far not as good as a CREATIVE human being.                                     "





                                                                                                  - Mihai Nadin




            emiotics is concerned with everything we use to express   forms of creativity, expressed in dancing, singing, writing and
        S ourselves. Of course, creativity is semiotically expressed:   reciting poetry, became  part of him.
        through sounds and images, or through the symbols of
        mathematics. Knowledge of semiotics led him to study the   After finishing high school, and still spurred by a desire
        works of Brancusi, the famous Romanian sculptor, and other   to understand creativity, he studied engineering and computer
        artists engaged in creative acts (theater, dance, painting, music,   science at Bucharest Polytechnic. One of his mentors, a lead-
        literature, etc.).                                     ing mathematician confused by Nadin’s “crazy” idea, got him
                                                               access to the computing center of the University. Nadin began
                                                               to learn how to create images with the computer at a time
            Having worked in this field all his life, Dr. Nadin remains
                                                               when studying computer sciences and working with comput-
        firm in his belief that computers—as spectacular as the
                                                               ers was revolutionary and regarded with suspicion.
        development of digital technology might be—are by “far not
        as good as a creative human being.” Computers and their pro-
                                                                  Dr. Nadin has authored more than 250 publications.
        gramming languages are the intermediary, the “agent” through
                                                               He holds a post-doctoral degree in Philosophy, Logic, and
        which feelings, emotions, thoughts and ideas are expressed.
                                                               the Theory of Science from the University of Munich. Since
        Computers support human creativity in ways never before
                                                               2004, he has been the director of the Institute for Research in
        considered possible.
                                                               Anticipatory Systems at the University of Texas, Dallas. Most
                                                               of his work has focused on human creativity, how to discern
            Born in 1938 in the medieval city of Brasov, Romania,
                                                               and analyze it and how to inspire others to be creative. He
        Mihai Nadin lived (and survived) through the Nazi terror of
                                                               maintains that anticipation, the main subject of his research,
        World War II. Two memories from this time left a lasting im-
                                                               drives creativity.
        pression: during machine-gun fire from airplanes bombing the
        city, his mother shielded him  with her own body as people
                                                                     His advice to ChildArt’s young readers is to follow
        ran to the wooded hills for shelter. He stayed in the
                                                                         their own instincts, to believe that each is unique,
        hospital for a year after a German military truck
                                                                             to embrace difference, and to pursue their
        ran over him. There is no bitterness in his
                                                                                individual creativity. Sameness destroys
        voice as he recalls this incident: “There
                                                                                  creativity. Even though it is impor-
        is no person who I met in those days,
                                                                                    tant to seek interaction with others,
        absolutely none, regardless of their
                                                                                     interaction should never result in
        religion or who they were—men,
                                                                                      conformity but in defining your
        women, old, young—who
                                                                                      own path. In the words of the
        wouldn’t try their best to give
                                                                                      great American poet Robert
        me a chance.”
                                                                                      Frost: “Two paths diverged in a
                                                                                        wood, and I took the one less
            He grew up in a city
                                                                                          travelled by, and that has
        with people from diverse
                                                                                           made all the difference.”
        backgrounds and identities:
        Romanian, Hungarian,
                                                                                            And his advice to grown-
        German, Bessarabian, Polish,
                                                                                           ups: “Stay a kid forever, try
        some Christian, some Jewish,
     ChildArt | April-June 2017 ChildArt | April-June 2017  workers, ideologues, artists… At a   spontaneous as  children are!”
                                                                                         to stay as open, as genuinely
        professionals, peasants, teachers,
                                                                                         interested in everything, and
        very early age he believed in human
        diversity and the expression of
        individuality. He grew-up fascinated by
                                                                                              By Martina Woebcken,
        the uniqueness and diversity of every
                                                                                          ChildArt contributing editor
  20    human being. The many different                                                          and freelance writer.
  20]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[MAPPING







                                                                                                  the



                                                  FUTURES







                                                                     With VIDEO







                                                                        Dr. Lisa Hasler Waters









           “Quiet on the set!” shouted one of the

           students as she steadied the camera on her
           co-stars. The YouTubers Club elective had

           just started and a slew of students had

           just poured into the media lab, ready
           to video, edit and upload to the

           Club’s YouTube Channel. Some

           of the students were preparing

           silly comedy shows. Others were

           creating do-it-yourself videos for
           how to draw or make songs, and some

           were recording themselves playing Mine-

           Craft, calling out strategies, epic fails and wins.
           But not Vlad. He was busy creating his "futures of
                                                                                                                     ICAF.ORG ICAF.ORG
           the world" video using online map-making tools.


                                                                                                                    21
                                                                                                                    21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[was a child. But much of what Vlad knows about history
              lad K is a sixth grader at an independent school
                                                            comes from his grandparents, who were from Russia and
              in northern Virginia, who attends my YouTuber’s
                                                            the Ukraine. They have told him many stories about their
       V Club elective class. My name is Mrs. Waters, and
                                                            life in eastern Europe and the hardships they experienced
       this Club is one of my favorite classes to hold because
                                                            while living under Soviet rule. Vlad’s Russian heritage is
       of the freedom students have to share their creativity
                                                            an important part of his life. He speaks Russian and has
       through videos they produce. Vlad has a twin sister, who
                                                            a connection to the land and its peoples. He has traveled
       is also in the YouTubers Club but she works on music
                                                            there a few times and speaks often with his grandparents
       video creations with her friend. Vlad signed up specifi-
                                                            about their Russian histories. As such, he is concerned
       cally for the Club so that he could work on his futures
                                                            over the fate of Russians in this current world and his
       mapping videos. Futures mapping videos are videos that
                                                            worries play out in his mapping videos. These videos
       use evolving images of maps of the world, in which the
                                                            imagine a bleak future for Russia and many other parts
       border lines morph and depict varying world scenarios.
                                                            of the world as continued nationalism rises and devolves
       These scenarios play out over a timeline, which tends
                                                            into dictatorships.
       to span 10 to 50 years or more. The videos are narrated
       using text and music is included to give the viewer an   Because of the dystopian views many of Vlad’s videos
       idea of the forces impacting the changing maps. Vlad   had been evolving into, I challenged him to think of
       carefully constructs the evolving maps, text, and music   alternative futures. Specifically, I asked him to think of
       is added to ensure that the viewer understands the tone   a more optimistic future and also his own aspirational,
       of the emerging future. You can view Vlad’s videos using   or dream future. This really intrigued Vlad. He had to
       the link provided here: Alternate Future of the World:                                      emerge from bleak futures he had been imagining and
       Episode 2, 4th Edition.                              allow himself to find ways to imagine brighter outcomes.
                                                            I encouraged him to find things happening in the world
          Vlad’s fascination with the future began with history!
                                                            that seemed hopeful and to come back to our class after
       He loves reading history books and searching for histori-
                                                            the weekend to weave these views into his videos.
       cal information on the Internet. His favorite historical re-
       sources are the history books he got from his dad because   As you can imagine, Vlad rose to the occasion! But
       these books his dad had himself received as gifts when he   how? Well, he reflected on two particular news items that
                                                            gave him hope. The first was news related to a technologi-
                                                            cal breakthrough that he learned about in which scientists
                                                            are one-step closer to being able to clone a Woolly Mam-
                                                            moth. Another piece of news struck Vlad as a positive
                                                            sign for the future. He had read that recently a jaguar had
                                                            crossed the border from Mexico into Texas. Scientists,
                                                            who were able to tag the animal, said that it appeared to
                                                             be sticking around and making a home in Texas. Vlad
                                                               said, “This makes me happy about the future because
                                                                  it gives me hope that the wall isn’t there and so
                                                                      animals can roam freely.” This vision spoke to
     ChildArt | April-June 2017 ChildArt | April-June 2017  Will science     to pass.
                                                                             Vlad as a symbol of the distant future
                                                                             in which Trump’s wall does not come
                                         bring back
                                                                                For Vlad, that speaks volumes
                                         the  Woolly
                                                                             about how the negativity that exists in
                                         Mammoth?
                                                                             this current political climate does not



  22
  22                                                                       become fully realized. His dream fu-]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[now call America: He explains that, “Native
                               Vlad K, a 6th grader at an independent
                                                                        Americans decide that they don’t like it and
                               school in Northern Virginia.
                                                                        that they’ve been hurt for so long. So, they
                               Watch Vlad's video here.
                                                                        create a new system, a new government, a
                                                                        new culture and they locate between the east
                                                                        coast and the Rockies.”
                                                                            He goes on to explain that at that same
                                                                        time, “My idea for everything west of the
                                                                        Rockies, from Alaska to Cape Horn, would
                                                                        be a California revolution that would be
                                                                        more socialist.” Further, he adds, “Or the
                                                                        very worst case scenario, is that these people
                                                                        do something entirely terrible...like the red
                                                                        button being pushed!” In this scenario, he
                                                                        imagines,“Everyone is for himself and the
                                                                        only good thing is that there is no real orga-
                                                                        nized war, just anarchy.” When Vlad “flips the
                                                                        clock 1,000 years” forward, he sees a single
                                                                        giant empire, a country with an emperor
                                                                        similar to the Roman emperors. These vivid
     ture is one in which animals do not continue to go extinct.        and broad imaginings come to life through
     Using these weak signals, Vlad set to work on his video to
                                                            Vlad’s mapping videos.
     add elements of the positive and aspirational futures he’s
     imagining.                                                Vlad likes thinking about the future he says because, “I
                                                            am a kid and I like thinking about my  life in the future.”
        There are of course many ways to creatively express
                                                            He also believes that kids should always think, because then
     ideas about the future but Vlad chose videos for a number
                                                            they can make more informed decisions to improve their
     of reasons. Mainly, he says, it is because he is afraid to speak
                                                            lives and the lives of those around them, and the world at
     in public. Also, he believes that most people get their infor-
                                                            large.  He believes that all kids should be inspired to think
     mation and entertainment from videos, and less from books
                                                            about the future and that the way to do this is to make sure
     or things in print. Additionally, he believes that videos can
                                                            it is fun. He points to his video experiences as being fun
     really capture people’s attention. The ideas for his videos
                                                            and recognizes that all kids like watching videos and many
     came from a number of other mapping videos on YouTube
                                                            would like making them too. He is also about to start work-
     he had seen. From these, he said his inspiration to start
                                                            ing in Scratch, the free coding program from MIT Lifelong
     making his own video came as he began watching the news
                                                            Kindergarten, to create his future mapping in code.
     about the presidential election. He said, “At first, during the
     presidential election, I wanted to make a tale if we made the
     wrong decision.”
        For him, the future is very interesting: He explained    When she's not
                                                             dreaming about the
     that, “...when it’s world peace, all the boundaries stay the
                                                              future, Lisa Hasler
     same, but when there is a time like now, when there are   Waters, PhD, works
     these people that threaten the peace, then it becomes really   as a technology in-
                                                             tegrator and coding
     interesting to document what they might do.” He views this
                                                               teacher at a JK-12
     scenario building as a form of storytelling. For example, he   school in Northern
     imagines that a, “... giant war would lead to so much change   Virginia and she is
                                                               adjunct faculty at
     that all the countries involved in the war would entirely
                                                             George Mason Uni-
     collapse and then a new country would emerge.” In this   versity's College of
     case, his tale ventures to what it would be like in what we   Education and Hu-                                 ICAF.ORG ICAF.ORG
                                                              man Development.
                                                                                                                    23
                                                                                                                    23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[Dr. Bishop is the Founder and Executive Director
                                                                                  of Teach the Future, an organization whose
                                                                                mission is to encourage and support educators
                                                                                 who want to include futures thinking in their
                                                                                           classes and schools at all levels.



















                          Dr. Peter Bishop

       E    very good story begins with a mystery which often   mock-up of the Space Station; pilots play with simula-

                                                              tors that give them the experience of flying while staying
            means something is missing.  So this story, my story,
                                                              on the ground. I would love to play with those machines
            is to describe what I believe is missing in school.
                                                              myself because it sounds like great fun.  And astronauts
        School is a lot of things – subjects, classes, teachers,
                                                              and pilots tell us that it is.
        books, homework, tests, etc.  It’s also a chance to be with
        your friends and maybe get a little exercise.  But what   People play sports for fun, from the pick-up games in the
        school doesn’t have is fun.  School is not supposed to be   park to the Super Bowl.  People play an instrument in
        fun.  It’s serious and important, but not fun.        the orchestra or a character in a play for fun.  And they
                                                              are learning at the same time.  They are playing to learn-
        What is fun, and when do we have fun?  We usually
                                                              -learning what to do, how to act, what to be in various
        have fun when we play.  When we were little, we played
                                                              situations that they will confront in the game or the play.
        outside, making up games and stories with our friends.
                                                              They practice, and practice, and practice all the while
        When we got older we played video games and sports.
                                                              getting better at what they do.  A famous author once
        And even older, we play golf or bridge.  Play is fun.
                                                              discovered that even the best “players” in sports, music or
                                                              whatever, have practiced over 10,000 hours before they
        We do play at school and have fun doing it, but it is
                                                              became really good.  Practicing 10,000 hours at 4 hours a
        usually after school.  We play an instrument in the band,
                                                              day every day of the year would take 2,500 days or almost
        character in a play or a position on a sports team.  Those
                                                              7 years!  That’s a lot of practice.  Is it all fun?  Maybe not.
        are fun for those who choose to play that way.                                                                Art by Giada Kuka (10), Albania
                                                              Sometimes it’s hard and frustrating, but it’s rarely boring.
        But during the school day?  No play, not much fun.  But   Those players have a goal--to win or be appreciated-- and
        does it have to be that way?  Some believe it does.  School  that is fun! And it’s fun to challenge yourself—to make
        is serious and important.  It prepares us for a serious life   10 baskets in a row (or a 100!); to play music without er-
        with serious adults in a serious job and raising a serious   rors, just once; to recite Shakespeare so the audience can
        family.  No fun there!                                understand it.
        But why can’t we prepare for serious things by playing?    And of course, for many, art is fun—drawing, painting,
     ChildArt | April-June 2017 ChildArt | April-June 2017  actors than the performance on Saturday night.  There’s   FUN IS GOOD
        In fact, we can and we do.  There’s nothing more serious
                                                              coloring, building, sculpting.  I believe  you are one of
        to football players than the game on Friday night or to
        nothing more serious than astronauts running the Space
        Station or pilots guiding a jet across the ocean.  Are they
        prepared?  Very much so.  Are they prepared by sitting in
        classrooms, listening to teachers, doing homework, and
        of their time they are playing.  Astronauts play with a

  24    taking tests?  In fact, yes, but not most of the time.  Most
  24]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[those people because you are reading this magazine.  You   were the young people?  Why weren’t we talking to high
        get joy and fulfillment in using your creativity to see what   school and young college students about the future they
        you can produce, to make it better the next time, to be   were heading to?  No good reason, except that teachers
        appreciated for what you have done.  That is fun!  So, art,   are already required to teach so much else, particularly
        music and maybe physical education are fun for many   about the past, that they don’t have time to teach about
        during the school day, but is that all?               the future.  And they don’t know how to do it anyway.
        Can math be fun?  Can history or science?  It is for some
                                                              So I created an organization called Teach the Future
        and good teachers make it so, but not that often.  But I
                                                              that helps teachers and schools put futures thinking into
        know a class that would be fun for everyone.  That class
                                                              their curriculum.  It’s hard work for me.  I have had to
        is about the future.  The future is fun – science fiction, for
        one.  Any good story is fun, in books or movies.  What is   learn to do many things that I never had to do as a col-
        going to happen?  How will it turn out?               lege professor – motivating people, raising money, man-
        That is fun.                                                        aging projects.  It is a challenge, and that
        But when do we have fun thinking and      "Why can't                is fun, just like the artist who aspires to
        talking about the future in school?  Un-                            be better or even great.
                                                  we prepare
        fortunately, hardly ever.  Teachers are
        preparing you for the future, but they
        have not told you about the future you are   for serious
        heading towards.  It’s not their fault.  They
        don’t know how to teach about the future      things by
        because they were never taught how to        playing?"
        when they were in school or even when
        they were preparing to be teachers.  Their
                                                          - Dr. Peter Bishop
        teachers didn’t teach about the future so
        they didn’t learn it or teach it either.
        Teaching about the futures seems impos-
        sible.  So many things are happening, and even more
        could happen in the future.  How are we to tell which
        one is the right one?  How are we to know what will
        happen?
        Surprise!  You can’t know what will happen, and don’t
        need to.  Really?  Then how can we talk about it?  The
        trick is not to talk about the future, as if it were just
        one thing—the one thing that will  happen.  No, we
 Art by Giada Kuka (10), Albania  have a good reason in the form of a good story to tell   And I believe that studying the future in school would be
        should talk about the futures, plural, all of the things
        that could happen.  And that’s fun, as long as you
        about how things could come about.  We call that story a
        ‘scenario’, a description of a plausible future.  Shouldn’t we
                                                              fun, too, exploring different possibilities, hearing
        have classes in school that develop scenarios, that let us
                                                              what others are thinking about and creating, and ulti-
        think about and discuss the world we are
        heading towards?
                                                              difference in the future.  I’m not sure how to make math
        I am a college professor, and I have taught about the fu-
                                                              or science fun for every student, but I strongly believe
        ture at the University of Houston for 30 years.  I managed   mately committing to a goal and a path for making a
        the first degree program in futures studies that began way   that studying the future would be fun for most, if not all
        back in the 1970s.  When I retired from the university, I   students.  So let’s play, let’s have fun, and let’s learn
        realized that I had been speaking only to adults.  Where   about the future together!
 FUN IS GOOD                                                                                                         ICAF.ORG ICAF.ORG












                                                                                                                    25
                                                                                                                    25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Chips and Tips for the Future:

        A Conversation with




        Dr. Dugan of Intel











            nventor, artist, winner of an Emmy.               the human body and the way it functions.
            Dr. Thérèse Dugan is a jack of all trades         She could not wait to grow up and become
        Iand master of quite a lot. Combining her             a pediatrician. In elementary and middle
        passion for science and technology, art and           school she was enrolled in a science enrich-
        design, and child development, she is a re-           ment class, where she was able to do hands-
        searcher and educator at Intel—the world’s            on activities such as building robots and
        largest semiconductor chip manufacturer.              participating in science fairs. She also had
                                                              the opportunity to be a part of a program
             “I was always really interested in chil-         that promoted girls and minorities who were
        dren and their thought processes; how and
                                                              interested in the medical field, taking biology
        when they start to become creative and criti-         and chemistry courses at a nearby medical
        cal thinkers. I also feel that it’s important to
                                                              college during her high school years.
        observe how technology affects a child grow-
        ing up.” Thérèse obtained her undergradu-                Although science was a big part of her
        ate degree in filmmaking at the University            life, Thérèse decided to pursue her passion in
        of Kansas and went on to pursue a PhD in              film making and the arts in college. Thérèse
        Learning Science and Human Development                graduated from the Governor’s School for
        at the University of Washington.                      the Arts magnet school program in Norfolk,
                                                              Virginia and worked as a photographer and
            Since her father worked for different cit-
        ies as an urban planner, Thérèse moved fre-           documentary film maker in college. After
        quently from state to state as a child. She also      graduating with her film degree, she then
        became interested in all forms of art. One            went on to work in television and news pro-
        of her main inspirations was her art teacher,         duction, including a nightly news broadcast,
        Mrs. Wyman, who had such a profound ef-               as well as, aiding in the production of a clas-
        fect that Thérèse wrote a dedication to her in  sic movie show, a news magazine, and politi-
        her Ph.D. dissertation. “She was very good            cal forum for the PBS station in Oklahoma.
        at helping us apply what we were learning in  “One of the things I realized is how powerful
        our classrooms to artistic and creative things.  media is in swaying people’s opinions. My
        For example, if we were learning about Japan  views might not have been the general con-
        in our social studies class, she would try to
     ChildArt | April-June 2017 ChildArt | April-June 2017  ing an interest in the sciences. When quite   lenge the viewers to hear out other people’s
                                                              sensus for the conservative place I was work-
        incorporate that into our art lessons.”
                                                              ing and living in, but I always tried to chal-
            Aside from art, Thérèse found herself tak-
                                                              stories. I think that’s the way people become
                                                              more accepting, and it made me interested in
        young she had dislocated her shoulder and
                                                              learning about others from a psychological
        upon seeing her x-rays and hearing the doc-


  26
  26    tor’s explanations, she became fascinated by          perspective.”]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Chips and Tips for the Future:  WWashington and working at the   in the traditional classroom setting in the
                                                                 Thérèse sees many changes taking place
               hile studying at the University of
 A Conversation with  Learning in Informal and Formal Envi-   near future. She predicts that education will

                                                              become much more mobile and ubiquitous
        ronments (LIFE) Center (an NSF-funded
        Science of Learning center at the University
                                                              and integrate more modern technologies
 Dr. Dugan of Intel  of Washington, Stanford, and SRI) and the   such as smart phones, laptops, wearable tech-
        Teacher Education Program, she took cross-
                                                              nology, and tablets. She also believes teachers
        disciplinary courses in the engineering school  could become more like guides to their stu-
        in human-computer interaction (HCI). “To
                                                              ing journeys. She hopes that schools will find
        be a good researcher, I really needed to un-          dents’ individualized and personalized learn-
        derstand children and technology from not             alternatives to rigorous standardized testing
        just a psychological or educational point of          and create more formative ways of assess-
        view but also an engineering point of view.”          ment. One possible path is a future where
        Her first move was to Nokia Research Cen-             schools invest in more immersive, hands-on
        ter in Palo Alto for user experience research.        experiences for the students, who also need
        There she designed research projects follow-          to learn vital career readiness skills. Thérèse
        ing how preschoolers used tablets, touch-             also believes that the boundaries dividing
        screen technology, remote communication,              creativity, the arts, analytics, and innovation
        and augmented reality on smartphones.                 will blur and cease to be quite so important.
            At Intel, she has worked on a team called         She strongly believes in the reciprocal nature
                                                              of innovation and creativity: one cannot hap-
        Intel Education (now Public Sector), which
        helps design and influence sales of laptops,          pen without the other.
        tablets, 2-in-1s, and other educational tech-
        nology solutions to governments and schools
        around the world. She also invents and
        designs smart toys and games.
        “Intel creates a lot of reference
                                                                                               Dr. Dugan is Senior
        designs, and we work with ex-
                                                                                                 Design Researcher
        ternal partners to create products
                                                                                               and Product Design
        that consumers are now able to
                                                                                                 Lead at Intel. Her
        see on shelves and in stores. We
                                                                                                 comments are her
        work with digital media partners
                                                                                                own and do not re-
        and partners in the toy and game                                                       flect the views of the
        industry. There’s a lot of co-design                                                             company.
        and co-creation that happens through
        Intel’s partnerships.”

            Thérèse’s life turned out a bit differ-
        ently than she had planned when she was
        a child. “I did end up becoming a doctor,
        just in a different way, and a scientist just
        in a different way. Without having had a
        strong educational background, the endless
        support of others, especially my family, and
        a number of fortuitous interactions, I don’t
        think I would be at Intel.” She believes that
        having a strong sense of adventure and em-
        pathy towards others really helps drive her
                                                                                                                     ICAF.ORG ICAF.ORG
        creativity and innovation.


                                                                                                                    27
                                                                                                                    27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[?
 Luna’s eyes jolted open as she awoke from un-
        Creating Your Future
 consciousness, for a moment she felt dazed


                                                                                      By Marianne Solomon
 and unaware of her surroundings.  Sudden-
            Casper’s family ambled

             to their FusionKar4 and
 ly, panic-stricken shrieks and wails of ter-
                                                                “We were so excited that we
             instructed the holographic
                                                               didn’t even realize we were
 ror pierced the air.  The sheer magnitude of
              display, “Home.”  (TOPIC:
                                                              creating babies smarter
                                                             than ourselves.”   (TOPIC:
               Surveillance Society)
                                                            Enhancing Human
 the earthquake-tsunami split had left abso-
                                                            Potential)

 lute devastation across the land.  High-rise


           Nano-particles were
 una’s eyes jolted open as she awoke from un-
            stored in all nutritional
             syringes used for synthetic
 consciousness, for a moment she felt dazed
              nourishment.  (TOPIC:

 and unaware of her surroundings.  Suddenly,
                Processed Foods)


 panic-stricken shrieks and wails of terror



                                                     that

 CHOOSERESEARCHWRITECHOOSERESEARCHWRITE



             hese opening sentences come from cham-           extending what is currently possible into futuris-
        Tpion student writings in the Junior Division  tic story lines.
        (grades 4 – 6) of the Scenario Writing Inter-           Students who love to write creative stories,
        national Competition, an annual competition
                                                              students who fantasize possible futures, and stu-
        offered by Future Problem Solving Program             dents who think outside the box will be attracted
        International.  A scenario, as defined by Future      to Scenario Writing.  Students who generate
        Problem Solving (FPS), is a short creative story      various, unimagined situations that could come
     ChildArt | April-June 2017 ChildArt | April-June 2017  important global topics or issues into the future.   dinary - will excel in this art form.  Beyond the
        (maximum of 1500 words) designed to project
                                                              true - predictions outside the realm of the or-

                                                              annual competition, Scenario Writing offers
        The Scenario Writing competition is ideal for
        students interested in developing possible futures  an opportunity for students in grades 4 - 12 to
        using the sci-fi genre.  FPS offers an opportunity  develop creative story lines that address criti-


                                                              humankind might be affected.
        writing, and want to develop possible futures by
  28    for students who love challenge, enjoy creative       cal global issues and devise a plot showing how
  28]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[?
 Luna’s eyes jolted open as she awoke from un-
 consciousness, for a moment she felt dazed



 and unaware of her surroundings.  Sudden-  Each year students choose from


        five provided topics, research it,
 ly, panic-stricken shrieks and wails of ter-  imagine it 20-30 years into the

        future, and develop a story line.
 ror pierced the air.  The sheer magnitude of   For example, students might re-

        search the topic "Identity Theft"
 the earthquake-tsunami split had left abso-  and the many ways this crime ex-
        ists today, imagining what identity
        theft could look like in 20 years.
 lute devastation across the land.  High-rise   How have governments improved
        – or what has become even worse
        than what is experienced today?
 una’s eyes jolted open as she awoke from un-  The topic “3D Printing” provides



 consciousness, for a moment she felt dazed   an opportunity to use the imagi-
        nation to think about what future
        might be possible by building on
 and unaware of her surroundings.  Suddenly,   what is happening today.  The

        student writer must research the
        chosen topic, but the creative spirit
 panic-stricken shrieks and wails of terror    of the student who loves to write

        is the main ingredient needed for
 that   WRITE  success.













              hen FPS was created, Dr. Torrance             aged to stretch their thoughts through the use of
      Wwanted to create a means for students to             a variety of creative and critical thinking tools.
      realistically jump into a possible future, using re-  Students look at the many aspects of the topic,
      search to determine the actual situations of today
                                                            like the psychological effects, the effects upon
      and move into realistically predictions of where
                                                            government and law, or economics and basic
      humankind might advance.  Students involved
                                                            needs.  No stone is left unturned as the student
      in Scenario Writing must stretch the mind to
      generate all the various possibilities that could     develops an appropriate theme and creates the
                                                                                                                     ICAF.ORG ICAF.ORG
      happen in many categories.  They are encour-          storyline.



                                                                                                                    29
                                                                                                                    29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[Now, enjoy this opening paragraph from a Junior      In addition, FPS now offers a competition entitled
                           th
        Division scenario (5  Place, 2016),                   Scenario Performance as a way to involve and celebrate
                                                              students who have a knack for storytelling.  The annual
        from the topic Recovering from Natural Disasters:
                                                              topics are presented to spark creative presentation of an
          Luna’s eyes jolted open as she awoke from uncon-    imagined story within the future, providing an opportu-
          sciousness, for a moment she felt dazed and un-     nity for students to share their creative thinking through
          aware of her surroundings.  Suddenly, panic-strick-  the telling of an imagined future.
          en shrieks and wails of terror pierced the air.  The
          sheer magnitude of the earthquake-tsunami split        We hope that students will find these artistic offer-
                                                              ings exciting and join with fellow writers and perform-
          had left absolute devastation across the land.  High-
                                                              ers around the world.  Visit fpspi.org to locate specific
          rise buildings that once were spectacular and mon-
                                                              information.
          strous in size now lay in crumpled heaps of rubble.
          And air transportation vehicles lay in mounds of
          twisted metal many still containing passengers who
          were taken by the fierce flooding and unable to exit
          the vehicles.



                                  th
            And this ending from a 5  place writing on the topic
        of Recovering from Natural Disasters:

          The ‘Queen Bee’ quickly took in the information and
          considered the available options.
          It is imperative to control global warming levels to
          ensure the survival of the planet.  Humankind has
          and continues to damage the ozone layer, deplete
          natural resources, and destroy the environment.
          Solution: Severe and immediate restriction required
          on all human activity.  Place all under surveillance
          and limit freedom.
          The ‘Queen Bee’ silently summoned her army.















     ChildArt | April-June 2017 ChildArt | April-June 2017                     Marianne Solomon has served as








                                                                               Executive Director of Future Problem

                                                                               SPI) since 2005.
  30
  30                                                                           Solving Program International (FP-]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Afghan Kids: Their Future and Ours


                                                                                           By Stefan Frischauf



                 n architect and engineer from                quote: “No one wants to become some-
                 Dusseldorf, I came to Kabul in               thing – everyone already wants to be
        A 2009 as a “rebuilding aide.” My                     somebody.”
        work in Kabul over the next two years
                                                                 What kind of future do the Afghan
        was the biggest professional and human
                                                              children paint? What hopes, expectations
        challenge of my life, and my most painful
                                                              and fears do they express? Are they al-
        failure.
                                                              ready somebody or still discovering?
            "Kids can paint – it just drives you cra-
        zy!” says the young house painter in “The                What are these kid’s dreams like? Do
        New Sorrows of Young W.”—a novel by                   their parents and elders may believe that
        Ulrich Plenzdorf in which he draws paral-             sidewalks in Western cities are paved with
        lels between his own life in East Germany  gold? Or, do they simply hate “Western
        in the 1970s and that of the protagonist              things?” Do children in Murad Khane, a
        in Goethe’s 1774 book “The Sorrows of                 part of Kabul’s own town, like the three in            ICAF.ORG ICAF.ORG
        Young Werther.”  One might add Goethe’s  the photo above, feel alienated too?

                                                                                                                    31
                                                                                                                    31]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[nd, who cares about their dreams
                                                                             of warm and safe nests, places to
                                                                     A feel hugged and loved, not to turn
                                                                     into illusions, pink clouds shattering into
                                                                     millions of pieces when falling on the hard
                                                                     earth?
                                                                         Reality can be much harder, much
                                                                     stronger in its impact than anything we
                                                                     might have expected before. But, it is also
                                                                     a challenge to ask anyone to find good and
                                                                     safe “future-proof ” solutions.

                                                                         Having read books about Afghanistan,
                                                                     I believed I was well prepared for what to
                                                                     expect. I wasn’t. We, in the West, are not
                                                                     ready at all to build up hopes in war torn
                                                                     countries, hopes of the weakest members
                                                                     of splintered communities—children and
                                                                     their fragile existence in a world overload-
                                                                     ed with grown-ups who think they know
                                                                     everything.
                                                                         Street kids like these three (to the
                                                                     left) with the “Afghan Reichstag” in Kabul
                                                                     behind them – what idea do they have
                                                                     about “freedom and democracy”? What
        The Darulaman Palace behind
                                                                     might they expect from “education” – and
        the kids was built in the
                                                                     “perspectives for building up a profession-
        1920s by French and Ger-
                                                                     al career”? Many of my younger Afghan
        man architects and engineers
        but lies abandoned as it was                                 colleagues now have far fewer kids than
        destroyed again and again in                                 their parents because of safety and secu-
        recent decades.                                              rity concerns, and perspectives regarding
                                                                     quality of life and education. Children are
                                                                     a liability in war times.

                                                                         Kabul is an extreme example of cities
                                                                     at the brink because of conflict and popu-
                                                                     lation growth due to rural exodus. As the
                                                                     fastest growing city in Central Asia which
                                                                     is already home to 5 or 6 million people
                                                                     after 37 years of war and insecurity, Kabul
                                                                     suffers more than many other places from
                                                                     a destroyed infrastructure and an increas-
     ChildArt | April-June 2017 ChildArt | April-June 2017           Angeles-based sociologist Mike Davis
                                                                     ingly harmful , “slum ecology”—as Los

                                                                     would call it.
                                                                         The reconstruction policy following
                                                                     the 2001 Western invasion aggravated
 9 9                                                                 many existing problems. For example,
        9 9 99
                                                                     increased private drilling for water caused
  32
  32]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[consumption to rise, but no sustainable
         urban wastewater management was provid-
         ed. Decreased rain and snow have caused
         a dramatic drop in the water table and its
         riverbed is now mostly dry. Many inhabit-
         ants call the Kabul River the “city’s biggest
         toilet”.  A dysfunctional waste removal sys-
         tem adds to that: plastic packaging clogs
         the surface drains. The stench of hydrogen
         sulfide caused by human waste in the city`s
         slums like Murad Khane mostly harms the
         weakest--children and expecting mothers.

            These days with the “refugee crisis” in
         Europe, many people, some from Afghani-
         stan, are coming to Germany. An urgent
         need for change has arrived in Central
         Europe. We need fresh perspectives that
         provide us, and them, chances for a life
         together which is more promising and not
         disappointing. More community builders
         are needed and legislation that protects
         and saves people, not banks or warlords.
            My own project, like many of other
         Westerners, offered a chance for "the
         West" to finally show that "we" were ca-
                                                                            "What kind of future
         pable of arrive at a concept for building up
         the war torn country. Places like Afghani-                                    do the Afghan
         stan teach us a lot about ourselves, and
         children there mirror our deepest fears.                                   children paint?"
            The future of our societies needs
                                                                                             -Stefan Frischauf
         schooling for international and inter-
         cultural development. Only this can bring
         us a step closer towards the future as a
         promise. The future is just a small window
         of opportunity in the continuous stream of
         time between the past and the present. We
         owe a brighter future to our kids and the
         children of Afghanistan.










           Stefan Frischauf worked in Kabul for two years in 2009 and 2010, and is back in
            Düsseldorf, Germany, working as an architect and engineer, and being a loving
                           father to his 15-year-old daughter and two sons, six and two.                             ICAF.ORG ICAF.ORG
                                  www.anyupae.com/english/book-2-fragment-fractal/

                                                                                                                    33
                                                                                                                    33]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[CHILDREN IMAGINING THE FUTURE

        Art from the ICAF Collection





















                                                                “I hope that technological developments do not destroy or alter
                                                                nature, with all its beauty and splendor... I want to show different
                                                                kinds of people, of different races and characteristics, living and
                                                                working together. ... I try to show an optimistic point of view,
                                                                a world in which discrimination and destruction do not exist.”
                                                                - Alejandro Goldzycher (9), Argentina.
















        “My Africa is crying…” Permanent Sam Wilmot (11), Liberia.




















     ChildArt | April-June 2017 ChildArt | April-June 2017  "Future is like an open book, for you to write."   “Because of pollution the buildings are bending down.” - Masa








                                                                Budimir (12), Croatia.
        - Anna Langer (12), Germany.


  34
  34]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[“As a girl and a female, I will become
           a woman and carry a child, giving
         him care and love. The bird represents
         peace, the pregnant mother represents
             the present, and the baby is the
           future peace. The flowers represent
          protection of the environment (past/
         present/future).”- Lotfieh Mohamed El
                     Masri (11), Lebanon.




































     “My idea was to create an image that showed the end of violence between
     people and between nations – the end of all forms of violence. ... To show
     the transformation of the world into a place full of love and peace, there is
     nothing better than the shape of a heart.” - Anna Carolina dos Santos Israel
     (12), Brazil.





                                                              “I want to see different cultures joining together to make peace throughout
                                                              the world, I want to see kids reaching their goals and dreams in life, I
                                                              want to see technology help us and not hurt our planet, and most of all I
                                                              want to see kids getting the education they need and an equal chance in   ICAF.ORG ICAF.ORG
                                                              life.” - Shellie Lee Korth (12), United States.

                                                                                                                    35
                                                                                                                    35]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[“I know not with what weapons World War III will be fought, but
                                                         World War IV will be fought with sticks and stones.”

                                                                                              - Albert Einstein























            ICAF’s two-decades long experience serving        from the Arts Olympiad, art submissions are
        American children and their peers around the          accepted only by 8- to 12-year-olds.
        world confirms the importance of creativity and
        empathy for sustainable prosperity and peace.             The Arts Olympiad winners will convene at
                                                              the 6th World Children’s Festival (WCF) in June
            This summer ICAF launches its 6th Arts            2019 on The National Mall in Washington for a
        Olympiad, an important national and global            three-day long transformative educational experi-
        initiative to foster creativity and imbue it with     ence. The young artists will collaborative produce
        empathy. The Arts Olympiad Lesson Plan                “Children’s Earth Flag” for the first human mis-
        introduces students to the “Artist-Athlete Ideal”     sion to Mars. Their talents will bring the human
        of the creative mind and healthy body. This           race together to celebrate Creativity, Diversity,
        paradigm liberates a natural tendency toward          and Unity.
        creativity and good health by linking imagination
        with embodiment. Self-image as artist-athlete             Regardless of how dismal sometimes the out-
        solidifies when students render it into personal      look may seem, ICAF is there to paint a brighter
        works of art. Though any student can benefit          future with you.






           ENGAGE                             CONTRIBUTE                          FOLLOW US



           The ICAF invites your participation in the   Please adopt the ICAF as your charity   FACEBOOK.com/ICAF.org
           6th Arts Olympiad, the world’s largest art   of choice by making a tax-deductible
           program for schoolchildren. Commencing   donation today. You can support the    TWITTER.com/ICAF_org
           in classrooms worldwide in 2017, the Arts   ICAF when you purchase from Amazon    INSTAGRAM @intlchildartfoundation
     ChildArt | April-June 2017 ChildArt | April-June 2017  Children’s Festival in 2019, and culminates     International Child Art Foundation   EMAIL childart@icaf.org
           Olympiad leads to community celebrations
                                              or eBay, donate through JustGive.org
           in 2018, followed by the 6th World
                                              or mail us a check at:
           in 2020 with a traveling exhibition of the
                                                                                  ONLINE www.icaf.org
                                              P.O. Box 58133
           winning artworks.
                                              Washington, DC 20037, USA
                                                                                  CALL  202.530.1000
           For more information, please visit:

  36       www.icaf.org/ArtsOlympiad/
  36]]></page></pages></Search>